<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Out-port-customers accompt, of all his receipts, to a shilling, or a penny, without concealement or enstaulement of any; according to his oath at his first admission. Wherein he plainely sets downe, as well the motiues and occasions, as the method and style of all his former writings ...</title>
            <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123346</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">68222460</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 68222460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183763</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07949)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183763)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2197:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Out-port-customers accompt, of all his receipts, to a shilling, or a penny, without concealement or enstaulement of any; according to his oath at his first admission. Wherein he plainely sets downe, as well the motiues and occasions, as the method and style of all his former writings ...</title>
                  <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[63] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Jaggard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer and date from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Head-piece, initial.</note>
                  <note>Contains ms. notes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹ B-P² Q³</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Columbia University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Commerce --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183763:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183763:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN OVT-PORT-CVSTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MERS ACCOMPT, Of all his Receipts, to a Shilling, or a Penny, without concealement or enſtaulement of any; according to his Oath at his firſt Admiſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein he plainely ſets downe, as well the</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues and Occaſions, as the Method and Style of all his former writings; namely, his firſt APOLOGY for CVSTOMERS, againſt Informers of all ſorts. His REPLY, or ſecond APOLOGY for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Traffique, againſt Priuate Societies. His CAVTION for Subſidies, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of Cuſtomes, againſt Extreamity by Farmers. His ALPHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BET and PRYMER for orderly Commerce. His ACROAMATA for Bullion and Staples: Beſides his late MYSTERY of INIQVITIE. ¶ All which, howſoeuer heeretofore held hard and <hi>obſcure; are heere out of Rules of Diuinity, and Humanity together, by way of Illustration, fitted to Capacity of Common Senſe and Reaſon; for the fuller ſatisfaction of all vnpartiall Readers, fearing</hi> GOD <hi>ſincerely, and vprightly ſeruing</hi> KINGS, <hi>and ſuch as are not deſperately wilfull, to make Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of their Conſciences, and dispiſe their owne Happineſſe.</hi> With an open Declaration of the MYSTERY itſelfe, to perfect this Accompt. <hi>Summa Totalis.</hi> The CVSTOMERS Reſolution. <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Summarum,</hi> His daily Confeſſion, Harty Prayer with Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing; and QVIETVS-EST. ¶ And a ſhort <hi>Memorandum,</hi> in <hi>Perpetuam Rei Memoriam,</hi> for the KINGS ſpeciall Honor, his Loyall <hi>Subiects</hi> Good, and his CVSTOMERS diſcharge, from all Imputations both paſt and to come, againſt <hi>Ignorance</hi> and her Fellowes.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ PSALME 37.</bibl>
               <p>Keepe Innocency, and take heede vnto the Thing that is Right, for that ſhall bring a Man PEACE at the laſt.</p>
               <bibl>¶ OR THVS.</bibl>
               <p>Marke the Perfect Man, and behold the vpright, for the End of that Man is PEACE. <hi>Dilige quae Bona ſunt, Rectum cole, Iuſta require; Haec faciens, alma</hi> PACE <hi>beatus eris.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:183763:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183763:2"/>
            <head>THE CVSTOMERS ACCOMPT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE number is but ſmall, at leaſt not very great, of Men that are ſo ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and weake of Iudgement, but general Inconueniences they reade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, and can eaſily diſcerne. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, to finde out the Groundes of publike harmes, and the means how to cure them, is a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſo intricat, and a practiſe ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, that wary men hold it ſafer to prouide for priuate eaſe, in regard of the Times, then to buſie their wits for any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Good.</p>
            <p>But how aduiſed ſoeuer, and reſpectiuely wiſe in this kind, the moſt ſort ſeeme to be, as wiſhing onely that all might goe well, though not long of themſelues: yet few or none are found of ſo ſtill a temper as not to complaine, when publique greefes worke their owne ſenſible ſmarts.</p>
            <p>Such then, as by long and extraordinary patience, ſupping vp their priuate wrongs, haue endeuoured to giue way to the ſtreame of publique Contumelies, in hope of better dayes; muſt needs be excuſed, if compeld at the laſt (by lawleſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity) to referre euents to GODS Prouidence, in diſcharge of their Duties to HIM, their PRINCE, and COVNTREY, they vndertake the Defence of their owne Reputations, in a Cauſe publike and generall. The rather, when as without purpoſe of offending any, their intentions appeare to yeelde onely a reaſon of ſuch and ſuch Diſorders in their owne preſent Functions, as for want of ſerious inſpection, or true informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, haue hitherto by Ielouſie and miſconceit onely, yeelded matter and occaſions of their ſpeciall Diſgraces and Obloquy.</p>
            <p>Euen ſuch and none other, haue the Drifts and Scopes been of all my former Writings, about <hi>Traffique</hi> and her Tributes, by the generall Name of <hi>Customes.</hi> For hauing ſpent and
<pb facs="tcp:183763:3"/>
conſumed the beſt part of my youth about publique Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as well at home as abroad, in FRANCE, FLANDERS, and SCOTLAND, for ſixteene years together; after the TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY that was ended at <hi>Barwicke,</hi> 1586. betweene the late Queen ELIZABETH, of moſt happy Memory, and our now dread Soueraigne IAMES; (cal'd <hi>Foedus arctioris Amicitiae inter Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiſſimos, &amp;c.</hi> The RECORD whereof in <hi>Scotland</hi> remains of my hand) which by the Goodneſſe of God, the truth of his Title, and his owne Patience together, was a ſpeciall meanes, that at laſt brought his Maieſty ſo happily among vs, and ſo quietly hither: deſirous to betake me to ſome ſtaid courſe of life; I was by Friendes perſwaded to become CVSTOMER of <hi>Sandwich,</hi> with the Member-Ports belonging, within the ſhire of KENT, where I was both bred and born, aſſuring me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that I might thereby, do GOD, my SOVERAIGNE, and my COVNTRY ſpeciall ſeruice, and ſo become <hi>Happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Happineſſe</hi> indeede being that eſtate of life, which all at leaſt wiſh for, and by all meanes belay, and the obiects of all <hi>Happineſſe</hi> being fixt in GOD and KINGS; by ſeruing KINGS Loyallie, Men hope to be happy, and ſo did I. Vpon which Motiue (therefore) being vrged ſo by Friends, I vndertooke the charge <hi>Simply,</hi> and <hi>doubted no harme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But GOD becomes abuſed, and KINGS may be deceiued, and ſo was I, and ſo become many, that ſeeke after <hi>Happineſſe</hi> by collecting <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> (in the Out-Ports at leaſt) as the caſe now ſtands. For the ſeruice being pretended and attended on by many, each values himſelfe aboue other, and his Place and ſtanding to be of moſt importance. But <hi>Multa ſunt quae non videntur, &amp; Multa videntur quae non ſunt omnino.</hi> For <hi>Customes</hi> indeed, and properly taken (like the Tithes of a Church, and <hi>Quitrents</hi> of a Mannor) being naturall Effects of that weighty Cauſe (TRAFFIQVE) whoſe Actions are conuerſant, about no meaner Obiectes, then <hi>Soueraignes</hi> Honour, and <hi>Subiects</hi> Wealth, and as due to Kings as the Crowne on their heades; imply a ſeruice both of ſpeciall reſpect, and abſolute truſt; wherein foure things there are, or ought to be concurrent, to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> enable the <hi>Customer,</hi> and iuſtifie his calling. Firſt, the <hi>Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that giues power to receiue the Duties of that kind. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the <hi>Ports</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> laide out and allotted for the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> bounds of his Function. Thirdly, Faithfull performance, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the exigence and importance of his charge: And <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> fourthly, <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> fit for ſuch a calling.</p>
            <p>All this notwithſtanding, I was no ſooner entred, but I found my ſelfe ſurpriſde; my former Liberty, turn'd into Thraldome, like the Bondage of <hi>Aegipt;</hi> and my Life become ſubiect to the Inquiſition of <hi>Spaine.</hi> For Ielouſie and Suſpition
<pb facs="tcp:183763:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
firſt bound me hand and foote, and ſwearing mee withall <hi>To do my beſt endeuor, to deale iustly and vprightly between the Prince and the People,</hi> ſent mee to my charge in thoſe <hi>Deſerts</hi> and <hi>Plaines,</hi> next the Wilderneſſe of <hi>Sin,</hi> and great FORREST OF SHIFTS; Namely, to SANDVVICH, with the Members; as <hi>Douer, Feuerſham, Milton,</hi> and <hi>Rochester,</hi> within the Shire of <hi>Kent.</hi> Where for my comfort, I found and might diſcerne, (which I could not ſee before) how <hi>Trafficke</hi> (on whom our work depends) hang'd awry, went backward &amp; forward as one that were bewitcht, and depriu'd of all her <hi>Cordials Cata-Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, Cat'auto,</hi> and <hi>Cath'olou-proton,</hi> was ſubiect to ſwooning, and often in a trance, her Face pale and wan, her Pulſes dull and dead, and all for want of <hi>Staples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her <hi>Ports</hi> either abandond, like places infected or haunted with Spirits, or elſe beſet with <hi>Harpies</hi> by Sea and by Land, to worry her from thence, if by chance ſhe came thither.</p>
            <p>Her <hi>Houſes</hi> neither Wind-tight, nor Water-tight, were ſtuft with ſuch Inſtruments as lou'd her Cuſtomes, but as Rats doe loue Cheeſe.</p>
            <p>And for all the Security (by Bondes or otherwiſe) that an honeſt Man can giue, a Chriſtian may affoord, or Wiſedome deuiſe:
<q>
                  <l>Her <hi>Seruants</hi> ſtill miſtruſted, and made Obiects of Diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Bewrayed their ſmall maintenance by the thinneſſe of their Cheekes:</l>
                  <l>And their Seruice made a meanes to fat others in their place,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt they dranke cold Water, and were glad to leape at Leekes.</l>
               </q>
In a word, I ſaw <hi>Traffique</hi> out of Order.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Yet I could not maruell tho,</l>
               <l>For all on priuate profit waite,</l>
               <l>Where Proiects guided by conceit,</l>
               <l>Made worke for <hi>Seeming-Goods</hi> deceit;</l>
               <l>And one Mans will, made all Mens wo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This made mee to rub where it did not itch before, and ſmothering vp my greefe, to wiſh as others did;
<q>O mihi praeteritos referat ſi Iupiter annos!</q>
            </p>
            <p>But, beeing thus a <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> in Name, at the leaſt, and apt enough to learne, though not able yet to teach; I ſpent the firſt two yeares in obſeruing of others, and bemoand my ſelfe by fits, as I durſt vpon occaſions, by words and writings: firſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our <hi>Huſhers,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">I bemoand the Diſorders of the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> ſeruices, and <hi>Out-Port-Cuſtomers</hi> Diſtreſſe, to Mayſter <hi>Thomas Fanſhawe Eſquire,</hi> then <hi>Remembrancer</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> to whoſe Study and Table I was often kindly welcome, firſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately by conference, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by writing, who ſhewed the ſame to the Lorde cheefe <hi>Baron Peryam,</hi> and He to the Lord <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer Burghley,</hi> but nothing came of it, which made me at laſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to the COVNSEL-TABLE.</note> and then by conſtraint, in a ſerious ſet diſcourſe of the preſent eſtate of <hi>Customes,</hi> in the Out-Portes of this Land, not ſo publikely then printed, as priuately directed, <hi>To the Graueſt, and Godly wiſe, in higheſt authority:</hi> by the Title &amp; Inſcription of THE CVSTOMERS APOLOGY, in theſe words following.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:4"/>
               <note place="margin">The Epiſtle of the APOLOGY.</note> ¶ A GENTLEMAN, a Friend, and a Louer of Learning, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into a Free-Schoole, where diuers young Schollers were learning their Grammers, deſirous to feele how they thriud at their Bookes, by ſome familiar queſtion, demaunded (their <hi>Huſhers</hi> ſtanding by) <hi>When an Engliſh is giuen to bee made into Latine, what's firſt to be done?</hi> The aunſwere is eaſie; Namely, To looke out the principall <hi>Verbe,</hi> but all ſtood ſilent, and as halfe amaz'd, till ONE at the laſt, the queſtion being repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and he vrged to ſpeake, what was to be done, replyed: <hi>No harme Sir I hope, at leaſt that I wot of.</hi> Which the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman then took in very good part, &amp; ſuſpecting rather Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the <hi>Huſhers,</hi> then want of wit in the Scholler, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſmiling.</p>
            <p>¶ Moſt Reuerend and Right Honourable; This Queſtion and Anſwere, encludeth the State of all the Students in the <hi>Free-Schooles</hi> and <hi>Portes</hi> of our <hi>Soueraignes Cuſtomes,</hi> where ſuch as the Teachers be, ſuch are the Schollers. Ther's a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for all things: And the reaſon heereof is not ſo much for want of wit or will in the Learners, <hi>to deale iuſtly betweene the Prince and the People;</hi> Which in this kinde of Doctrine is the principall <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbe,</hi> as in the ſternneſſe of <hi>Huſhers,</hi> who whilſt the <hi>Graue Maiſters</hi> and <hi>Moderators</hi> of the Schooles, were buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſtracted in the ſtudy and practiſe of higher points of Learning, haue vſed no Method but beating the Schollers:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qui paria eſſe volunt peccata, Ipſi<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> laborant</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cùm ventum ad verum est, ſenſus moreſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> repugnant,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ipſa Vtilitas, Iusti propè Mater &amp; Aequi.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That make all faults alike, yet they themſelues are domme,</l>
                     <l>When Truth in queſtion fals, each Fingers ſeemes a Thomme:</l>
                     <l>And Profit holds the Seat alone, where Honour firſt ſhould come.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which kind of Diſcipline, diſcouraging all Men, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing many good wits from the Schoole, to the ſecret iniury of the whole <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> for'ſt me to my Booke, and as well as I could, to analize my Leſſon, meaning thereby with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid plaine Scholler; <hi>No harme at all.</hi> Such therefore as it is, I haue breefely ſet downe in the Diſcourſe following. The <hi>Matter</hi> whereof, partly drawn from mine owne Patience and Experience: and partly, obſerued and learned from others: The <hi>Forme</hi> (I confeſſe) is meerly mine owne, and hath for my warrant, the Rules of my <hi>Grammer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince things are then well done, when thinges are well taken. To cleere and acquit me from partiall clamor, and the ſinne of <hi>Preſumption:</hi> The will applyant to reaſon, is guiltleſſe of paſſion, and Nature ouer-borne, appeales to neceſſity. <hi>Quae quòd cogit ipſa, ſolet vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> defendere.</hi> Hard therefore, and aboue
<pb facs="tcp:183763:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
meaſure extreame muſt their caſes appeare, that ſtill ſubiect to beating, may neither bemoane themſelues, nor be ſuffered to cry. And ſo much the rather, when as <hi>So farre as I wot of,</hi> in all their complaints ſo tenderly toucht, and breefely runne ouer, there is nothing concluded nor included, at leaſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereby, but a naturall Defence of an honeſt Reputation, in that kind of calling, which the Law it ſelfe in great Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath laide out and reſerued; <hi>For Men of beſt ſort onely,</hi> and a dutifull zeale to finde out thereby <hi>The Principall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>But,</hi> Pro captu Lectoris habent ſua fata Libelli.</q>
            <p>I ſought to finde comfort, and light vpon new comber; For the APOLOGY being written for vnderſtanding Readers, and the <hi>Matter</hi> ſo digeſted, that by reading it onely without <hi>Gloſſe</hi> or <hi>Comment, Paſſion</hi> or <hi>Partiality,</hi> ſuch might be their own &amp; other Mens Iudges, was notwithſtanding by <hi>Ignorance</hi> oddely cenſured,<note place="margin">The APOLOGY ſtrangely cenſured by Ignorance.</note> and ſtrangely miſtaken, Vainely ſtriuing to make good that within Book which neuer was in queſtion, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly vrging ſome things without Booke, neuer meant nor mentioned, nor fit to be defended. But with ſuch ſucceſſe as ſtill befals folly, who delighting to ſee her owne ſhaddowe dance, hath not the grace to conceale her owne ſhame. I ſet but lightly by it when the thing was firſt brought me, till I ſaw the Booke twice printed at MIDLEBOROVGH &amp; LONDON, then leaſt he that ranne alone, might thinke himſelfe ſtill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt; I was for'ſt to ſay ſomething, and <hi>Replyed</hi> in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.<note place="margin">The Motiue and occaſion of the REPLY.</note>
            </p>
            <p>¶ About ſuch time, is by the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of GOD,<note place="margin">The Method and Style of the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> REPLY.</note> the light of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> began to lay open the errors of Superſtition in theſe parts of the World, and by the hands of our <hi>Soueraignes,</hi> to diſperſe them in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſundry queſtions were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to vphold ſome points of the <hi>Popiſh Religion,</hi> but none for the time were ſo hotly diſputed, as thoſe which they tearme, <hi>The Sacrament of the Altar, and praying to Saints.</hi> Whereof, amongſt others, a certaine young Scholler, more confident then wiſe, hauing newly vndertaken a ſerious Defence; as one ſicke of loue with the thing he had begotten, and ambitiouſly affecting the publiſhing of it, entreated a Friend of his, whom he knew to be both learned and well minded to the Cauſe to read it firſt ouer. The requeſt was performed; but when as looking ſtill for Arguments fitting the queſtion, he found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all but a needleſſe endeuour, to approoue and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by the Catholike Creede. What? <hi>That</hi> IESVS CHRIST <hi>was the true Sonne of God, very God, and very Man, that redeemed the World,</hi> and <hi>That there was alſo a Communion of Saints:</hi> The Booke was return'd with a ſlender ſmile, but no applaud at all, or ſhew of ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Right Honorable, ſuch was the ſucceſſe of a like late lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Writer, who Printing a <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>publique Commerce,</hi> (ſuch was his Title) in fauour of a priuate ſociety, or <hi>Conclaue</hi> of <hi>Marchants,</hi> with very much ado, and a heape of ſilly words, (farre vnfitting the Grauity of his Theame) ſet all his wit to worke, and endeuour'd all he could, to perſwade his Reader. What? That <hi>Traffique,</hi> forſooth, rightly ordered, was the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Kings,</hi> and Proſperity of <hi>Kingdomes;</hi> and withall, that <hi>Trades</hi> and <hi>Occupations, Arts</hi> and <hi>Mysteries,</hi> were at al hands to bee cherriſhed, and <hi>Marchants</hi> likewiſe fauour'd in euery <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> which none but Fooles or mad men (to my vnderſtanding) did euer yet deny.</p>
            <p>But it's ſtrange to obſerue, what ſtrong apprehenſions are able to worke in weake mens braines. For as a plaine ſimple Man in reading his <hi>Beleefe,</hi> was ſometimes perſwaded, that if <hi>Pontius Pylate</hi> had not beene a Saint, the Apoſtles would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue ſuffered his Name to ſtand in the Creede: ſo this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Writer, reading in a <note n="*" place="margin">This Treatiſe was written by one of <hi>Embden,</hi> 1564. about the beginning of the Diuiſions of the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and Colloquy of <hi>Bruges,</hi> to ſhew the <hi>Emperor</hi> and <hi>P P.</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> the great aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> then had ouer all Chriſtendome, by the <hi>Load-ſtones</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſtill tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported thither, earneſtly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the fitneſſe of the time, and happy occaſion then offered, to drawe them from <hi>Antwarp</hi> to <hi>Embden,</hi> for the good of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</hi> All which Maiſter <hi>Wheeler, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary</hi> to the <hi>Marchant Aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Commerce,</hi> ſeemes to make his owne <hi>(Sic vos non vobis)</hi> and leauing the Matter, admires onely the Men, and fals downe before the Perſons, that for their priuate profit tranſport them ſtill ouer, and would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the World to commit the like Idolatry.</note> 
               <hi>Treatiſe</hi> by a Stranger, long ſince written, a full diſcourſe at large, of the Golden bliſſings of ENGLAND; turning <hi>Creekes</hi> into <hi>Portes,</hi> ioyning <hi>Ports</hi> vnto <hi>Townes,</hi> raiſing <hi>Towns</hi> into <hi>Citties,</hi> and enriching whole <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries</hi> with <hi>Artificers</hi> and <hi>Trades, Marriners</hi> and <hi>Shipping,</hi> whereſoeuer they became: in the ſtrength of his conceit (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Pride</hi> bewitcht with <hi>Couetiſe,</hi> and puft vp with flattery) would beare the world in hand, that the life of all our <hi>Trafficke</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> of GREAT BRITTAINE, ſtood wholely or cheefely, by the ſtanding and ſupporting of his priuate Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Applauding their <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> beſides by their mannaging of <hi>Traffick</hi> within themſelues, commending their diſpoſing, mincing, abridging, reſtraining, ſwearing, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining the ſtore and <hi>Staples</hi> thereof, (not ſhewing <hi>Cui Bono</hi>) within the wals of Places out of ſight, beyond Seas coloured with the Title of their ſpeciall <hi>Mart-Townes.</hi> And aboue all, extolling their excellent wits and abſolute cunning, in moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Lawes by meere Diſcretion, to hold all men vnder, and themſelues ſtill aboue. For ſending, or ſayling but croſſe the narrow Seas, without hazzard of Gods, or danger of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons more then vſuall or ordinary. And for wearing Chaines of Gold about their Neckes, Cappes with Greene Feathers, Hats with white Feathers, Purple Veluet Buskins, Guilt Rapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Daggers, Bridles, and Spurres, at Triumphs beyond Seas, and publike meetings there: But cheefely, for feeding, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, and ſetting to worke, thouſands of Strangers there, when God knowes the wants, and hears the cryes of <hi>Myriades</hi> for idleneſſe at home; would faine perſwade others (beeing bound to admire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe) that their PONTIVS or <hi>Gouernor,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:5"/>
was for skil the PILAT, for Grauity the POPE, and for wiſdome the Oracle of all orderly <hi>Commerce.</hi> Their priuate Decrees, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Common Lawes at home, or Treatiſes abroad. Their particular <hi>Synodes,</hi> aboue Generall Counſels, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claue or Company, a Communion of Saints: pronouncing al that withſtand, diſtaſt or diſlike their Doctrine, or contemne their Diſcipline, for ENTERLOPERS; that's to ſay, <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, Schiſmatickes,</hi> and excommunicated Perſons, not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to breath ſo much as common Ayre, or liue in any well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi> Concluding at laſt thus ſtrongly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. That theſe Men thus put in ſpeciall truſt, with the tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Credit of our Kingdome, the very Creame of our Land, and cheefeſt of our <hi>Load-stones,</hi> whereby wee ſhould draw <hi>Bullion</hi> (CLOATH) muſt needes be reputed, more loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to their <hi>Soueraignes,</hi> more ſeruiceable to the <hi>State,</hi> more welcome to our Neighbours; and therefore more to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then any other men (bee they neuer ſo Free-borne) with a Name aboue all Names, of MARCHANT-ADVENTVRERS.</p>
            <p>With this and ſuch like ſtuffe, the Booke being confuſedlie fraught. <hi>Cuius contrarium veriſſimum est;</hi> might wel haue been ſuffered to haue dyde in the Birth, had it not beene mingled with aſperſions of vntruthes, and Obloquies withall, againſt the poore <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> of the <hi>Out-Ports</hi> of this Realme. <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers!</hi> A kind of Creatures, capable as well of Religion as Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Free-men</hi> by birth, and of beſt education, Men euery way happy, ſaue in their Names and Calling, and in nothing more wretched, then in the place of their <hi>Functions.</hi> The <hi>Out-Ports</hi> of this Realme. O thrice happy LONDON! Men (I ſay) that by the curious eye of the Lawe, choſen of the beſt and moſt ſufficient that Wiſedome can finde, or choyce affoord, would faine retaine the reputation, if not of <hi>Saints,</hi> yet of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> at leaſt, and plaine honeſt men.</p>
            <p>But as Men once ſuſpected, are ſaid to be halfe hang'd, ſo fares it with <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> for with them aboue all men, it is not enough to be an honeſt man. Leauing therefore mine <hi>Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt,</hi> to beleeue ſtill in the <hi>Chriſtian Catholique</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolique</hi> Creede, whoſe Articles aſſuredly, are holy all, and true, though PONTIVS PILATS name ſtand for no Saint. I ſent the reſt to the Story of ISIS, whoſe Image of Gold it was, that Men ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired in all Places where it came, and not the beauty of the Beaſt that bare it; and ploughing with a <hi>Heyſer</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1564. At, or about the time of the <hi>Colloquy</hi> of <hi>Bruges,</hi> A <hi>Marchant Aduenturer,</hi> to enforme the State at home, of the grounds of ſuch Diſorders in the matter of <hi>Traffick,</hi> as then the world was diſquieted withal; out of Conſcience and Duty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray'd the practiſes, and aduantages of that Company by <hi>Vſury,</hi> which they ſtill call <hi>Exchange.</hi> A Coppy of whoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe lying by me, I ioyn'd to my <hi>Reply,</hi> without adding or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, ſaue onely the <hi>Praeface</hi> or <hi>Introduction,</hi> and <hi>Epilogue</hi> or <hi>Concluſion,</hi> to help out the Method, and giuing it a Title which it had not before.</note> that had ſometimes beene their owne. I anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> with a <hi>Counter-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,</hi> of <hi>Exchange</hi> in <hi>Marchandize,</hi> and <hi>Marchandizing Exchange,</hi> wherein
<pb facs="tcp:183763:6"/>
was laid open by plaine Demonſtration, the <hi>Canker</hi> of <hi>Traffick,</hi> and all mutuall Commerce: I ſay, an open Detection of that Contempt of <hi>Law,</hi> Diſdaine of <hi>Equity,</hi> Scorne of <hi>Soueraignty,</hi> and Diſhonor of <hi>Kings.</hi> And a liuely Deſcription of that Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Creete</hi> (VSVRY) deuouring by daily, monthly, and yearely <hi>Tributes,</hi> the Bodies of Men, and Soules of Chriſtians, his Hatching and Brood, his Muces and Hauntes, his practiſe and ſhifts, his ſhape and his Name, by the Title of <hi>Marchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Exchange.</hi> The Labyrinth of whoſe inextricable Errors, none may ſafely enter, and whoſe Perſon none can encounter and quell but fatall THESEVS, aſſiſted by the thred of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, and counſell of ARYADNE. A diſcourſe proiected to giue light vnto others, but happily reſerued by the prouidence of GOD, to honour our AEGEVS, to preſerue our THESEVS, and bliſſe our daies withall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> became firſt engaged and prouoked to Apologiſe for <hi>Trafficke,</hi> as well as for <hi>Cuſtomers.</hi>
               </note>For <hi>Traffique</hi> by this meanes, as wel as for <hi>Customers,</hi> being formerly bound, then thus prouoked and drawne on by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; I became at laſt confident and bold to contend, the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing whereof, like Honny in Hiues, encreaſeth <hi>Customes.</hi> But not that <hi>Traffique</hi> forſooth, which he childiſhly deſcrib'd, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring Pointes for Pinnes, or Goſſiping with Women. Nor that <hi>Traffique,</hi> which to Fodder vs with Folly, or to fat vs vp with Pride, brings Toyes and TOBACCO, little Bels and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Hawkes-Hoods and Hobby Horſes, together with Silks and Veluets, Cambricks and Lawnes, for our better Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, of <hi>Wooll, Wooll-felles,</hi> and <hi>Cloath, Tinne, Lead,</hi> and <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> deſtined for <hi>Bullion.</hi> But that <hi>Traffique,</hi> which euery way ſubſiſting of <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> both in Number, Weight, and Meaſure, by turning all our <hi>Load-stones</hi> into fine <hi>Siluer</hi> and pure <hi>Gold,</hi> makes <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes</hi> happy. Which when I came to view, and withall to conſider, how like a Coach diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered ſhe hung at one ſide: ſeeing AEGEVS with his ISIS, and our THESEVS his Sonne, the hope of our happineſſe, with all the Royall Iſſue, ſitting cloſe therein together; my heart began to fall, and my haire to riſe. For <hi>Traffique</hi> beeing the Chariot that beares our GLORIOVS LIGHTS; I found her Harneſſe worne, and her Wheeles diſpla'ſt. The ſtrong Spokes of CVSTOMES ſupplyd with weake <hi>Subſidies</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage,</hi> and thoſe likewiſe lin'd with ITALIAN <hi>Impoſitions.</hi> And perceiuing a far off a certain kind of Horſe-men,<note place="margin">The Motiue and occaſion of the CAVTION.</note> like the foure Sons of AYMON, or the <hi>Mynotaure</hi> of CREETE, then proudly ſetting forward, from the <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> and FORREST OF SHIFTS, to bound ouer our <hi>Deſerts,</hi> and vndertake her at aduenture out of order as ſhee was, and draw vs all in Tryumph: I could not but cry out. And ſeeing as I did, (my ſtanding made me ſee, and my ſeeing moou'd my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:183763:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not to hold my peace) both the looſeneſſe of their raines, their bits within their teeth, the dangers of their courſe, ouer Hils and Dales, Bawkes, and many By-waies, and all without a Coach-man or Guide that I could ſpy, (they out-running al, and controleable by none for hindring of their courſe) I could not I ſay, out of <hi>Duty, Feare,</hi> and <hi>Zeale,</hi> to our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> ſpeciall ſafety, and all our happy beings, but giue CAVTION afore hand of the fierceneſſe of their Courage and deſperate Carrier, that they that then ſtood nigh them might be warn'd at leaſt to looke but to their heeles.</p>
            <p>For there being but two maine <hi>Subſidies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Method and Style of the CAVTION.</note> which <hi>Loue</hi> was deſirous that <hi>Loyaltie</hi> ſhould offer by way of humble preſents, to honour our <hi>Soueraigne</hi> with, at his firſt comming hither, (beſides his <hi>Customes,</hi> which as tyde vnto this Crowne, were his owne before;) namely, the <hi>Subſidie</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> and that of <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Goods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt (vſually miſtermed by the generall Name of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes</hi>) are thoſe ſpeciall tokens of affectionate Loue, which <hi>Marchants</hi> freely giue, and humbly preſent to MAIESTY, and none other, for maintenance of the Nauy, and ſafe paſſage at Seas. The other likewiſe, tokens and franke offerings of <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty,</hi> from <hi>Subiects</hi> to their <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> for maintenance of <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty,</hi> and <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both theſe twins of one birth, borne vnder one <hi>Law,</hi> nam'd at one <hi>Font,</hi> knowing no Motiue but <hi>Loue,</hi> no Mould but <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty,</hi> no Obiect but <hi>Royalty,</hi> no vſe but <hi>Equity,</hi> no Ends but the ſafety of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> without difference at all ſaue onely this. That the firſt by <hi>Parliament</hi> is for tearme of life giuen him once for all. The ſecond by <hi>Parliaments,</hi> are vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally renewed.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this one being of both, and one kinde of beginning: yet in their ſeuerall Collections, to the wonder of God and Angels, they are made ſo to differ, that the firſt ſeemes meerely ſeruile and ſubiect to bondage: The ſecond, Free-borne.<note place="margin">This point alone but ſeriouſly weyghed, would rectifie all Diſorder in Cuſtome-ſeruice, and quit <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> from diſgrace and blame.</note> The firſt, expoſde to all kind of <hi>Extreamities,</hi> and thereby put to <hi>Shifts:</hi> The other, maintainde by <hi>Mercy, Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty,</hi> and <hi>Loue.</hi> In the one, the leaſt part or ſhred of each mans <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Goods,</hi> is held ſufficient. In the <hi>Marchandize</hi> of the other, all, &amp; in ſome things more then all, is not held enough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Laſtly, the firſt, a diſturbance to the <hi>Marchant,</hi> and <hi>Customers</hi> Diſgrace. The ſecond, a daily credit and countenance to all her <hi>Receiuers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, great hath beene the care indeede, and inuentions ſundry that haue beene vndertaken, for the aduancing, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and true anſwering, euen of theſe very <hi>Subſidies</hi> of <hi>Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> and <hi>Pondage,</hi> as well as of <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> but the Collections
<pb facs="tcp:183763:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of either being euery way diſordered, and the wordes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues miſtaken; the one for the other, Moule-hils become Mountaines, and Complaints beget Complaints, to the <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> daily cumber, diſgrace, and onely blame. Who beeing bound hands and feet by Ielouſie and Suſpition (without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing any, for that was the Deuils part euen from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) plead onely for themſelues, but the Law of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Quod imputari non debet ei per que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non ſtat ſi non facit quod per ipſum est faciendum,</hi> whoſe reaſon goes withall, That <hi>Culpa careat oportet, qui ſcit &amp; prohibere nequit:</hi> Yet are ſo far withal from iuſtifying themſelues, &amp; excuſing of others, that they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly confeſſe. Faults there are, euer were, and euer will be many. <hi>Perfection</hi> knowes no Reſidence but <hi>Heauen,</hi> diſclaimes priuate directions in publique affaires, diſtruſt their owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and therefore cries alowde as they may, dare, or can, but ADSIT REGVLA.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">HORACE.</note>,,For <hi>Haud Natura poteſt Iuſto ſecernere Iniquum, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It is not in <hi>Diſcretions</hi> hand, nor power to ſtay,</l>
               <l>Or hold the tickle Scales of <hi>Iuſtiec</hi> ſtill vpright:</l>
               <l>Nor is that <hi>Reaſon</hi> good, that mak'ſt all one by day,</l>
               <l>To crop a Neighbours Garden-Leekes, and rob a Church by night.</l>
               <l>ARVLE muſt guide the whole, to keepe the parts from ſwaruing,</l>
               <l>And puniſh faults in euery one, according to deſeruing.</l>
               <l>And not to thinke that euery ſlip,</l>
               <l>Like deadly Sinne deſerues a whip.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Beſides, their <hi>Helpers</hi> are their <hi>Hinderers:</hi> For their <hi>Searchers</hi> being no Saints, as they cannot liue by the Ayre, ſo they know not how to fiſh but in pudled Waters. Their <hi>Comptrollers</hi> know no <hi>Rules,</hi> but <hi>Actum agere.</hi> And their violent <hi>Superuiſors,</hi> crying <hi>Halfers</hi> were good <hi>Fiſhers,</hi> like confident <hi>Empirickes,</hi> with repercuſſiue Medicines ſo tormented poore <hi>Traffique,</hi> that dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing her at laſt, from the <hi>Lyme-kill</hi> to the <hi>Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-pit;</hi> it grew to be a queſtion, to Farme out her <hi>Subſidies</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> together with her <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi> A ſtrange kinde of Playſter for Sores of this Nature; as if <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Loue</hi> were thinges transferrent, from that Royall <hi>Preheminence,</hi> that giues it Life and being, and the <hi>Homage</hi> of <hi>Subiects,</hi> and honour of <hi>Kings,</hi> were vendible for <hi>Money,</hi> or fit for <hi>Farmers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though other Kingdomes doe the like, as ſome obiect and ſay; <hi>England</hi> liues by Lawes. Examples may illuſtrate, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude no neceſſity of generall imitation. For Gouernments are diuers, ſome better, and ſome worſe, and <hi>England</hi> with the beſt, may rather giue then take example; <hi>Et praeſtat legibus obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire <add>quod amodo Iniquis,</add> quàm viro bono quantumuis optimo,</hi> ſince one mans will may be all mens woe.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if <hi>Reformation</hi> ſpeede beſt in looking backward, al men may know, that it was not thus with <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> from the
<pb facs="tcp:183763:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
beginning, to be ſubiect to blame for their owne ſinnes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, till creeping <hi>Caterpillers,</hi> blowne in by Eaſterne-winds, and whiſpering <hi>Informers,</hi> bred vp in muddy waters, were che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht and maintain'd, whom <hi>Wiſedome</hi> in all ages ſtill ſhund or deſtroyd. And I ſhew'd a plaine example, not yet by all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, that there was a time, when a Creature of this crew, to curry fauour with a worthy Lorde TREASVROVR,<note place="margin">The Lorde <hi>Treaſurer Paulet,</hi> in whoſe daies if a <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> comming vp to the Tearme, had not dynde or ſupt with him before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, he had been ſure of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuant</hi> to fetch him vp againe. And a <hi>Marchants</hi> Bond or Bill, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowd in his Accompt, as any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Money.</note> came fraighted with complaints againſt the <hi>Towne</hi> and <hi>Port</hi> of SANDVVICH, for tranſportation and dealings there, laying his complaints cheefely vppon Packes of Cloath and Beere, wherein as he conceiued, the <hi>Prince</hi> was much abuſed. The Tale being told, and heard out to the end, the <hi>Relator</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded whence, and what he was, who anſwered; A <hi>Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> but no <hi>Marchant</hi> at all. What makes thee (quoth his L.) to ſee ſo farre of, and ſo skild in <hi>Marchants</hi> cauſes? The <hi>Princes</hi> ſeruice (quoth the <hi>Fellow</hi>) and the meanes that I haue to know the doings there. His L. ſeeing his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence vpon theſe two grounds, deſcends to particulars, and firſt deſires to know of him, how, and whereof the <hi>Sandwich</hi> Beere was made.<note place="margin">The Riuer of <hi>Delf</hi> running through <hi>Sandwich.</hi>
               </note> Who readely could deſcribe the running ſtreame that ſerues the Townes vſe, and maintaines the <hi>Hauen</hi> there. When they Brew not (quoth his L.) whether runnes that Water? Into the Sea (quoth the <hi>Fellow?</hi>) And what make they then of it? Nothing. And Brew they, or Brew they not, they want no Water? No my Lord (quoth <hi>He</hi>) for the ſtreame euer running, keepes the Riuer full. So that (quoth his L.) the ſame Water, whoſe courſe is continuall, beeing Brewde, yeelds ſomething, and not brewde, nothing? Nothing (quoth <hi>He.</hi>) Why then in good faith (quoth his <hi>Honor</hi>) be thou rul'd by me, and let them boyle it on the Fire, and with a few Hops and ſome Malt, make ſomething of the water, bee it neuer ſo ſmall, for the leaſt ſomething that may be, is, and will be ſtill, better then nothing at all.</p>
            <p>Nowe for the Packes (quoth his L.) know'ſt thou whoſe they are? They belong (quoth <hi>He</hi>) to <hi>Marchants,</hi> that ſend them downe thither, but their Names I cannot tell. Are they ſimply their owne that ſend them to vent and diſpoſe? Yes my Lord (quoth <hi>He</hi>) before they be tranſported. Then though they bee ſhipped, if they croſſe not the Seas, the PRINCE hath no intereſt in them, nor profit by them? None at all (quoth the <hi>Fellow</hi>) for from <hi>Port</hi> to <hi>Port,</hi> both Land and Seas are free.</p>
            <p>Well then (quoth his L.) I perceiue a good meaning hath brought thee hither, but let me aduiſe thee in theſe <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> affaires, to let thinges alone, till eyther thou become a <hi>Sandwich-Brewer,</hi> ot a <hi>Portſman</hi> at leaſt, to know what it is to
<pb facs="tcp:183763:8"/>
be a good <hi>Townes-man</hi> at home where euer thou dwell, or till thou bee a <hi>Marchant</hi> thy ſelfe, that experience may tell thee what it is to ſeeke <hi>Marts</hi> and <hi>Markets</hi> abroad, and then I doubt not, but as others do, thou wilt be glad of a good peny-worth of that which being thine, to diſpoſe of is already thine owne.<note place="margin">The entertainement giuen by a Lorde <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> to an Informer, againſt a <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer</hi> of <hi>Sandwich.</hi>
               </note> And ſo being diſmiſt, he was wild firſt into the Seller, but from thence out of doores.</p>
            <p>Such was the regard in thoſe daies that was had of <hi>Whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> though now it be holden for beſt ſeruice to the State, to talke moſt of Errors, and diue deepeſt into <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> but many ſpeake of ROBIN-HOOD that neuer drew his BOW.</p>
            <p>And although the Farming of ſome fewe particulars that were let out already, might ſeeme but a miſcheefe of leſſer harme; yet harme more or leſſe, towards <hi>Soueraignes</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects</hi> make no Man happy, and therefore to be ſhund: but to Farme out all, was a publique inconuenience, ſo great in my conceit, as might worthily deſerue the wiſeſt preuention, which made me giue warning according to my place.</p>
            <p>For if <hi>Trafficke</hi> be truely cald the Nurce of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> wherein <hi>Soueraignes</hi> and <hi>Subiectes</hi> ſtand intereſt alike: ſo naturall is the Vnion of <hi>Religion</hi> with <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that the Farming out of <hi>Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> (effects of <hi>Trafficke</hi>) together with the <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> or guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them ouer with the Golden Name of <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> may fitlie be reſembled to the impropriating of religious offerings, by the Name of <hi>Tithes.</hi> The one due to none but to heauenly <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> The other alſo onely, to <hi>Soueraigne</hi> Princes. The one, a wrong to GOD, a ſtop to Religion, and a beggering of the Church; The other, a diſhonouring of <hi>Kings,</hi> a rub to <hi>Trifficke.</hi> and a meanes to impoueriſh <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and diſturbe <hi>Common-Weales.</hi> Howſoeuer, ſome few priuate, particular preuenting Perſons, perhaps may raiſe themſelues, &amp; by chance may thriue thereby.</p>
            <p>But to make all this more plaine. If the <hi>Subſidies</hi> aforeſaid, vpon <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Goods,</hi> were vrg'd to be collected; as <hi>Cardinall Woolſey</hi> once thought to prooue vpon the <hi>Cleargy,</hi> or expoſed out to <hi>Farmers</hi> by <hi>Hundreds, Lathes,</hi> or <hi>Shires,</hi> or generallie vndertaken, as <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage</hi> is, who ſhould collect it?<note place="margin">Read <hi>Hall</hi> and <hi>Stow</hi> in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 1526.</note> Or who were able to abide it? Yet for comparing theſe two together, and fore-warning miſchiefes at hand and to come, by the farming out of either; like the ſimple <hi>Satyre,</hi> that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sky-ſtolne fire from the Wheeles of this Chariot, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring it in loue, and but kiſſing it in kindneſſe, found it burnt his lippes, CASTOR miſinformed, and POLLAX being offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; I was gratiouſly chidden and ſhent for my labour: ſuch is the lot of <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> in this lower kind of <hi>Traffick</hi> &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Commerce,</hi> that in their beſt endeuours haue no hap to bee
<pb facs="tcp:183763:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
happy, but in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I hope for better. <hi>Non eſt mortale quòd opto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Thus farre forth, and in theſe very words, or to this effect at leaſt, hauing ſometimes vndertaken a priuate Defence in a Cauſe of importance, both publike and generall, and finding all my groanes and heauieſt complaints, to vaniſh ſtill like <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choes,</hi> and valued but as voyces in the <hi>Deſerts</hi> and <hi>Plaines,</hi> next the FORREST OF SHIFTS, the ſound whereof as moſt Men went by, they heard not; ſome heard, but vnderſtood not; ſome few perhaps vnderſtand, but regard not, and none ſeem'd to pitty. Like thoſe that broken with vnthankfull toyle, Seeke others health and happineſſe, and looſe their owne the while; I began to ſigh, and wiſh withall beſides,
<q>
                  <l>Si ie pouuoys renaiſtre,</l>
                  <l>Et changer tous mes voeux,</l>
                  <l>I' apprendroys meulx ma letre</l>
                  <l>Et ſerois bien-heureux.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But being as I was, I reſolued with my ſelfe, as a Barne ſo ding'd, that I durſt no longer greet, to giue way to the times, and ſup vp my greefe with ſilence.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, when I perceiued, that though I ſat ſtill, the cauſe it ſelfe daily did grow worſe and worſe; And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred withall, my vow to my <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and PATRON,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> are ſworne at their firſt admiſſions, to doe their beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, to deale iuſtly betweene the <hi>Prince</hi> and the <hi>People.</hi>
               </note> of our <hi>Schooles</hi> at my firſt admiſſion; in diſcharge of my Duty, which in that reſpect I owe to <hi>God,</hi> to my <hi>Prince,</hi> and Natiue <hi>Country:</hi> I once more reſolu'd to ſpeake with my Pen, and examine all my former Writings. Not as by way of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> to preſcribe a new Art to our <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Graue Maisters,</hi> for that had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in the higheſt degree, nor as by <hi>Analiſis</hi> to conteſt with the Method of our ſeuereſt <hi>Huſhers,</hi> for that had beene but humour and indiſcretion, but whilſt others of higher Formes, and farre better Learning, diſtruſting their Schooles, remoou'd their Seats to a farre ſurer ſtanding; as a poore Shol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, deſirous to learne and thriue by my Booke, to ſpell out my Leſſons, by the Letters of mine ALPHABET, and Lines of my PRYMER, that ſo at leaſt-wiſe redeeming but the time, I might beſt giue way to the ſtreame of Diſgraces, in hope of better daies in comming. Remembring ſtil withall, that Errors had no being but in abſence of <hi>Truth,</hi> and that howſoeuer Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors paſt had multiplyde themſelues, the ages ſucceeding muſt reforme as they may, and that as there was a reaſon, ſo GOD had appointed a time for all thinges. For <hi>Dies dat conſilium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſidering therefore the Reuolutions that were paſt,<note place="margin">The Motiue and occaſion of the ALPHABET and PRIMER.</note> and the preſent diſpoſition of theſe happy daies, by the comming of AEGEVS in our late ISIS place.<note place="margin">KING and PRINCE.</note> Our DAY-STAR beeing riſen, and the DAVVNING in our eyes receiu'd my dull Spirits,
<pb facs="tcp:183763:9"/>
gaue life to my hopes, and made me at laſt breath thus much &amp; ſay, that the time may come, when this hearty zeale of mine to my <hi>Soueraignes</hi> Honour, and his Peoples happineſſe might be better regarded, and the ages to come finde ſomething at leaſt, to muſe &amp; to maruaile at Ignorances paſt, when it ſhould plainely appeare, by demonſtratiue Reaſons, and no wandring Diſcourſe, that in poore <hi>Customers, Truth</hi> was neuer <hi>Error,</hi> nor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice,</hi> as the World had beene told, and long borne in hand; for can they but ſee, they ſhall learne to ſpell, and by ſpelling their Letters, both read and vnderſtand (beſides <hi>Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Matters</hi>) that <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners</hi> are ſeuerall wordes, and implye a diſtinction both of Manners and Men. And were it, or might it be, that docible perſons might be ſuffered but to learne, <hi>Publicans</hi> both could and would teach <hi>Sinners</hi> to be like vnto themſelues, not <hi>Saints,</hi> nor <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> but humble-minded Chriſtians, and plaine dealing Men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Method and Style of the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> ALPHABET and PRIMER.</note>Thus ſetling my ſelfe to mine <hi>Alphabet</hi> againe, thereby to ſpell my <hi>Primer.</hi> In my beginning praying God to bee my ſpeed, I felt his <hi>Grace</hi> and his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> did helpe mee to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede. For opening but my Booke, I found how great A. and little A.<note place="margin">A.</note> 
               <hi>Per ſe,</hi> and by themſelues, like the <hi>Creator</hi> and <hi>Creature,</hi> or the <hi>Maker</hi> and <hi>Modell</hi> ſhewing <hi>Deity</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> did ſtand for GOD and MAN,<note place="margin">A. GOD. MAN.</note> and ioyned both together, did make but <hi>One Medium,</hi> in the perſon of IESVS CHRIST, to perfect al our happineſſe, both in Heauen and Earth. For as the <hi>God-head</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>God-head</hi> of the <hi>Sonne,</hi> with the <hi>God-head</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> did make but one <hi>Eſſence</hi> in the ſubſtance of the <hi>Deity;</hi> and GOD and MAN vnited to the Perſon of IESVS CHRIST, did make but one Sauiour in the ſubſtance of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,</hi> ſo Chriſt and his Church, by the Vnion of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> did make but one Body. To ſaue and finde out Man, when couetous preſumption by <hi>Pride</hi> had ſo ſedu'ſt Him in his leaſt part of truſt, that he loſt both him and his.</p>
            <p>A Miracle of Miracles, and Myſterie to muſe on, but by no meanes to expreſſe, as whereby the greateſt looſer hath made the greateſt gaine.</p>
            <p>Heere therefore I ſtaid a while, and ſet my ſelfe to wonder: For as the <hi>Motiue</hi> of this <hi>Modell,</hi> was the Makers onely will, the <hi>Medium</hi> his owne word, the way his owne wiſedome, and the meaſure <hi>Aequum &amp; Bonum,</hi> bounds of his owne <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> by <hi>Preheminence</hi> of <hi>Iustice:</hi> ſo the abſolute perfection and End of all his worke, was his owne affection and deſire to preſerue by <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> of his owne firſt loue and boundleſſe Mercie, that the Creature might haue iuſtly wherein to admire both his Creators infinite Honour, and his owne eternall happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Now by this, it was apparent to common ſenſe and reaſon,
<pb facs="tcp:183763:9"/>
that what Nature can affoord, or Man beeing thus reſtord is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to poſſeſſe, is Gods owne Free-guift, euen from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: that as a <hi>Lord per amount,</hi> his <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Seruice</hi> might iuſtly bee knowne two ſeuerall waies to all his <hi>Free-Tenants;</hi> namely, by his owne ſpeciall Duties, and peculiar Rights, and their thankfull acknowledgements of their eaſie Rentes in ſo rich a Free-farme, by the Titles of their Tenures. The Titles of whoſe <hi>Tenures,</hi> being <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice:</hi> The one, to maintaine his perſonall Rights, and demonſtrate his Honor. The other, motions of affection, and reciproke Loue, to ſhew and ſet forth <hi>Loyalty</hi> for the <hi>Tennants</hi> mutuall good.</p>
            <p>The Lawes, Cuſtomes, and Doctrine whereof, pend by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and drawne from the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of his owne heauenly <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> being ſo concurrent, that where both of them are not, there can be neyther: I choſe heerewithall, comparatiuely to vſe in this my preſent Leſſon, as well to ſanctifie my Wit, and bliſſe mine endeuours, as to illuſtrate each other.<note place="margin">The Method vſed by the <hi>Cuſtomer,</hi> to perfect this Accompt before God and the Worlde, by ioyning <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> together, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde <hi>Paradoxicall Replies</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Now, by the Rules of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> both, <hi>Qui per ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um facit, per ſemet ipſum facit:</hi> Euen Gods immediate Rents, God himſelfe expects daily to receiue at our hands; namelie, <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Thankeſgiuing,</hi> ſuch is our Tenure: for being iealous of his Name, hee will not haue his Honour transfer'd to any other. The reſt he accepts of, beeing faithfully payde to his <hi>Stewards</hi> and <hi>Lieutenants;</hi> namely, <hi>Tithes</hi> and <hi>Tributes.</hi> In which regard, I ſaw how we ſtood bound, to reuerence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the tranſcendent aſpectes of MAIESTY and SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNTY, euen in earthly ſublimities, by their <hi>Attributes</hi> and <hi>Tributes,</hi> as Gods among Men. For the <hi>Attributes</hi> of Power in heauenly <hi>Deity,</hi> beeing <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> in regard of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe:</hi> The <hi>Attributes</hi> of Greatneſſe in earthly <hi>Humanity,</hi> in regard of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Bounty,</hi> are PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEMINENCE and PREROGATIVE, the two ſacred Titles of MAIESTY and SOVERAIGNETY, in the height of all Sublimitie: The one, to ſhew the Dignity both of <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Places;</hi> the other, tranſcendes to the motions of their <hi>Minds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> did guide my Deuotion through deepe contemplations, till holding vp my head, and caſting mine eyes to ſeek about for <hi>Tributes,</hi> mine owne EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THVSIASME beginning to awake, ſo quickned all my ſenſes, and withall, vntyde my tongue, that my <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>owels</hi> made me ſpeak <hi>a. e. i. o.</hi> and <hi>u.</hi> and by their ſeuerall ſounds, to gather and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the vſe of all my Letters, deuiding them as <hi>Conſonants</hi> into <hi>Semivowels, Mutes,</hi> and <hi>Liquides,</hi> with &amp; <hi>Per ſe</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſe,</hi> and <hi>Title Title, eſt Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe I came to learne (to my ſecret comfort and priuate conſolation) how our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> great and ſmall out of meere
<pb facs="tcp:183763:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Neceſſity</hi> to ſupply the want of Nature by Artificiall Mynes, both in <hi>Matter, Places, Perſons, Order,</hi> and <hi>Endes,</hi> ſhould bee ſpeld by themſelues, for the Demonſtration of MAIESTY in the furniſhing of BVLLION. And how our foreſaide <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage,</hi> out of <hi>Loues</hi> reciprocation, and <hi>Loyalties</hi> owne affection, were frankely preſented for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Seas, and protection of <hi>Marchants</hi> in their <hi>Goods</hi> or <hi>Liuings,</hi> in their <hi>Liberties,</hi> in their <hi>Liues,</hi> in their <hi>Honours,</hi> and in the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Vnion</hi> of our Land; ſtood likewiſe by themſelues. Whereby I plainely ſawe, and did ſhew it vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for the generall good of <hi>Subiects,</hi> both how MAIESTY might be ſeene, and how SOVERIGNTY might ſubſiſt, as by peculiar <hi>Attributes,</hi> ſo by <hi>Tributes</hi> of their owne; namely, <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies,</hi> but cheefely <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two wordes of Forraine birth I could not vnderſtand, for their <hi>Heteroclyte</hi> vſe and conuertible ſounds, <hi>Impoſts,</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> which being but the <hi>Genus</hi> to thoſe former two, and held for a <hi>Species</hi> of ſome other <hi>Duty,</hi> in my weak conceit haue deceiued many.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> Originall, beeing thoſe <hi>Duties</hi> artificiall that our <hi>Kings</hi> muſt needes haue, and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> impoſeth on all that tranſport by our <hi>Staple-Commerce,</hi> to ſupply our wants of <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Subſidies</hi> collaterall, thoſe naturall <hi>Respects</hi> that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> frankely offer, and willingly impoſe and lay vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for protection of the Seas, and free <hi>Traffique</hi> beſides: beyond the bounds of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Free will,</hi> I know not what <hi>Nature</hi> hath to read, or <hi>Art</hi> to ſpell.</p>
            <p>Beſides, whereas MAIESTY muſt, may, and can but bee ſeene, and SOVERAIGNTY ſubſiſt, as in GOD ſo in KINGS; looke what <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> are to GOD, the ſame are <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies</hi> to his <hi>Lieutenants:</hi> and beyonde the bounds that <hi>Wiſedome</hi> hath laid out for the practiſe of <hi>Truth, Diſcretion</hi> may hunt, but ſhall finde naught but <hi>Errors,</hi> for as <hi>Omne nimium vertitur in vitium,</hi> and <hi>Omne minimum</hi> is <hi>inimica Naturae:</hi> ſo what exceedes or is leſſe, is but <hi>Popery</hi> or <hi>Preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> to diſorder the <hi>Church,</hi> and diſturbe <hi>Common-weales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I wot not well how, though enough make the Feaſt, and abuſes marre all, the World beeing bewitcht with two kinds of <hi>Imposts</hi> and ſtrange <hi>Impoſitions;</hi> as <hi>Aliquid Boni prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vicinum Bonum,</hi> ſo <hi>Aliquid Mali propter vicinum Malum:</hi> our Neighbours ſower Grapes haue ſet our teeth on edge, for by their Examples drawne (as they tearme it) from <hi>Soueraigne Prerogatiue,</hi> but would ſay <hi>Preheminence</hi> if they vnderſtood themſelues; <hi>Impoſitions</hi> are made <hi>Taxes</hi> vppon <hi>Marchandize,</hi> by meere <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> beſides the Duties aforeſaid, which wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:183763:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Vſe</hi> in the ſtudy and Schooles of <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoc autem de quo nunc agimus, illud ipſum eſt quod <hi>VTILE</hi> appellatur; in quo verbo lapſa conſuetudo deflexit de via, còquè ſensim deducta eſt, vt <hi>Honeſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi> ab <hi>Vtilitate</hi> ſecerneus: <hi>HONESTVM</hi> aliquid conſtituerit quod uon ſit <hi>VTILE,</hi> &amp; <hi>VTILE</hi> quod non ſit <hi>HONESTVM</hi> qua, nulla pernicies maior vitae Hominum potuit aſſerri. <hi>Cicero offic. Lib. 2.</hi>
               </note> haue likewiſe no part in the Honour and Endes there taught and propounded, where VTILE is moſt dangerous, if it eyther go alone or follow not HONESTVM.</p>
            <p>For beeing but effects of conceited priuate Proiects, vpon vnknowne or obſcure <hi>Cauſes,</hi> of <hi>Matter</hi> vncertaine, and of <hi>Forme</hi> no waies fitting the Mowld of <hi>Free-Commerce;</hi> all Men refuſe to haue to do (if it may be) with them; to argue, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine, to deuide, or to bring them once in queſtion. The rather for that being naturally irreguler and letigious, they haue been occaſions of much vnreſt, diſvnion, and diſorder, by meanes of <hi>Popery</hi> in former times, till <hi>Magna Charta</hi> compounded ſuch greefes. And albeit the vſe of them ſince, might happily ayme at the beating backe of ſome Forraine idle Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, brought in vppon vs, and obtruded by Strangers, to the hindrance of our <hi>Trades,</hi> and decay of our <hi>Ports,</hi> both in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners</hi> and <hi>Shipping,</hi> which the wiſedome of our <hi>State</hi> muſt ſeek to maintaine; yet gathering withall vppon the naturall Free-borne <hi>Subiectes,</hi> they repine thereat, as men willing to obey, but not able to diſcerne betweene the diſpoſitions of <hi>States</hi> and changings of <hi>Tymes,</hi> and ſo is a ſpeciall occaſion of many Diſorders. The <hi>Subiect</hi> ſtill appealing to the Poſitiue Lawes of our owne Free-<hi>Traffique,</hi> as a generall Inheritance; and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers vrging their <hi>Treatiſe</hi> and mutuall <hi>Contracts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Impoſts</hi> of <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> or ſtrained <hi>Preheminence,</hi> haue likewiſe begotten ſome other <hi>Impoſitions</hi> of baſer Nature, and more dangerous Effects, whereby that ſacred word of <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Bounty, Mildeneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> (SOVERAIGNE PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROGATIVE) becomes vnreuerently proſtituted, and many waies profan'd: For whereas SOVERAIGNES are ſometimes pleaſed (as well may beſeeme them) out of meere Grace and Fauour in publique Reſtraints, by ſpeciall leaue and licenſes, to make ſome of their <hi>Seruants</hi> more happy then their <hi>Fellows;</hi> the ſame by ſales and tranſactions, tranſmuted and transfer'd, is a meanes to make Subiects from hand to hand, to racke and impoſe euen vpon and among themſelues, whereby <hi>Subiectes</hi> worrying <hi>Subiects,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Licentijs ſumus omnes deteriore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and deuouring one another, by meanes of ſuch <hi>Imposts</hi> waxe rich in an inſtant, as <hi>Rauens</hi> fat by Carrion; When indeede and in truth, the <hi>Grace</hi> doth looſe her <hi>Beeing,</hi> and the <hi>Grant</hi> becomes void vpon the firſt <hi>Exchange.</hi> For if <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorites</hi> get ſuits of Licenſes or Farmes vnfit for their callings,<note place="margin">Wine, Beere, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. And whatſoeuer of this kind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed by way of Licenſes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gracious fauor is afterwards transferd, ſold, or put ouer from the firſt recieuer, to a ſecond and third hand for Money. <hi>Simones Magi. Acts Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>verſe</hi> 20.</note> or vſe them not themſelues, it is but <hi>Witchcraft</hi> &amp; <hi>Sorcery</hi> that all ſuch entend, as by <hi>Leaſes</hi> or <hi>Purchace</hi> for priuate gaine, thinke SOVERAIGNES PREROGATIVES eyther vendible for <hi>Money,</hi> or ſubiect to <hi>Exchange.</hi> Such <hi>Impost Maisters, Religion</hi> hath accurſt, their <hi>Money</hi> and themſelues therefore (without
<pb facs="tcp:183763:11"/>
harty repentance) muſt periſh both together.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Imposts</hi> or <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> tearme them how you liſt, as they are but Romiſh <hi>Peter-pence,</hi> &amp; <hi>Italian</hi> Inuentions, where their Princes <hi>Preheminence</hi> and for'ſt kinde of Dignities haue little other Subſiſtence, being but eyther borrowed or obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon vs; I paſt them ſlightly ouer, and ſo ſent them home againe, for <hi>England</hi> beeing no waies obnoxious to <hi>Italy,</hi> nor Vaſſall to <hi>Rome,</hi> hath, or elſe may haue (beeing rightly vſed) enough of her owne.</p>
            <p>For our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>owels</hi> and our <hi>Conſonants</hi> agree ſo well together, that ſpelling all by <hi>Vnion,</hi> and ending all in <hi>Peace,</hi> they perfect all our <hi>Alphabet</hi> without the helpe of others, though the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of ſome CAPITALS in the world elſe-where abroad, by their lewd and ill examples, be a cauſe of ſome vnreſt. Whoſe <hi>Pride,</hi> profane <hi>Preſumption,</hi> and <hi>Couetiſe</hi> beſides, by <hi>Equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> ſounds makes words be ſo miſconſtrued, that MAIESTY ſeemes ecclip'ſt, and like to be out fa'ſt.</p>
            <p>For <hi>R. P.</hi> that with honeſt auncient <hi>Romans,</hi> was reade for <hi>Reſpublica,</hi> is now <hi>Reſpriuata:</hi> And <hi>P. P.</hi> for <hi>Principes</hi> or <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> now either by themſelues, or pla'ſt before <hi>A.</hi> in the ſtead and <hi>Rome</hi> of <hi>M.</hi> makes <hi>P AP A</hi> (ſometimes <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>) ſtand and ſtriue for MAIESTY before GOD and KINGS. And <hi>C.</hi> crept vp to <hi>K.</hi> makes <hi>Cardinals</hi> challenge <hi>Kings</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Crownes to be knowne by, or Kingdomes of their owne; ſo that as <hi>P AP A</hi> now ſpels ANTICHRIST, ſo <hi>Cardinals</hi> AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TI-KINGS. Whereby <hi>S. P. Q. R.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <figure/>
               </note> ſometimes the Armes and Honor of <hi>Rome,</hi> for <hi>Senatus Populus Que Romanus,</hi> may now as well bee read, <hi>Stultus Populus Querit Romam,</hi> to the great diſgrace of <hi>Catholiques,</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thoſe two great words of Power, PREHEMINENCE and PREROGATIVE, beginning both with P. did moſt of all perplex me. For ſeeing <hi>Iustice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> in the height of al ſublimitie, attending heauenly MAIESTY ſo reuerently toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the ſame in earthly <hi>Attributes</hi> conteſting each with other, I knew not how to ſpell them. For though they both contained the very ſelfe-ſame <hi>Letters</hi> that mine <hi>Alphabet</hi> did teach, yet the firſt importing <hi>Iuſtice</hi> I durſt not looke vpon for the ſternneſſe of her face and ſetled <hi>Seuerity;</hi> and the ſecond full of <hi>Mercy,</hi> I could not but admire for her milde aſpect and infinite <hi>Serenity.</hi> In the firſt I could diſcerne but two of our Vowels, <hi>e.</hi> and <hi>i.</hi> for <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> but the ſecond had them all, <hi>a. e. i. o.</hi> and <hi>u.</hi> I meane <hi>u.</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> Sirs, &amp; <hi>v.</hi> my Lords, <hi>w.</hi> and all. The one of greateſt Power, yet bounded in her <hi>Greatneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">KING and PRINCE. Counſell, and Common-wealth.</note> The other, a very <hi>Hieroglifique,</hi> aboue my reach and reaſon: yet hearing ſtill withal, how at all hands &amp; daily, PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEMINENCE for PREROGATIVE, and PREROGATIVE
<pb facs="tcp:183763:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for PREHEMINENCE, were ſtrangely ſpeld together; I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peald vnto the <hi>Wiſeſt</hi> in higheſt Authority, to compound the diſtractions that the World was ſubiect to, by the miſ-vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of wordes of ſuch importance, as both for <hi>Matter, Perſons, Place, Order,</hi> and <hi>End;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The important neceſſity of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing preciſely, the diſtinct vſe and Ends of <hi>Preheminence</hi> and <hi>Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue,</hi> in all words and Actions.</note> ſo neerly concern'd all our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings,</hi> all our <hi>Liues,</hi> all our <hi>Liberties,</hi> all our <hi>Honours,</hi> and all the <hi>Peace</hi> of our Land vnited ſo together. And let all men in Gods Name that haue eyes to ſee, will to learne, or wit to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, ſpell and diſtinguiſh the value of the <hi>Conſonants,</hi> and compaſſe of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>owels</hi> theſe two wordes containe, for they ſhew the difference and diſtinction betweene <hi>Soueraignty</hi> and <hi>Subiection,</hi> and the height of Dignity, both of <hi>Deity</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,</hi> the very right of GOD and KINGS.</p>
            <p>Heere (I ſay) is worke indeed for <hi>Wiſedome</hi> to conſider, and <hi>Power</hi> to reconcile, both theſe two <hi>Attributes</hi> and wordes of like import. For by their Example, as the <hi>Maſſe</hi> would ſeeme the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and <hi>Vſury</hi> is cald <hi>Exchange;</hi> ſo our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> ſtand for <hi>Subſidies, Subſidies</hi> for <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> and <hi>Impoſts</hi> nowe equiuocate both our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>This is the fruit of Trauailers by wandring ſtill to <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> il beholden to ſuch as trauailing for Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, thinke the <hi>Impoſitions</hi> of <hi>Italy</hi> a fit preſident for Pollicy or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment when they come home</note>
               </l>
               <l>That hunting for experience, ride early and late:</l>
               <l>To make the <hi>Impoſts</hi> of <hi>Italy</hi> as ſoone as they come home,</l>
               <l>A Preſident of Gouernment, as fit to guide our State.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Whereby as <hi>Maiesty</hi> ſtands eclip'ſt, ſo <hi>Customers</hi> in diſgrace are in nothing yet more wretchedlike then in their Names and Place, for beeing borne happy, bred happy, and looſing themſelues in ſeeking happineſſe for others, themſelues can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be happy.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Delicta ſequnter Perſonas,</hi> and greateſt offences de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue greateſt puniſhments; that mine owne Faith to GOD-ward, and obedience to my SOVERAIGNE, declaring my Religion and ciuill conuerſation, may warrant mine Accompt both before GOD and KINGS: Hauing thus far ſpeld &amp; read by the help of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> I proceeded to my <hi>Creede,</hi> and then my <hi>Ten-Commaundements,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By the <hi>Cuſtomers Beleefe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> note the true Religion taught and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in <hi>Great-Brittaine.</hi>
               </note> whereby being taught to <hi>Cypher,</hi> I came at laſt by telling, 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. to ſet downe my Receipts, and to cleere vp all my Reckonings, without ſuſpending any, or enſtaulement of a Penny. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to caſt Accompts for my ſelfe and for others, (<hi>Customers</hi> are Accomptants, euen for the ſinnes of others) I found that twelue <hi>Articles,</hi> two <hi>Mysteries</hi> and ten great <hi>Commaundes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſumme of true Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſting of twelue <hi>Articles,</hi> two <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ten Commaundements,</hi> containes all Chriſtian Duties, both to God and Kings.</note> made the ſumme of mine <hi>Alphabet</hi> iuſt foure and twenty Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; namely, <hi>a. e. i. o. u.</hi> and <hi>b c. d. f. g. h. k. l. m. n. p. q. r. ſ. t. w. x. y. z.</hi> And the number of all numbers,<note place="margin">The compaſſe and number of the <hi>Alphabet,</hi> conſiſting of 24. Letters, comprehend and teach all <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice.</hi>
               </note> where perfection is confin'd both of Heauen Earth, <hi>[Ten.]</hi> Three being Gods own
<pb facs="tcp:183763:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
number and perfection of <hi>Deity;</hi> as GOD the Father, GOD the Sonne, and GOD the Holy-Ghoſt: and ſeuen of <hi>Humanity,</hi> in our firſt and free <hi>Election, Creation, Redemption, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocation, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, Sanctification,</hi> and <hi>Glorification,</hi> by the meanes of CHRIST IESVS, that is both GOD and MAN. By this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I ſpeld our owne <hi>Ten Courtes</hi> of <hi>Iustice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By the ten Soueraigne Courts of fundamentall <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> are pointed at and meant the Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. The <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> Grace. His Prayers.</note> the perfection whereof diſtributiuely, makes vs al ſo happy, and for which, as <hi>Grace</hi> made me ſay <hi>Grace,</hi> and giue God harty thanks, ſo <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> bad mee pray for the bleſſed State and happineſſe of my SOVERAIGNE, firſt by Name King IAMES, and for his Priuy COVNSELL, for his ISIS, for the Prince, and all the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Iſſue, for the CLEARGY, for the NOBLES, &amp; COMMONS of the Land. In a word, for the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> And for <hi>Traffique</hi> at the laſt, though my Faith ſeemd fraile, and my credit almoſt gone, yet not to deſpaire; but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtill my <hi>Creede,</hi> and thoſe very <hi>Ten Commaundements</hi> mine <hi>Alphabet</hi> doth teach, to remember but mine Oath, and do my beſt Endeuour, and hope withall
<q>
                  <hi>That</hi> Vnus Homo Nobis cunctando restituet Rem.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So cloſing vp mine <hi>Alphabet</hi> with a publique confeſſion and with a daily Prayer, for &amp; <hi>Per ſe,</hi> and <hi>Con per ſe,</hi> and all the reſt together; I proſtrately preſented and encluded a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the KING our ſacred SOVERAIGNE, for his Sonne the Princes ſake, in the Name of all the <hi>Customers</hi> of the <hi>Out-Ports</hi> of this Land, to be read at his beſt leyſure; within thoſe ſanctified wordes, and effectuall forme of Prayer, which the Son GOD of himſelfe commanded and taught, that as his is the KINGDOME, the POVVER, and the GLORY, for euer and euer, So be it, Amen. So our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> treble Title, with <hi>Est</hi> and <hi>Amen,</hi> might perfect all our happineſſe: ſaying laſtly for my ſelfe;
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nil ſum, nulla miſer noui ſolatia, Maſſam</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Humanam niſi quod tu quo<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>
                        </hi> CHRISTE <hi>geris:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tu me ſuſtenta, fragilem tu</hi> CHRISTE <hi>guberna,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fac vt ſim Maſſae ſurculus</hi> Ipſe <hi>tuae.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I nothing am, and in my ſelfe no comfort finde but this,</l>
                     <l>That CHBISY the Maſſe of humane fleſh hath tane and ioynd to his:</l>
                     <l>Then ſaue me CHRIST and grant withall, that this fraile fleſh of mine,</l>
                     <l>A twig at leaſt, may bud and branch from that great Maſſe of thine.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Magna, Magnus perficit</hi> DEVS.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, that I ſeeme not thus by <hi>ſpellinge</hi> to <hi>Cabalize</hi> in ieſt, or think to conſtrue <hi>Hieroglifiques</hi> by Common ſence and reaſon; Hauing found by mine <hi>Alphabet,</hi> thoſe Conſonants of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wherewith the very <hi>Wiſedome</hi> of the Bible is expreſt, and hearing by my Vowels the ſame ſound of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> doth teach; and the very ſelfe-ſame <hi>Truth</hi> (for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb facs="tcp:183763:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
at the leaſt, let perſonall defects ſtill aunſwere for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) that CHRIST and his APOSTLES, yea, S. PETER with the reſt did leaue vnto the World, for <hi>Soueraignes</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, and <hi>Subiects</hi> to obey: If <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> may be helde ſufficient to help vs to happines, what <hi>Kingdome</hi> in the world, nay, what <hi>Citty, Port,</hi> or <hi>Towne,</hi> eyther publique or priuate, for <hi>Temples</hi> and <hi>Courtes,</hi> and <hi>Free-Schooles</hi> beſides, may compare with GREAT-BRITTAINE? where for <hi>Matter, Places, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Order,</hi> and <hi>Endes,</hi> all <hi>Learning</hi> now Tryumphes, and AL-BOVNTY commaunds. For our Reuerend <hi>Byſhops</hi> and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Diuines,</hi> worke obedience in <hi>Subiects</hi> by the rules of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and both by life and Doctrine, directing the way how to win <hi>Heauen,</hi> teach <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Good-workes,</hi> and Preach in all our Churches, that Faith onely and alone in the Action of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, is the cauſe of Saluation, in regard of the freedome of ſanctifying <hi>Grace;</hi> but in the Party ſaued, both muſt concurre together, to iuſtifie the calling; (And not as thoſe <hi>Cardinals</hi> doe, and <hi>Deſtructiue Ieſuites,</hi> that to builde vp their <hi>Popery,</hi> would blow vp <hi>Common-weales,</hi> and by looſeneſſe of Life and Traditions of Men, being Subiects themſelues, contemne their owne <hi>Soueraignes,</hi> kill ſacred <hi>Kinges,</hi> conteſt with Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and rob CHRIST of his honour. Nor as theſe <hi>Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue Teachers</hi> would doe, that prepoſterouſly propounding ſuch fancies of Perfection, as no Reaſon can reach to, nor themſelues expreſſe; preferre Sacrifice before obedience, and obtrude vpon GOD more then he requires) aſſuring vs withal out of warrant from the WORD, that to all whom his SPIRIT makes truely repentant, GOD by IESVS CHRIST, both is, and will be, a moſt gracious and a moſt louing GOD, but GOD without CHRIST, is a conſuming Fire. ¶ And our <hi>Worthy-Graue Iudges</hi> ſit vpright in all our Courts of fundamentall <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and both by Lawe and Conſcience, maintaine the perpetuities of all our Landes and Goods, by the Name of <hi>Liuings,</hi> all our <hi>Liberties,</hi> all our <hi>Liues,</hi> all our <hi>Honour,</hi> and the <hi>Peace</hi> of all our <hi>Land</hi> diſtributiuely; diſcerning and decyding by <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> as well in <hi>Tythes</hi> as in <hi>Tributes,</hi> the Caſes and Queſtions of ſpeciall <hi>Right</hi> and generall <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as wel betweene 1.<note place="margin">1 The Court of COMMON-PLEAS, and Staples.</note> 
               <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect</hi> and <hi>Subiect,</hi> as the 2.<note place="margin">2 The Court of KINGS-BENCH, and of Wards and Liueries.</note> 
               <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and his Vaſſals, by the <hi>Common-Lawes, Statutes,</hi> and peculiar <hi>Customes,</hi> caſt in the Mould, and fitted to the 3.<note place="margin">3 The High Court of PARLEMENT.</note> Wiſedome of our owne State and Land: moderating <hi>Extreamities</hi> by 4.<note place="margin">4 The High Court of CHANCERY, and Court of Requeſts.</note> Conſcience among Men, and maintaining ſtill the <hi>Good</hi> by cenſuring the <hi>Euill,</hi> 5.<note place="margin">5 The Court STAR-CHAMBER, and Counſell-Table.</note> 
               <hi>Sic Iraſcuntur vt vitia tantum perimant ſeruatis hominibus, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ita tractatis vt viri Boni neceſſariò fiant, quantumque damni autea dederint in reliqua vita reſarcire queant:</hi> And being honorably ennobled by APOLLO themſelues to decide both the doubts,<note place="margin">6 The Court of CHEVALRY, and Mareſchals Verge</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:13"/>
and determine the queſtions of reputation and worth, in all Rankes and Degrees of <hi>Natiue</hi> Ingenuity and <hi>Datiue Honour;</hi> ſo maintaine our Credits,
<q>
                  <l>Vt per Titulos numerantur Aui, ſemperqùe renata</l>
                  <l>Nobilitate virent, &amp; Prolem Fata ſequuntur,</l>
                  <l>Continuum propria ſeruantia lege tenorem.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And our learned <hi>Ciuilians</hi> ſo belay the publike <hi>Peace</hi> of our 7.<note place="margin">7 The Court of ADMIRALTY.</note> Seas and our 8.<note place="margin">8 The Court of ARCHES.</note> Land, that by doing vs <hi>Iustice,</hi> our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours take no wrong. And laſtly, our SOVERAIGNE likewiſe hath his owne Courts apart,<note place="margin">9 The Court of EXCHEQVER.</note> for his publike 9 Reuenewes and priuate 10 Expences,<note place="margin">10 The Court of GREENE-CLOTH.</note> where Acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptants are heard, diſcharg'd, &amp; diſpacht by Court-Rowles, and Court-Rules, grounded on <hi>Preſidents,</hi> of <hi>Wiſedomes</hi> owne Examples, without partiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, or priuate Diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Now, if it be a happineſſe for men to haue the freedome to come to ſuch Churches, to frequent ſuch Temples, and to dwel within Houſes, whoſe Foundations are laide on ſuch aſſured grounds; what reaſon haue Catholiques (if they be not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witcht) to fly from their Countrey, or be wedded ſo to <hi>Rome?</hi> For <hi>Customers</hi> want wordes to expreſſe their inward ioyes, and ſhew their beſt conceits, of the bleſſings of God in theſe our daies and times, for the ſtayes of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Distributiue Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;</hi> only our Court of CHEVALRY wants but her <hi>Iudges</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide points of <hi>Honour,</hi> and preuent thereby our Cumbats, and our <hi>Traffique</hi> wants her <hi>Staples:</hi> for were thoſe two 1.<note place="margin">1 The High Coneſtable and Earle Mareſchall of England.</note> 
               <hi>Patrones</hi> of <hi>Honor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 The Heralds.</note> on whom 2 <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhould ſerue by APOLLO but found out; and the Roofes of our Schooles made but Winde-tight and Water-tight, in the breaches and wants of <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue Right,</hi> &amp; had <hi>Traffick</hi> but her <hi>Staples,</hi> as <hi>Religion</hi> hath her Temples, we would ſoone make Verſes in praiſe and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our <hi>Prelats</hi> and our <hi>Nobles,</hi> of our <hi>Prince</hi> and our <hi>Peeres,</hi> and ſing all <hi>Alleluiah</hi> to the great KING of Heauen.<note place="margin">Aux Chicanneurs l'honneur n'ha poynt de lieu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Car ſans argent vous parlez en Hebrieu.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But this part of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> being moſt out of frame, and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing all the reſt <hi>Commutatiuely,</hi> keepes downe our voyces, which now falling out, and fitted for my Leſſon, I muſt by my Letters goe ſpell out the wordes that belong to the Titles of my <hi>Soueraignes Tributes.</hi> Wherein being thus farre proceeded, by the helpe of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> with <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> being both on my ſide: I reſolu'd by the <hi>Medium,</hi> to dig on and delue for <hi>Truth,</hi> the Foundation of <hi>Felicity,</hi> and ſo become happy. For ſince the Oxe is not muzled that treads out the Corne, by the Rules of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> allowes to each la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer his hire: I ſaw no right nor reaſon, why ſeruing at the Altar, I might not hope at leaſt, at laſt to liue thereby, though I held my peace: For <hi>Aſſai demanda encor che mai non grida chi ben ſeruendo tace.</hi> And why treading out the path of happineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:183763:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for others I ſhould be put by. Therefore hauing now learnde all my Letters, and CHRISTS Croſſe being my ſpeed, and the Holy-Ghoſt, lowly ſetting forward, I thus began to fly.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Habet &amp; Muſca ſplenem &amp; formicae ſua bilis ineſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The PRIMER.</note> Yet far be it from <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> to value themſelues by way of reuenge, or diſgracing of others. But ſince al men euen by Nature deſire to be happy, by the rules of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> bids <hi>Reaſon</hi> haue an eye ſtill to <hi>Nature,</hi> and be next her ſelfe: of all worldly happineſſe, if the meaneſt be but Wealth, and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cheefeſt, <hi>Honour</hi> being held a recompence for all our loſſe beſides. If all quit their <hi>Liuings,</hi> for their <hi>Liberties</hi> to worke, (Nature giues no priuiledge for any to be idle;) If all forgoe their <hi>Liberties</hi> for the purchaſe of their <hi>Liues;</hi> If <hi>Liuings, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Liues,</hi> and <hi>All</hi> ſeeme nothing to our <hi>Credits.</hi> And if GOD ſo priſe his holy Name, that he is Ielous of his <hi>Glory,</hi> to ſhew how his LIEVTENANTS ſhould be curious of their <hi>Honour,</hi> I came at laſt to ſee, and therewithall to wonder, that the Names euen of KINGES, GODS immediat <hi>Lieutenants,</hi> nay, of GOD himſelfe through <hi>Ignorance</hi> and her <hi>Fellowes,</hi> are ſubiect to diſgrace as well as <hi>Cuſtomers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as <hi>Quaedam ſunt &amp; non videntur,</hi> and <hi>Quaedam videntur &amp; non ſunt omnino.</hi> So <hi>Plus quandoque valet in Rebus promouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, opinio Ignorantium quàm Rei veritat.</hi> Which made me to conſider, that though <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> were the Arts of <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city;</hi> yet as euery Text had his <hi>Gloſſe,</hi> and euery Art her <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery;</hi> ſo <hi>Religion</hi> beeing the Rule for <hi>Apprentiſes</hi> of <hi>Piety,</hi> to learne the way to <hi>Glory,</hi> ſhew'd the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> for <hi>Myſtery.</hi> And the ſetled Art of <hi>Equity,</hi> that raiſeth all to <hi>Honour</hi> by the rules of honeſt <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> for her <hi>Myſtery</hi> had <hi>Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt being wholly heauenly, and faſtned to <hi>Diuinity,</hi> is taught by <hi>Diuines,</hi> and I am but a <hi>Cuſtomer,</hi> yet a faithfull Chriſtian Catholique, and a Loyall <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Man. But the other from <hi>Humanity,</hi> more fit for ſence and reaſon, with dim eyes and trembling handes, to ſhow the beſt endeuour of a feeble wit and weaker braines, I gaue my ſelfe to ſpell, and directly to diſcouer.</p>
            <p>An Argument I confeſſe of a higher pitch, and farre greater compaſſe, then I did or could imagine, when I tooke it firſt in hand: wherein hazzard euen at firſt did very much diſcourage me, in reſpect of the times. In the midſt, by Friends I was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waies diſſwaded in regard of the paines, and I had giuen it ouer (for I wrought all alone) but for the <hi>Enthuſiaſme</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of Adoption ſtill ſounding in mine eares, <hi>Religion</hi> takes thy part, and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> on thy ſide:
<q>
                  <l>Ton Ame ne doibt ta flamme eſtant diuine,</l>
                  <l>Rien ayme ny ſeruir ſi'l n'est egual aux Dieux.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:183763:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thy Soule is ſo beſet by Vowes that are Diuine,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt not tread amiſſe, let not thy heart decline.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>By whoſe perſwaſion, when I had but once begon, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thruſt me forward, and thus preuaild at laſt:
<q>
                  <l>Ie veulx quùn bel ozer honore ma ruyne,</l>
                  <l>Et ſi'l fault que Ie tombe Ie l'ay voulu des cieulx.</l>
               </q>
Then danger ſtand aſide (quoth I) ſince <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> cals me to it, If ought doe put me by, tis <hi>Wiſedomes</hi> hand ſhall doe it.</p>
            <p>My ſtayes beſides were theſe: As <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> cal'd me forward, ſo <hi>Truth</hi> was ſtill my <hi>Ground,</hi> which as <hi>Time</hi> did ſuggeſt, <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> ſtill ſupplide: My Pen <hi>Oportet</hi> made, and was euer apt to mend, (beeing ſworne to doe my beſt) <hi>Order</hi> gaue the <hi>Forme,</hi> but the Stile I ſtill ſuſpected, and ſawe ſome cauſe to doubt, till Prayer in concluſion, vndertooke to perfect or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the beſt; ſo that if the Phraſe for the plaineneſſe, might paſſe without offence, I was ſure the Matter for importance, might deſerue a double and treble reading. Now the <hi>Matter</hi> indeede was <hi>Traffique,</hi> I meane our owne Free-borne <hi>Trafficke</hi> that honeſt Nurce of <hi>Iustice,</hi> that ſo kindly feedes vs all, and handled <hi>Ab effectis,</hi> containes thoſe ſelfe-ſame <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> for which the poor <hi>Schollers</hi> in the <hi>Out-Schooles</hi> of Tributes, haue ſo long time bin ſubiect to bayting and beating, and for which my ſelfe was ſo gratiouſly chidden.</p>
            <p>Thus ſearching after <hi>Truth,</hi> that onely of it ſelfe makes all in all happy, though it be my hard fortune to worke ſtill alone; <hi>Quo fato neſcio ſed non ſine Numine:</hi> As my hope and comfort is, yet following ſtill mine ALPHABET, and Lines of my PRYMER, I came at laſt to ſpell thoſe very ACROAMATA of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Motiue and occaſion of the ACROAMATA.</note> ſo fitly ioyn'd together, by <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> that leades all to <hi>Truth,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> as made me read out plainely, and write diſtinctly thus.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Method and Stile of the ACROAMATA.</note>¶ All Men by Nature are deſirous to be <hi>Happy,</hi> as well as <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers,</hi> and ayme at <hi>Perfection</hi> by rules of <hi>Order,</hi> and degrees of <hi>Goodneſſe.</hi> But <hi>Ignorance</hi> beeing euery way the Mother of <hi>Errors,</hi> and Grandame of <hi>Miſcheefes,</hi> begotte with all thoſe <hi>Inconueniences,</hi> which pretend indeede <hi>Order,</hi> but lead all to <hi>Diſcord, Diſorder,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion.</hi> Is ought then out of <hi>Order,</hi> and fit to bee reformed? Conſult but with <hi>Wiſedome</hi> and wee neede not diſpaire. For <hi>Priuatio ſemper preſupponit habitum:</hi> Sickneſſe it ſelfe ſhowes a habit firſt of Health, and the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion'd Diſpoſition of any Function, high or low, doth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue an Intention and poſſibility of <hi>Order.</hi> Nay, <hi>Ignorance</hi> her ſelfe knowes and tels it all ouer, that ERRORS haue no <hi>Being</hi> but in abſence of <hi>Truth,</hi> and vnawares to her ſelfe doth teach <hi>Reformation</hi> how in ſeeking after <hi>Truth</hi> the beſt rule of <hi>Order,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in finding her to wander is ſtill to looke backward: for euen out of <hi>Confuſion, Perfection</hi> may bee drawne as <hi>Truth,</hi> by the Cauſes of <hi>Truth,</hi> comes once to be knowne; ſo by this I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, <hi>Foelix qui poterit Rerum cognoſcere Cauſas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now GOODNES, TRVTH and WISEDOME, make but one Eſſence, and being euer linkt together, I found that GOD himſelfe was both <hi>All</hi> and eyther, and therefore All-ſufficient, and onely <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All,</hi> which firſt made me bolde and thus to read out: AB IOVE PRINCIPIVM.</p>
            <p>For all things in the World (God alone excepted) affecting to be happy, beſides the inclination, they haue in themſelues (for vſe or knowledge) drawe helpes from others to externall perfection; and whatſoeuer they ſeeme to acquire, the ſame they tearme alwaies poſitiuely their <hi>Good,</hi> but that wherein perfections ſelfe doth reſt, their <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> or <hi>Soueraign</hi> bliſſe. For of things that are called but ſimply <hi>Good,</hi> and ſought but for themſelues, ſome are as Inſtruments to direct and help vs to the <hi>End</hi> of our deſires, of which ſort are <hi>Riches:</hi> others alſo we wiſh for in regard of themſelues; as <hi>Health, Wiſedome, Honour;</hi> yet not being the marke that wee gladly would hit, our <hi>Deſires</hi> ſtill proceede. Thus we are firſt borne to labour, we labour to eate, we eate ſtill to liue, and we liue to do good by ſome calling or other, in the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi> Wherein all we doe or can doe, euen our beſt endeuours are but as ſeed ſowen with a reference, and reſpect to ſome further future Harueſt; ſo that ſtill we proceede till wee come to a pawſe, whereat we needs muſt reſt.</p>
            <p>There are likewiſe ſome thinges deſired but only for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, becauſe the <hi>Deſirers</hi> imperfection can affect them no further, as Cattle doe their foode. But that which Man ſeekes for with referencc alwaies to a further <hi>End,</hi> that he ſtill deſires with a <hi>Meanes</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> euery way conuenient and fitted to that <hi>End,</hi> and to the <hi>Good</hi> he affects onely as <hi>Good</hi> within it ſelfe, his deſire is infinite: ſo that vnleſſe that <hi>Good</hi> be likewiſe infinite in it ſelfe, he erres in his choiſe, and miſtakes his <hi>End,</hi> as they that ſeeking <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> place their <hi>Summum Bonum</hi> in popular applaud, worldly <hi>Wealth</hi> or <hi>Pleaſure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omnis Forma Boni infunditur ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum meritum Materiae.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But nothing can indeed be infinitely deſird, ſaue that <hi>Good</hi> which in it ſelf is euery way infinite, for the better any <hi>Good</hi> is, the more to be deſird, &amp; that alone moſt deſird, wherein there is abiding an infinity of <hi>Goodnes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bonum quo Communius eò ſemper melius.</note> ſo that where any thing deſird hath an infinity of <hi>Beeing,</hi> or is infinite in it ſelfe, that, of all <hi>Things</hi> that can <hi>Be,</hi> is of all <hi>Beings</hi> to bee moſt of all deſired; But nothing <hi>Is</hi> or can <hi>Be</hi> infinitely <hi>Good</hi> ſaue GOD. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mans higheſt happineſſe, <hi>Summum Bonum</hi> and perfect <hi>Bliſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>DEVS</hi> Tantum Infinite Bonus ergo ſummum Bonum.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Now <hi>Deſire</hi> tends to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>Good</hi> which is deſired, for bare poſſeſſion makes no Man happy, but the vſe and fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Goodnes</hi> being once obtain'd. For <hi>Quò mihi Fortuna ſi non conceditur vti?</hi> Then <hi>Happineſſe</hi> thus ſpeld, and the wordes put together, I was taught to pronounce, to be that State of Life, wherein wee ſo enioy <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in the height of all perfection, that though we be but Men, yet we liue, as it were the very life of GOD himſelfe, <hi>Et Homo Homini Deus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perfection</hi> then of Happineſſe reſiding ſtill in <hi>Heauen,</hi> the <hi>Throne</hi> of our GOD, and the <hi>Earth</hi> but his <hi>Foot-stoole;</hi> his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> drawing our <hi>Deſires,</hi> muſt helpe vs vp thither, by a kinde of <hi>Free-Traffique</hi> betweene his fixed Seat in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> and wandring Church on <hi>Earth;</hi> his heauenly Inſpirings downeward, and our holy Deſires vpward, being as <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Marchants</hi> betweene GOD and vs. That as his Doctrine doth teach <hi>Him</hi> for our Supreame <hi>Truth,</hi> and our Prayers confeſſe <hi>Him</hi> for our <hi>Soueraigne Good:</hi> ſo our Faith in him aboue belay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Happineſſe, our Charity below muſt work out our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by a <hi>Medium,</hi> ſo conuenient both for <hi>Deity</hi> and <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> as fits both GOD and MAN, which can be no other then IESVS CHRIST himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Faith I ſay (that workes ſtill by Loue) apprehending the Mercies of GOD the Father, for the Merits of GOD the Son, by the working of GOD the Spirit, the Fountaine of all <hi>Grace</hi> and Mother of <hi>Obedience.</hi> For great is the <hi>Mysterse</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs vnto the Art of all our heauenly <hi>Happineſſe, (Godlineſſe,</hi> or <hi>Piety</hi>) by <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> in the Doctrine of <hi>Religion,</hi> the ſumme whereof is this. GOD manifeſted in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſeene of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> beleeued in the World, and receiued vp to <hi>Glory</hi> reſides in <hi>Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For liuely Types whereof, and ſpeciall remembrances, CHRIST IESVS Himſelfe our <hi>Medium</hi> GOD and MAN, before his departure and Aſſcention vp to Heauen, to prepare our <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> beſides his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Promiſe,</hi> did leaue vnto his Church his ſanctified <hi>Elements,</hi> of <hi>Water, Bread,</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> to comfort both our Bodies, and confirme our Soules and Minds, as in Mirrors to behold <hi>Him,</hi> and as by <hi>Pledges</hi> to aſſure vs of his comming again, to draw vs vp thither: Namely, <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> and the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> at his owne laſt Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion</hi> therefore as the Rule of Chriſtian <hi>Piety,</hi> by the Doctrine of <hi>Truth,</hi> muſt lay the firſt foundation and ſafeſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to our <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> and heauenly Happineſſe.</p>
            <p>¶ Thus farre poore <hi>Cuctomers</hi> being taught to ſpell and read, praiſing God with all their harts, do cleerely pronounce and ſteadfaſtly beleeue, which ſhewes them to be <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> If
<pb facs="tcp:183763:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that which likewiſe followes approue them to be honeſt, why ſhould they not be happy as well as other Men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Happineſſe</hi> in perfection, by that which hath beene ſpeld, being that eſtate of life, wherein wee ſo enioy the fulneſſe of all Bliſſe, as though we be but Men, yet we liue as it were the very life of God himſelf: to liue the life GOD, is to liue as in his preſence, and ſee his glorious face in the <hi>Maieſty</hi> of his <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Soueraignety</hi> of his <hi>Goodneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">No perfect Happineſſe but by the ſight of MAIESTY, perſonally fixt</note> To ſee therefore ſacred MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTY euery way ſtill fixt, and SOVERAIGNTY ſubſiſt, is the only ſtate of life that perfects all happines, both in <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> In the ſeeking whereof, for my ſelfe and for others, as <hi>Piety</hi> directed my Deſire vp to <hi>Heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Primum querite Reg num Dei, Deinde Meum &amp; Tuum.</note> by the <hi>Rules</hi> of true <hi>Religion;</hi> ſo from <hi>Piety</hi> to <hi>Equity</hi> by the Rules of <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> to ſee how MAIESTY ſtood fixt, and how SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNTY might ſubſiſt as well on <hi>Earth</hi> as in <hi>Heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magnifica <hi>MAIESTATIS</hi> deſcriptio.</note> 
               <hi>Iustice</hi> to encourage me held vp my Booke, and bad me be bold, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, honeſt Man ſpeake out; whereupon I thus ſet forward.<note place="margin">
                  <l>Poſt Chaos, vt primum data ſunt tria Corpora Mundo,</l>
                  <l>Inque nouas ſpecies, omne receſsit opus:</l>
                  <l>Pondere terra ſuo ſubſedit, &amp; aequora traxit:</l>
                  <l>Ad-Coelum leuitas in loca ſumma tulit.</l>
                  <l>Sol quoquc cum ſtellis, nulla grauitate retentus,</l>
                  <l>Et vos Lunares exiluiſtis equi.</l>
                  <l>Sed neque Terra diu Coelo, neque caetera Phaebo</l>
                  <l>Sydera cedebant, par erat omnis <hi>Honor.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Saepe aliquis Solio, quod tu <hi>SATVRNE</hi> tenebas,</l>
                  <l>Auſus de media plebe ſedere <hi>Deus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Et latus Occano quiſquam <hi>Deus</hi> aduena iunxit:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thetis</hi> &amp; extremo ſaepe recepta loco eſt.</l>
                  <l>Donec <hi>Honor,</hi> placidoque decens <hi>Reuerentia</hi> vultu</l>
                  <l>Corpora legitimis impoſuere thoris.</l>
                  <l>Hinc ſacra <hi>MAIESTAS,</hi> quae Mundum temperat omne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                  <l>Quaque die partu eſt edita. Magna fuit.</l>
                  <l>Nec mora, conſedit medio ſublimis Olympo,</l>
                  <l>Aurea purpureo conſpicienda ſinu.</l>
                  <l>Conſedere ſimul Pudor et Metus: omne videres</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Numen</hi> ad <hi>HANC</hi> vultus compoſuiſſe ſuos.</l>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>¶ As GOODNES, TRVTH, and WISEDOME, ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting all together in the gloriouſneſſe of <hi>Deity,</hi> made <hi>Man</hi> the firſt Modell of <hi>Perfection</hi> like it ſelfe, for the vſe and good of All, by the Rules of <hi>Religion:</hi> ſo <hi>Grace</hi> begetting <hi>Bounty</hi> in the Nature of <hi>Humanity</hi> by <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum,</hi> fixt MAIESTY and SOVERAIGNTY in the perſons of ſome Men for al mens Weale, by the rules of <hi>Iustice.</hi> Now in following <hi>Iuſtice</hi> rules, I light vpon <hi>Equity, Equity</hi> ſpake to <hi>Probity, Probity</hi> ſpeld out <hi>Honeſty, Honeſty</hi> brought forth <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> fixt, ſhewd me the glorious Word of <hi>Reuerence,</hi> and abſolute power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum</hi> (ſacred MAIESTY) no where ſeene fixed but in GOD and KINGS. For as among all the <hi>Attributes,</hi> and glorious Titles of Celeſtiall Orders, recorded by Religion; as <hi>Angels, Arch-Angels, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues, Principalities, Dominions, Thrones, Seraphins,</hi> and <hi>Cherubins,</hi> I could not ſpy out MAIESTY but infuſiuely, ſaue only in GOD alone: ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the Titles, Orders, and Degrees of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> that <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> hath ſet downe, in <hi>Gentlemen, Squires, Knights, Baronets, Barons, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice-Countes, Earles, Marqueſſes, Dukes, Arch dukes, Princes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ayvods,</hi> nor <hi>Doges,</hi> nor <hi>Seruo Seruorum Dei;</hi> I could not ſee MAIESTY <add> perſonally fixt</add> ſaue onely in Gods LIEV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENANTS by the Name of KINGS. No not in EMPERORS, but as they were inueſted with the powerfulneſſe of KINGS, which made me glad to ſee, and thus to proceede.</p>
            <p>¶ As all things in Nature ſtill tend to ſome End, and that as perfection of the thing for which it workes, is attain'd vnto
<pb facs="tcp:183763:16"/>
onely by apt and fit meanes: ſo that which moderates and formes out fitneſſe, is tearmed Natures Law, by which as by Rules, the World and all therein are diſtinguiſht and ſtinted: which limitation alſo, both perfects &amp; preſerues all the things themſelues. <hi>Meaſure</hi> therefore that workes by proportions is the meanes to <hi>Perfection.</hi> And ſince nothing doth periſh but through too much or too little of that, the due proportion whereof, doth giue <hi>Perfection; Meaſure,</hi> is alſo the preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all things; for to proportions, <hi>Exceſſe</hi> and <hi>Defects</hi> are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite. <hi>Omne minimum Inimica Naturae,</hi> and <hi>Omne Nimium vertitur in vitium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iustice</hi> then the <hi>Rule,</hi> and in regard of <hi>Truth,</hi> the <hi>End</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed in <hi>Equity,</hi> for all honeſt Actions to guide themſelues by, as <hi>Religion</hi> in <hi>Piety,</hi> for holy Contemplations; is preſcribed firſt by Lawes, and preſerued by Meaſures, which beeing the charge of earthly <hi>Soueraignes,</hi> ſets forth and limits their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence</hi> and <hi>Prerogatiue,</hi> qualities tranſcendent aboue their humaine ſubſtance. For in regard of <hi>Iustice,</hi> it is ſaid they are <hi>Gods,</hi> though their perſons dye like Men. Now <hi>Iustice</hi> being <hi>Commutatiue</hi> as well as <hi>Distributatiue,</hi> the <hi>Commutatiue</hi> part in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes our lower <hi>Traffique,</hi> to ſupply all neceſſities in the vſe of thoſe Good thinges that helpe to make vs happy; either, by bartring Good things for Good things, by the Name of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities,</hi> or by ſome <hi>Medium</hi> and meanes, certaine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to preuent aduantage. The <hi>End</hi> then of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> in regard of <hi>Truth</hi> in Actions, being <hi>Equity</hi> in Contracts, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of worth in Wares, and the onely vſe <hi>Exchange,</hi> the <hi>Medium</hi> is by conſent of <hi>Nations</hi> cald <hi>Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in all kinde of Meaſures, being <hi>Standarts</hi> and <hi>Beames</hi> for generall <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> like <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim</hi> are onely <hi>Soueraignes</hi> charge; to giue thereby both weight and content, with length and breadth to all proportions: ſo the Coyning of Money, and valuation of it by their <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Wiſedomes,</hi> are eſſentiall Notes of their abſolute Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; ſo that putting all together, ſeeing GOD to begin, and that KINGES were to follow, I read and ſpake out; <hi>Ab Ioue Principium</hi> (REGES) <hi>Iouis omnia plena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ For if <hi>All</hi> things that are be ſo by GOD directed to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Ends, by ſundry meanes and diſtinct operations, neither violent nor caſuall, as falling out by chance; his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fountaine of all Happineſſe, and <hi>Piety</hi> the top of all Morall Vertues. Let KINGES themſelues, both thinke and thanke GOD, and doe homage to <hi>Religion,</hi> by which all their Inſtruments become ſo iuſtly fitted. For if they that are <hi>Agents</hi> for <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Ciuill Gouernment,</hi> or ſit in high places for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance
<pb facs="tcp:183763:16"/>
of <hi>Iustice,</hi> thinke <hi>Pollicy</hi> a <hi>Trade</hi> fit for nothing but gaine; <hi>Formalities</hi> of <hi>Equity</hi> doe but ſmother <hi>Right,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Weale</hi> pretended, is turn'd to <hi>Common-Woe;</hi> making vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence their <hi>Load stone, Extreamity</hi> their <hi>Compaſſe,</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> the guide of all their beſt endeuours. But as <hi>Nullum violentum</hi> can be <hi>Perpetuum,</hi> ſo <hi>Careat ſucceſſibus opto Quiſquis ab euentu facta notanda putat.</hi> And ſo I concluded, <hi>Non temerè ferimur</hi> (DEVS) <hi>nec Nos Fortuna gubernat, ſed vita &amp; vitae Dux es &amp; ipſa via.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> being found the true Supporters and Fundamentall ſtayes of all <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes:</hi> I came at laſt to finde out our <hi>Commerce;</hi> for <hi>Iuctice</hi> beeing <hi>Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> as well as <hi>Diſtributiue;</hi> the <hi>Commutatiue</hi> part encludeth <hi>Traffique,</hi> which ſubſiſting of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> and conſiſting of <hi>Truth,</hi> both in <hi>Matter, Perſons, Place, Order,</hi> and <hi>End;</hi> I ſpeld and read thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Traffique</hi> is eyther a mutuall Free-bartring of <hi>Meum</hi> for <hi>Tuum,</hi> or direct buying and ſelling of vendible Wares by <hi>Marchants</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> according to the Rules of Reciproke Commerce, generally entending the SOVERAIGNES <hi>Honor,</hi> and SVBIECTS <hi>Wealth.</hi> Which deuiding it ſelfe into <hi>Outward</hi> and <hi>Inward,</hi> of things bred at home, or fet from abroad; three things there are, that by the Spirit of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> giues it three Degrees of Life, and thrice happy <hi>Beings.</hi>
               <note place="margin">BONVM.</note>
            </p>
            <q>COMMODITIES, MONEY, EXCHANGE.</q>
            <p>The firſt <hi>(Cata-pautos)</hi> as the <hi>Maſſe</hi> or <hi>Matter</hi> in the Bodie of Commerce, vpheld the Worlde by <hi>Weight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The rule of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> by <hi>Weight</hi> in <hi>Quantity.</hi>
               </note> bartring <hi>Good</hi> thinges for <hi>Good</hi> thinges, (cald <hi>Wares</hi> or <hi>Commodities</hi>) at the <hi>Standart</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> till <hi>Fraud</hi> came in.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, <hi>(Cat'autos)</hi> as the Blood or the Soule to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all the Body, a <hi>Weight</hi> of <hi>Soueraigne Worth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Rule of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> by <hi>Weight</hi> and <hi>Number,</hi> in <hi>Quantity</hi> and <hi>Quality.</hi>
               </note> to maintaine <hi>Equity</hi> in <hi>Actions,</hi> and <hi>Equalitie</hi> in <hi>Wares,</hi> and diſtinguiſh <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Meum,</hi> as well by <hi>Number</hi> as <hi>Weight</hi> at the <hi>Standart</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> made <hi>Good</hi> things firſt vendible by the Name of <hi>Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third, <hi>(Cat'holou proton)</hi> like the Spirit in the Soule, giues life to all the Body at the Standart of <hi>Wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Rule of <hi>Wiſedome</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> by <hi>Number, Waight,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> in <hi>Quantity, Quality,</hi> and <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> directing proportions of <hi>Good, Better,</hi> and <hi>Best,</hi> to <hi>Number, Weigh,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> the true worth and vſe of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> for <hi>Quantitie, Quality,</hi> and in all vendible thinges, as well by <hi>Money,</hi> as in <hi>Money</hi> it ſelfe, by the Name of <hi>Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt, whilſt <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> made all thinges alike,<note place="margin">Honeſtum.</note> knew not the Titles of <hi>Kinges</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> but magnified <hi>Honeſtie</hi> in the Actions of <hi>Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, is that Meanes or right hand of <hi>Iustice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Honour.</note> which Crowning KINGS, laid the firſt Foundation of PREHEMINENCE
<pb facs="tcp:183763:17"/>
and <hi>Dignity;</hi> and fixt <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reuerence</hi> in the perſons of Men, to ſhew the Diſtinction betweene SOVERAIGNES and SVBIECTS.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Maieſtie.</note>The third, by the <hi>Forme</hi> ſhewes vs MAIESTIES owne Face betweene <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum,</hi> and the abſolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Soueraignes</hi> ouer <hi>Subiectes,</hi> by tranſcendent PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROGATIVE of <hi>Mercy, Loue,</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> that of Mortall Men makes GODS on Earth.</p>
            <p>Then putting all together, to ſhew the ſenſe and meaning, I ſpeld and read out thus.</p>
            <p>¶ By <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> I meant that beautifull aſpect, and beneficiall influence of <hi>Soueraigne Beatitude,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Soueraignty.</note> which the <hi>Grecians</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the <hi>Calocagathia,</hi> ſanctifying and aſſuring the <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, Formall,</hi> and <hi>Finall Endes</hi> of all <hi>Happy Beings</hi> efficientlie; for <hi>Bono ſuo conſtant omnia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Commodities,</hi> I meant all <hi>Goodneſſe-fixt,</hi> what, where, &amp; howſoeuer, but cheefely or <hi>Catexochen,</hi> and <hi>Inſtar omnium,</hi> the Elementall perfections of <hi>Fineneſſe</hi> and <hi>Pureneſſe,</hi> in <hi>Golde</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Weight.</note> by the Name of <hi>Bullion;</hi> laid out by Nature at the <hi>Standart</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> to <hi>Weigh</hi> the proportions of <hi>Good, Better,</hi> and <hi>Beſt,</hi> for extention of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and eaſe of Commerce, for as <hi>Omne Bonum eſt ſui diffuſiuum,</hi> ſo <hi>quantò communius eò ſemper melius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Money,</hi> I meant thoſe figured proportions of <hi>Number</hi> ioynd with <hi>Weight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Weight and Number.</note> laid out by Art at the <hi>Standart</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> for <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> to meaſure <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> by in vendible thinges, through the naturall perfection and worth of it ſelfe: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quod vſpiam naſcitur Boni id apud omnes affluat:</hi> which none but <hi>Kings</hi> may Coyne, and <hi>Monarkes</hi> make currant by their abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute powerfulneſſe, and powerfull <hi>Preheminence,</hi> becauſe <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne quod efficit Tale, id ipſum ſemper magis Tale est &amp; eſſe opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by <hi>Exchange,</hi> I meant that Rule of Order, in <hi>Wiſedome, Pollicy,</hi> and <hi>Gouernment</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> which viſibly demonſtrates by <hi>Weight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Weight. Number. Meaſure.</note> 
               <hi>Number,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> thoſe honorable aſpects of MAIESTY and SOVERAIGNTY, that GOD from Heauen imparts to KINGS on Earth, within their owne Dominions, by their owne ſtamps in <hi>Money</hi> materially, for the furtherance of <hi>Traffique</hi> in vendible thinges.<note place="margin">Traffique.</note> That as <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> diuinelie ſublimate in all commodious thinges, becomes fixt by conſent in <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bullion.</note> by the Name of <hi>Bullion.</hi> And <hi>Bullion</hi> onely Coynd, receiuing life in it ſelfe by <hi>Soueraigne</hi> Authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes currant withall, through all the members of vendible Commerce, to ſhew the <hi>Preheminence</hi> that <hi>Soueraignes</hi> haue of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> aboue their <hi>Subiectes</hi> by the meanes of <hi>Money:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Money.</note> So <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ordering <hi>Proportions</hi> by <hi>Meaſures,</hi> more or leſſe,<note place="margin">Exchange.</note> to ſhew the vſe of <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> as well in all thinges by Coyne, as in Coyne it ſelfe, ſets forth the PREROGATIVE of their abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>Powers, Prudence, Prouidence, Mildeneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe of <hi>Bullion</hi> being cheefely <hi>Money,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bullion.</note> to ſet forth SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERAIGNTY, and ſhew MAIESTY by, as it were face to face.</p>
            <p>The vſe of <hi>Money,</hi> to make <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> vendible,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Money. Traffique.</hi> Honeſtum Vtile. <hi>Order. Artes. Trades. Calling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ars Artiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>(Moneta) or</hi> vera Ars reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi. <hi>Moneta</hi> autem dicta quaſi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens ne quid fraudis, in Materia ſigne vel pondere fiat.</p>
               </note> for the quicke diſpatch and eaſe of <hi>Traffiicke.</hi> And the <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Traffique</hi> the <hi>Soueraignes Honour, Subiects Wealth,</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes Peace,</hi> ſtill moouing and diſpoſing all Mens ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors by willing courſes, and perpetuall motions, in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Arts, Trades,</hi> and <hi>Callings,</hi> to ſerue and worke for ONE: and that ONE made able to maintaine the <hi>Syntheſis</hi> and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Traffique,</hi> in ſeruing all Mens turnes by his <hi>Art</hi> of Coyning <hi>Money,</hi> and <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I ſet downe as breefely as I could, how <hi>Traffique</hi> is the hand that layes out all Men their worke, prouides all men their foode, and payes all Men their Fees; and therefore ought at all hands to be ſeriouſly ſuppoorted that ſo ſupports vs all, and her willing <hi>Diſturbers</hi> and witting <hi>Peruerters,</hi> held enemies to <hi>Order;</hi> that's to ſay, to GOD and Nature.</p>
            <p>But as out of <hi>Confuſion Perfection</hi> firſt was drawne, when GOODNES, TRVTH, and WISEDOME, by the Name of DEITY, conſulting together, made MAN the firſt Modell of Perfection like it ſelfe, for the vſe of <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All;</hi> and GRACE begetting BOVNTY by GREATNES and DECORVM, fixt MAIESTY and SOVERAINGTY in the Perſons of ſome Men by the Name of KINGES, for all <hi>Subiectes</hi> Weale; that Nature teaching all Men howe to ſeeke <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> and ayme at <hi>Perfection</hi> by the Rules of <hi>Order</hi> and Degrees of <hi>Goodneſſe:</hi> ſo the mingling or miſtaking of things by ſpeech or writing, which GOD hath diſtinguiſht &amp; Nature deuided, is the ground whereon <hi>Ignorance</hi> by <hi>Diſcord</hi> and <hi>Diſorder</hi> drawes all to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, as before I breefely toucht, when I came to ſpell <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Subſidies, Impostes,</hi> and <hi>Impoſitions;</hi> where I ſhew'd in their Collections, that <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> cald <hi>Subſidies,</hi> and <hi>Subſidies Impoſitions,</hi> and all put together ſeeming nothing elſe, but <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> haue brought <hi>Traffick</hi> to diſorder, <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> to diſgrace, and their <hi>Customes</hi> (I may ſay) <hi>Almoſt</hi> to confuſion.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Almoſt</hi> was neuer hang'd. Yet as a <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> ſans <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes,</hi> ſince my Credit's out of date, let <hi>Experience</hi> nowe tell <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> if ſhe come not all to late; or if <hi>Quos</hi> DEVS <hi>perire vult, hos Ipſe non occaecat;</hi> What's become of <hi>Cuſtomes?</hi> And I will out of other words, ſo proſecute <hi>Diſorder,</hi> and the grounds of all debate, that common ſenſe ſhall ſee how <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> haue
<pb facs="tcp:183763:18"/>
reaſon to bemoane themſelues and others, before GOD and his LIEVTENANTS, and <hi>Traffiques</hi> poore eſtate.</p>
            <p>Namely, or <hi>Instar omnium,</hi> thoſe higheſt <hi>Attributes</hi> of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Sublimity,</hi> by <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum</hi> PREHEMINENCE and PREROGATIVE, but cheefely and <hi>Cat'exochen,</hi> thoſe ſacred <hi>Mysteries</hi> of heauenly and earthly <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> by <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> the EVCHARIST and EXCHANGE. The firſt two miſtaken and confounded together, are both become abuſd: the other two profaned by the MASSE and VSVRY. For, beſides that milde and gratious word PREROGATIVE, &amp; <hi>Attribute</hi> of comfort, in whom al our fiue Vowels, <hi>a. e. i. o. u.</hi> that giue life to our <hi>Traffique,</hi> as well <hi>Downeward</hi> as <hi>Vpward</hi> by <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> in our firſt and free <hi>Election, Creation, Redemption, Vocation, Iustifying, Sanctifying,</hi> and <hi>Glorifying</hi> at laſt; appeare to bee vnited and meete all together; and by whom all our <hi>Mutes</hi> and <hi>Liquides</hi> are made to ſpeake, and ſound the daily preſeruation of our <hi>Liuings, Liberties, Liues, Honour,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of our Land, beeing taken and abuſd for ſterne PREHEMINENCE, with <hi>e.</hi> and <hi>i.</hi> only for <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Place:</hi> hath bred in the World ſuch dangerous contempts and Capitall Errors, againſt MAIESTY and SOVERAIGNTY in the height of all <hi>Sublimity;</hi> as no <hi>Power</hi> but the greateſt, nor <hi>Wiſedome</hi> but the graueſt, may, or can reforme.</p>
            <p>Beſides, this I ſay, thoſe other two, like Witchcraft or Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the beſt, namely, the MASSE and VSVRY, the one debauching GOODNES; the other equiuocating TRVTH, in the EVCHARIST and EXCHANGE; haue enchanted ſo our <hi>Traffique,</hi> as well <hi>Downeward</hi> and <hi>Vpward,</hi> in the Art of <hi>Piety</hi> and Rules of <hi>Religion:</hi> as <hi>Outward</hi> and <hi>Inward,</hi> in the Art of <hi>Equity</hi> and Rules of <hi>Iustice;</hi> that as <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by kept aſunder and cannot come together; ſo <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> can no way kiſſe each other, which makes vs all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy.</p>
            <p>For whereas all things by Nature affect to bee happie, and encline to <hi>Perfection</hi> by the Rules of <hi>Order,</hi> and degrees of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> whereof nothing on Earth is capable but <hi>Man,</hi> in regard of his Reaſon; and none but <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by a Doctrine of <hi>Humility, Patience,</hi> and <hi>Charitie,</hi> in the Art of <hi>Piety, aliàs Holineſſe, aliâs Godlineſſe, aliâs Felicity,</hi> laid vp in IESVS CHRIST, by meanes of the <hi>Myſteries</hi> that belong to <hi>Religion, (Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Euchariſt)</hi> through <hi>Faith</hi> &amp; <hi>Repentance</hi> in a Kingdome of <hi>Obedience, Mercy, Loue</hi> and <hi>Grace;</hi> obtaine it in <hi>Heauen:</hi> The MASSE ſeeing <hi>Catholikes</hi> enquire the way thither, tels them of a <hi>Place</hi> without the Boundes of <hi>Nature,</hi> neuer ſeene, found, nor heard of, on Earth, nor in Heauen, but fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide out by Dreames, VTOPIA, <hi>aliâs</hi> PVRGATORY. And
<pb facs="tcp:183763:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of a Doctrine how to merit Heauen, if they liſt of themſelues, &amp; for themſelues and others (their Friends at the leaſt) by <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteron Proteron,</hi> and Rules of <hi>Diſorder,</hi> changing <hi>Patience</hi> to <hi>Preſumption, Humility</hi> into <hi>Pride, Loue</hi> to <hi>Rebellion,</hi> turning Creatures into <hi>Gods, Gods</hi> into <hi>Idols,</hi> and CHRIST into AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TI-CHRIST, and <hi>Metamorphoſing Grace,</hi> turne <hi>Grace</hi> into <hi>Merits,</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> into <hi>Lyes,</hi> by an Art of <hi>Impiety,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſticall Popery eclipſing MAIESTY in GOD.</note> 
               <hi>aliâs Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, aliâs Hereſie, aliâs Popery,</hi> in a Kingdome of <hi>Preſumption, Merits,</hi> and <hi>Free-will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas GOODNES, TRVTH, and WISEDOME, ſubſiſting together by Name of DEITY, made Man the firſt Modell of Perfection like it ſelfe, for the vſe and <hi>Good</hi> of <hi>All.</hi> And GRACE making BOVNTY to ſubſiſt in <hi>Humanity,</hi> by the GREATNES of it ſelfe, fixt MAIESTY and SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAINGTY in the Perſons of ſome Men by the name of KINGS, for all <hi>Subiectes</hi> Weale; by an <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Equity, aliâs Probity, aliâs Honesty, aliâs Honour, aliâs Order, aliâs</hi> worldly <hi>Happineſſe:</hi> and a <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in all <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> cald Royall <hi>Exchange: Vſury</hi> ſeeing <hi>Subiects</hi> ſeeke <hi>Happineſſe</hi> on Earth by the helpe of <hi>Golde</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi> and ſeeking to behold the MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIE of KINGES ſtill liuely repreſented, as it were in a Mirroer, by the ſtamps of their Coynes, tels the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a way from <hi>Beggars-Alley</hi> to <hi>Rich-mans Row,</hi> beyond <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> or the Rules of right and reaſon, by the ſound and ſight of Coyne, without <hi>Exchange</hi> for any thing, or altering the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety,</hi> making <hi>Money</hi> ſeeme a <hi>God,</hi> that's but a Creature to <hi>Kings,</hi> as <hi>Kings</hi> are to <hi>God;</hi> by <hi>Couetiſe</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring but the ſtamps that SOVERAIGNES put in Coyne, as the <hi>Heathen</hi> did their Idols, REMPHAM and RHYMMON, by an Art of <hi>Extortion, aliâs Iudaiſme,</hi> thereby deriuing <hi>Maieſty</hi> from beyond the Bounds of <hi>Royalty,</hi> and erecting ſuch a <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty</hi> aboue <hi>Empires</hi> and <hi>Monarchies,</hi> that <hi>Cardinals</hi> ſtand for <hi>Kinges,</hi> or <hi>Anti-Kinges</hi> at leaſt, by <hi>Flattery, Pride, Preſumption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secular Popery ecliſing MAIESTY in KINGS.</note> 
               <hi>Couetiſe,</hi> and <hi>Money,</hi> in a Kingdome of <hi>Rebellion, aliâs High-Treaſon, aliâs Popery:</hi> whereby the World, as in an extaſie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd and bewitcht, ſeemes ſtill to ſtand and wonder howe <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Preſumption,</hi> the one, Motiue to <hi>Sinne,</hi> the other fall of <hi>Angels</hi> ſhould make <hi>Couetouſnes</hi> the roote of all <hi>Euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> finding that <hi>Popery</hi> alone eclipſing MAIESTY, both in GOD and KINGS, becomes the only let, to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and earthly happineſſe, by means of the <hi>Maſſe</hi> (the bane of <hi>Religion</hi>) Ecle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtically, and by means of <hi>Vſury,</hi> (the bane by <hi>Iuſtice</hi>) ſecularly: Leauing the <hi>Maſſe</hi> to Diuines, and entending direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſearch and fift out <hi>Vſury;</hi> is heere interrupted by <hi>Ignarance</hi> and her <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</hi>
               </note> and the loue of <hi>Money</hi> to bee flat <hi>Idolatry;</hi> that's to ſay, <hi>Popery,</hi> though GOD himſelfe haue ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Ignorance.)</hi> VTOPIA <hi>aliâs</hi> PVRGATORY? <hi>Impiety, aliâs Hereſie? Extortion, aliâs Iudaiſme? Iniquity aliâs Rebelion? Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetiſe, Deceipt?</hi> And the loue of <hi>Money</hi> to be flat <hi>Idolatry?</hi> The one from the <hi>Maſſe;</hi> the other, from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> and all to end in <hi>Popery, Popery</hi> in <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> with <hi>High-Treaſon?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
What ſpelling call you this? And how hang theſe words toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Since the Queſtion is of <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> which <hi>Catholiques</hi> by <hi>Deuotion,</hi> and the World ſeekes for by <hi>Money?</hi> For grant that <hi>Impiety</hi> ſhould lurke within the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and pretendeth moſt <hi>Deuotion,</hi> yet howe becomes <hi>Iniquity</hi> a conſequence of <hi>Popery,</hi> though the <hi>Maſſe</hi> ſhould ſeeme <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> ſauour <hi>Rebellion?</hi> Can you Paralell the <hi>Maſſe</hi> with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> and the <hi>Eucharist</hi> with <hi>Exchange?</hi> And yet proue a flat <hi>Antitheſis</hi> betweene the one and the other, oppoſing the <hi>Maſſe</hi> to the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> and <hi>Vſury</hi> to <hi>Exchange?</hi> The <hi>Maſſe</hi> pretending <hi>Piety,</hi> as well as the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> and <hi>Exchange</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſing the daily vſe of <hi>Money,</hi> no leſſe then <hi>Vſury?</hi> Heere muſt needes bee Witch-craft, ſome Sorcery, ſome Iugling, a <hi>Paradox</hi> at leaſt, or a <hi>Mystery</hi> as you faine.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Ignorance</hi> ſtill tels <hi>Catholiques,</hi> that my ſpelling is but idle, and my labour all in vaine; therefore to helpe them out of this maze, I muſt turne the Leafe againe, for herein lyes the <hi>Mystery</hi> indeede that puts vs all to paine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cuſtomer forced to returne to his former grounds, to ſatisfie <hi>Ignorance</hi> about the Myſtery of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity.</hi>
               </note>It is granted at all handes, and Nature makes it good, that <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> haue euer gone together, their Vnion bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo naturall, that where both of them are not, there can be neither. Now for <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> Diuines haue laid it open, that the way from wretchedneſſe to <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> is by <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and finding <hi>Reformation</hi> to ſpeede beſt in looking backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, haue happily made vs happy, by reducing the <hi>Eucharist</hi> to her firſt Inſtitution, and branded the <hi>Maſſe</hi> with Idolatrous <hi>Impiety,</hi> &amp; Heathen <hi>Superstition,</hi> which being made ſo intricate by opinions and diſputes, may bee plainely diſcerned by ſenſe and reaſon thus.</p>
            <p>Looke but what the <hi>Glaſſe</hi> of a Chriſtall Mirroer is (beeing ſpecially fitted by <hi>Art</hi> as well as <hi>Nature</hi>) to demonſtrate and expreſſe the liuely face and feature of all that can but ſee, and haue eyes to looke into it, though the thing repreſented by tranſubſtantiating nor conſubſtanting with it, bee neither of the <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> not any waies within it: the ſame is the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> to all intents and vſes, by GOD &amp; MAN ſo fitted, and by CHRIST himſelfe ordained, that as well his <hi>Deity</hi> in Diuinity, as <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> in <hi>Humanity,</hi> are therein repreſented by bleſſed <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> to all capable of Saluation, by <hi>Wit, Will,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> to beleeue withal, that his patient reall ſufferings, &amp; actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all word of <hi>Promiſe,</hi> are the only all-ſufficient means to purge our <hi>Imperfections,</hi> and perfect all our <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> and to frame their liues accordingly, vſe ſtill their beſt endeuours; though his Perſon then at Supper, held his Place there with others, and reſiding now in Heauen, be from thence to fetch vs thither. I ſay ſpecially fitted, and ſuch as can diſcerne with their own eies
<pb facs="tcp:183763:19"/>
and ſee, for though all <hi>Glaſſe</hi> be needfull for ſome vſe or other, yet all haue not power, nor are fitted to that <hi>End,</hi> and with blinde Men or Hood-winkt, euen Myrrors are but idle: And <hi>Grace</hi> I ſaid withall, to beleeue beyond our ſight, for though our wits by Art and Nature, may be capable of <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> and our wils haue reaſon to bee forward to deſire it, yet as <hi>Grace</hi> reſides in <hi>Heauen,</hi> and from thence begets <hi>Beleefe;</hi> ſo <hi>Faith</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone aboue with <hi>Grace,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Charity</hi> below to worke out our Saluation, takes vs by the hand to lift vs vp thither. Whereby <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> the one Fountaine of all Graces, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Obedience;</hi> the other, Bond of all <hi>Perfection,</hi> maintaine as it were a free continuall <hi>Trafficke,</hi> betweene the <hi>Throne</hi> of GOD in <hi>Heauen,</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> vpon <hi>Earth,</hi> by Doctrine and Prayer for the daily vſe of <hi>Goodneſſe.</hi> His heauenly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings <hi>Downewards,</hi> and our holy deſires <hi>Vpwards,</hi> being as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> or <hi>Marchants</hi> betweene <hi>Him</hi> and vs.
<q>
                  <l>Yet if this may not ſerue to make thine eies to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Hold, vſe my dim Spectacles, come ſit thee downe by me:<note place="margin">The <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> heere endeuors his beſt, by the happineſſe of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate <hi>Exchange,</hi> the better to expreſſe at laſt the Myſticall Miſery of <hi>Vſury.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And read thy ſelfe, or hearke at leaſt, chuſe whether,</l>
                  <l>How Chriſt and his Church (by this meanes) become</l>
                  <l>(wedded ſtill together.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>First heare, then ſee, then like, then loue, and then liue, be fiue</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>good points in wiuing:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If thou wilt liue a happy life, but ſtill remember thriuing.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
But for a true and liuely patterne, ſee two moſt happy Louers,<note place="margin">The orderly wooing, Princelie proceeding, ioyfull enterview, and firſt meeting together of FRIDERICK the fift, <hi>Count-Palatine</hi> of <hi>Rhyne, &amp;c.</hi> and the Lady ELIZABETH, Princeſſe of <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> Sole-Daughter to KING IAMES: fore-ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their likings to be honorable, their loues to be ſanctified, their mariage to be bleſſed, and them ſelues to be moſt happy, by the Grace of GOD and general ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaude of all. For <hi>Vox</hi> POPVLI <hi>vox</hi> DEI <hi>eſt.</hi>
               </note> that but lately came together, who wooing by their Pictures, as it were in a Myrroer, each harkning after other, came at laſt both to ſee, and by ſeeing, both to like, and by liking both to loue, that though <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> both, deſeru'd to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, that had wrought and wooed ſo well; yet <hi>Grace</hi> was moſt admired, when comming both together, they ſaw, they met, they kiſt. To whom now <hi>All</hi> wiſh all <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> and I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, for the good of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> both; that as our <hi>Euchariſt</hi> hath blinded the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and prou'd it but a lie, ſo <hi>Exchange</hi> may hood-winke <hi>Popery,</hi> and thruſt out her eye. I meane <hi>Vſury. Ignorance.</hi> What <hi>Catholiques</hi> and all, doe they reioyce with others, and <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> to? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Yea, <hi>Catholiques</hi> I meane, for good <hi>Catholikes</hi> are good <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> where euer they goe? <hi>Impudence.</hi> And are <hi>Customers</hi> then <hi>Chriſtians? Cuſtomer.</hi> Yea, and <hi>Kentiſh-men</hi> too? <hi>Diſcretion.</hi> Then may they be honeſt, and ſo become happy? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> It may be we hope well, but let that matter goe.</p>
            <p>Now this alone thus fitted for Common ſenſe and reaſon, to ſhew the vſe of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> repreſented by a Glaſſe: euen as in a <hi>Glaſſe</hi> or <hi>Myrroer,</hi> without <hi>Impiety</hi> or <hi>Iniquity</hi> illuſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:183763:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
our <hi>Exchange:</hi> But in the <hi>Maſſe</hi> and <hi>Vſury</hi> by meere <hi>Deceptio viſus,</hi> or ſome <hi>Legierte-de-maine,</hi> it is vrged otherwiſe, which prooues both the <hi>Antitheſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The oppoſition or <hi>Antitheſis</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Maſſe</hi> and <hi>Vſury,</hi> to the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> and <hi>Exchange</hi> heere prooued.</note> and the Iugling of the <hi>Medium.</hi> For euen as if the <hi>Myrroer</hi> had life both to quicken, and power withall to change all within it, or about it, by turning Signes into Subſtances, and Shadowes into Bodies: <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in the <hi>Maſſe</hi> is adored for a GOD; and in <hi>Vſury,</hi> the very Stamps which <hi>Soueraignes</hi> doe but put vpon their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and their Coynes, are worſhipped for Idols.</p>
            <p>This being the State of <hi>Traffique,</hi> for heauenly <hi>Happineſſe</hi> at this day in GREAT-BRITAINE, in regard of true <hi>Religion,</hi> by meanes of the <hi>Eucharist</hi> reſtored and maintained by our Learned graue <hi>Diuines,</hi> and defended by our <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> I leaue to our <hi>Lyturgie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Lyturgie</hi> of the Churches of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </note> and as a <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> and Lay <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Man, out of <hi>Iuſtice Commutatiue</hi> I am confident for <add>Exchange</add> and dare ſpeake boldly thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Exchange</hi> in buying and ſelling of vendible thinges (for I meane not mutuall bartring, <add>of wares fro ware</add> though the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety by either be altered and gone, nor lending out of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> though it looſe by the loane.) I confeſſe moſt willinglie, ſtill preſuppoſeth <hi>Money,</hi> as <hi>Money, Golde</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Bullion,</hi> and that <hi>Money</hi> muſt be Coynd. Now though Coyning and Creating bee wordes of like import, as meerely <hi>Synonimas,</hi> and meane but one <hi>Power</hi> fitting none but GOD &amp; KINGS; yet heerein they varry. GODS <hi>Power</hi> in Creating being abſolutely abſolute, is onely al-ſufficient, and ſubſiſteth of it ſelfe immediatly: and that of KINGES beeing likewiſe abſolute within their owne Dominions, is but ſo by GODS Commiſſion mediatly. GODS <hi>Power</hi> is likewiſe infinite all manner of waies, both in Heauen and in Earth, and his <hi>Will</hi> the onely Motiue of all his owne Endeuours: the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Wils</hi> of KINGS, are bounded with their Kingdomes, <hi>Ex Legum Preſcriptis, ne euadant in Tyrannos,</hi> or become like other Men. GOD without a Patterne, Creates all <hi>Thinges</hi> of <hi>Nothing,</hi> by the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of Himſelfe, and Man aboue all for his owne vſe and glory, and his other Creatures <hi>Good. Kinges</hi> by <hi>Gods</hi> Example, by their owne fixed <hi>Honour,</hi> finding truſt in their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and putting credit in their <hi>Subiectes,</hi> adde <hi>Honour</hi> vnto <hi>Honeſty, Nobility</hi> vnto <hi>Honour,</hi> and creat it in others by the <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> of themſelues: And by their Pictures ſtampt in <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> value <hi>Goodnes</hi> in all things by the <hi>Truth</hi> of their proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of <hi>Good, Better,</hi> and <hi>Best,</hi> both in <hi>Number, Weight,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> expreſſed in their Coynes by the Name of <hi>Money,</hi> to their own ſpecial <hi>Honor</hi> firſt, and then their <hi>Subiects Wealth,</hi> for both muſt go together, though they may not be confounded;
<pb facs="tcp:183763:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Honestum</hi> firſt, then <hi>Vtile,</hi> nor <hi>Vtile</hi> firſt, nor <hi>Honestum</hi> alone,<note place="margin">Honeſtum &amp; Vtile.</note> or <hi>Vtile</hi> without <hi>Honestum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Word, GOD created all things by the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that his MAIESTY might be ſeene, &amp; his SOVERAIGN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY ſubſiſt in the <hi>Order</hi> of his working all the Worlde ouer, though himſelfe reſide in Heauen, and the <hi>Beauty</hi> of his <hi>Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in his ſanctified <hi>Temples:</hi> But <hi>Kinges</hi> muſt haue matter to fixe their <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in, which is that we call <hi>Bullion;</hi> that the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> aboue other Men, that's to ſay, their <hi>Bounties,</hi> that's to ſay their <hi>Honour,</hi> I meane that their <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> by their Faces and their Armes may be ſeene, and their <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignties</hi> ſubſiſt in the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of their Coyne, as in a <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roer,</hi> all their Kingdomes through: though their perſons bee ſeen to ſit vpright in their <hi>Throns,</hi> or reſide in their Seats of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> betweene <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum;</hi> namely, in their Courts of <hi>Equity, Subalterne,</hi> and <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> for <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum Diſtributiuely,</hi> and <hi>Mints</hi> of <hi>Equalities,</hi> and <hi>Staples</hi> of free <hi>Commerce Commutatiuely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby it now appeares, how by all mens conſent <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi> the Seats of fixed <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> by the Name of <hi>Bullion,</hi> become <hi>Ab Effectis,</hi> as it were <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queene</hi> of the world, becauſe theſe alone make <hi>Kinges</hi> in their <hi>Thrones</hi> powerfull, to protect both their <hi>Subiects</hi> and their <hi>Friendes,</hi> both by Sea and by Land,<note place="margin">Trafficke, Lapis Philoſophicus.</note> and diſpoſe of <hi>Trafficke</hi> by their owne <hi>Elixars</hi> and <hi>Mines,</hi> or <hi>Load-stones</hi> of price within their owne Dominions; as <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> their onely Iudge and Patterne, both in <hi>Number, Weight,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> firſt made the World, and ſtill doth guide the ſame.</p>
            <p>Each <hi>King</hi> in this reſpect being a liuely <hi>Idea,</hi> euen of <hi>Deity</hi> it ſelfe, ſo much excelling in <hi>Preheminency</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> for his <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> and <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> of <hi>Wiſedome</hi> for <hi>Bounty</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> by how much they endeuour to expreſſe in themſelues, and ſhew foorth to others the Characters of MAIESTY, and Titles of their SOVERAIGNTY in the truth of their Coyne. I meane by their <hi>Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how <hi>Exchange</hi> alone becomes that Cordiall preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, which eaſing all Greefes in ſores,<note place="margin">Exchange, Vniuerſalis medicina.</note> ſuppling all ſores in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and curing all diſeaſes in particular Members, holds the whole Bodies of Kingdomes in health; the ſacred Rules where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as no profane Couetiſe could euer comprehend, nor confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Empericke</hi> attaine to practiſe, ſo none of priuate difcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or partiall affection, may preſume to alter, or any way controle, as beeing a Doctrine peculiar vnto none, but the <hi>Graueſt</hi> and <hi>Wiſeſt</hi> in higheſt Authority, and <hi>Soueraignes</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bullion</hi> therefore <hi>Catexochen,</hi> that's to ſay, all kinde of <hi>Golde</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and <hi>Siluer</hi> not Coyn'd or made currant, (for euen Coynes that are not currant may be taken for <hi>Bullion</hi>) by generall conſent, as the Sunne in the higheſt Globe of <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Money</hi> beeing the <hi>Beames; Exchange</hi> becomes the light that makes the world to ſee: And as <hi>Bullion</hi> beeing the <hi>Pylot, Money</hi> is the <hi>Sterne,</hi> and <hi>Exchange</hi> the <hi>Compaſſe</hi> that guides all courſes right; nay, as <hi>Bullion</hi> being the <hi>Chylus, Money</hi> is the Blood, <hi>Exchange</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the <hi>Spirit</hi> that quickens all the Body. In a word, <hi>Bullion</hi> being the Body and very Blood of KINGS. <hi>Money</hi> is the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> betweene <hi>Subiects</hi> and their <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Exchange</hi> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Cyment</hi> that glewes them both together.
<q>
                  <l>O that my Tongue or Pen were able to expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Or had the guift to make Men vnderſtand</l>
                  <l>Thoſe great and graund effects, of Sacred <hi>Happineſſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exchange</hi> alone would worke by <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi> hand:</l>
                  <l>Religious <hi>Iuſtice</hi> would then ſo bleſſe our Land,</l>
                  <l>That Men on Earth might ſee, by this <hi>Idea</hi> made,</l>
                  <l>What Heauen it ſelfe doth boad, by this our Kingly Trade.</l>
               </q>
Seeing then that <hi>Bullion,</hi> or <hi>Gold</hi> &amp; <hi>Siluer</hi> Coynd, is the Bodie and Blood of <hi>Kings,</hi> not as <hi>Men</hi> but as <hi>Gods,</hi> truely repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the comfort of their <hi>Subiects</hi> through all their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the ſtampes of their <hi>Money,</hi> though their Perſons keepe their <hi>Thrones.</hi> And <hi>Exchange</hi> that Spirit of <hi>Traffique</hi> and My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall <hi>Cyment,</hi> that glewes ſo faſt together the communion and coniuction of <hi>Soueraignes</hi> and <hi>Subiects,</hi> by Reciproke <hi>Loue</hi> &amp; <hi>Grace,</hi> as <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> both, teach vs to beleeue:</p>
            <p>Let's all cry out of <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein firſt was hatcht the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that enchants and tranſubſtantiates our <hi>Eucharisticke Sacraments</hi> of the Body and Blood of CHRIST, repreſented euery where within his Church Militant, as liuely as in a <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> till his comming againe (though his Perſon be in Heauen) by bleſſed <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> into Idolatrous <hi>Maſſes;</hi> and our <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Exchange,</hi> into <hi>Iewiſh Vſury.</hi> I ſpeake therefore with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to all that ſeeke for <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> and loue their owne Saluation, not bewitcht as it were, or void of ſence and reaſon, be wary ſtill of <hi>Italy,</hi> as <hi>Aeneas</hi> with his <hi>Miſſelto</hi> when he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueld towards <hi>Hell,</hi> and let all come home from <hi>Rome,</hi> for feare of the curſſe that by <hi>Iuſtice</hi> hangs vpon her.</p>
            <p>For if <hi>He</hi> alone, whoſe abſolute Power could work ſo wel, that all he made became ſtill like himſelfe, exceeding <hi>Good,</hi> to his own eternall <hi>Glory,</hi> and Mans immortall bliſſe. GOD I ſay, (the <hi>Father</hi>) GOD I meane (the <hi>Son</hi>) and GOD the third time, (the <hi>Spirit</hi>) though once for all. (The <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and <hi>Vnity</hi> in <hi>Trinity</hi>) whom onely to know is euerlaſting Life, and ioy but to heare and make mention of his Name; be that ſpring or Fountaine of <hi>Goodneſſe, Truth,</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> from whence
<pb facs="tcp:183763:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
all ſtreames beſides, both in Heauen and Earth deriue not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>Eſſence</hi> but <hi>Happineſſe</hi> in being, and whence to ſwarue, is to turne againe to nothing; <hi>Quia vidit Deus, quod omnia quae fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerat erant valde bona:</hi> What greater bane then Sinne?<note place="margin">Sinne. Pride.</note> What greater ſinne then <hi>Pride?</hi> What greater <hi>Pride</hi> then the height of all <hi>Preſumption</hi> in one ſinfull Man, that vſurping on the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers both of Heauen and Earth,<note place="margin">Darkeneſſe. Freewill. Profaneneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> to drowne Light in Darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, both in <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> of his owne meere Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wil, giues Lawes vnto <hi>Iustice,</hi> and profanes all <hi>Religion,</hi> the Rules of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodnes,</hi> both in <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Kings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If heauenly <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> in all <hi>Perfections,</hi> both of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi> be thoſe beautifull aſpects, and beneficiall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of heauenly beatitudes, which the <hi>Grecians</hi> do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe by their <hi>Calocogathia,</hi> to make al things happy;<note place="margin">Chaos. Euill.</note> 
               <hi>Quia Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ſuo diffuſiue &amp; verè constant omnia.</hi> What <hi>Euill</hi> ſo infectious? What infection ſo poyſonous, and what Poyſon ſo accurſed, as that <hi>Chaos</hi> of Doctrine, that by <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Preſumption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preſumption. Merits. Equiuocation.</note> profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> turnes <hi>Grace</hi> into <hi>Merits,</hi> and <hi>Equiuocating Truth,</hi> turnes <hi>Truth</hi> into Lyes, in all the Contractes, both of GOD and Men?</p>
            <p>If <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi> of all the ſollide Bodies which Nature preſents at the Standart of <hi>Truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Truth.</note> be fitteſt and ſureſt by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſent to fixe <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in, for eaſier extention in vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Commerce by the Name of <hi>Bullion. Quia omne Bonum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bullion.</note> being <hi>ſui diffuſiuum &amp; quantò communius eò melius, &amp; infun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur ſemper ſecundum meritum materiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fraude. Wrong. Priuate-Gaine. Couetiſe. Deceipt.</note> What fraud like pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique wrong? What wrong like priuate gaine? And what gain more deceiptfull, then couetouſly to hoard or ſophiſticate the pureneſſe and fineneſſe which Nature weighes in <hi>Bullion,</hi> for the generall vſe of <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> by <hi>Traffique</hi> among Men?</p>
            <p>If <hi>Money</hi> or <hi>Coyne</hi> bee thoſe figured proportions of <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> more or leſſe for <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Waight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Money.</note> by <hi>Maiesty</hi> layde out at the Standart of <hi>Iustice</hi> to value <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> by,<note place="margin">Iuſtice.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quòd vſpiam naſciter boni id apud omnes affluat;</hi> and by <hi>Soueraignty</hi> made currant in all vendible Commerce. <hi>Quia omne quod efficit Tale, id ipſum magis Tale eſſe ſemper oportet:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſ order Error. Iniuſtice.</note> What <hi>Danger</hi> like <hi>Diſorder?</hi> What <hi>Diſorder</hi> like to <hi>Errors?</hi> And what <hi>Error</hi> like <hi>Iniustice,</hi> when <hi>Subiectes</hi> become <hi>Coyners,</hi> the onely Trade of <hi>Kings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, if the Myſticall practiſe of <hi>Goodneſſe, Truth,</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> that is meant by <hi>Exchange,</hi> be that <hi>Ars Artium,</hi> and <hi>vera Ars regnandi,</hi> which viſibly demonſtrates thoſe heauenlie Aſpectes themſelues, of MAIESTY and SOVERAIGNTY, that <hi>Deity</hi> imparts vnto Mortall Men on Earth by the Name of KINGS, in the ſtamping of their Coyne: Or if the <hi>Standarts</hi> themſelues, with all their proportions of <hi>Weights, Numbers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Standarts. Proportions.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and <hi>Meaſures,</hi> for generall <hi>Equity</hi> bee the <hi>Soueraignes</hi> charge onely; as the Coynage of <hi>Money</hi> is their only <hi>Hoc-age,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to none but <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and <hi>Exchange</hi> their Compaſſe to guide all courſes right: what greater <hi>Error</hi> then <hi>Priuat-miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe?</hi> What greater Miſchiefe then publike Inconueniences? And what ſo inconuenient, as that which peruerting both the <hi>Waightes, Numbers,</hi> and <hi>Meaſures,</hi> in all our <hi>Proportions,</hi> and <hi>Worth</hi> of all our <hi>Standarts,</hi> debauching <hi>Equity</hi> in Actions, and profaining <hi>Piety</hi> in the Conſciences of Men, by a Myſticall <hi>Iniquitie</hi> threates ruine and confuſion to <hi>Empires, Kinges,</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iniquity. Vſury.</note> VSVRY. Againſt which Art of witch-craft.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Would God my Pen or Tongue could write or tell,</l>
               <l>Or had the guift to make Men vnderſtand,</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſtrong and ſtrange effects of miſchiefes hatcht in Hell,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Couetiſe</hi> by <hi>Vſury,</hi> begets in euery Land:</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Kinges</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi> both, would lift vp eyes and hand,</l>
               <l>To ſee on Earth by this <hi>Idea</hi> made,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Hell</hi> doth win, and <hi>Heauen</hi> doth looſe by this accurſed Trade.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So that, great out of queſtion are the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> by <hi>Impiety</hi> and <hi>Iniquity,</hi> through <hi>Pride, Preſumption, Couetiſe,</hi> and <hi>Money;</hi> the ſumme whereof is this: One Man of ſinfull Fleſh, obtruding vpon <hi>Deity,</hi> and diſpiſing <hi>Humanity,</hi> without remorſe of Conſcience, accurſed of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſupported by <hi>Cardinals,</hi> Preached by <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> admired ſtill by <hi>Flatterers,</hi> tels <hi>Catholiques</hi> of a <hi>Purgatory,</hi> but ſends them ſtraight to Hell; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not this the ſelfeſame ANTI-CHRIST ſo long ago foretold? that Childe of perdition? and profeſſed Aduerſary to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice?</hi> exalted aboue all that is or can be <hi>God,</hi> or fit to be adored? ſo ſeated in the <hi>Church</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> that he boaſtes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for GOD? and brauing <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Kinges,</hi> makes <hi>Emperours</hi> but his Footmen, and <hi>Kings</hi> his very vaſſals, in deſpight of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus as <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> the two generall Fountaines of heauenly &amp; earthly <hi>Happines,</hi> flowing euery way together from <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> haue the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> and <hi>Exchange</hi> by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> to maintaine their currents, for the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> good of <hi>Chriſtians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">How <hi>Impiety</hi> &amp; <hi>Iniquity</hi> meete in one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Popery,</hi> Eccleſiaſtically and Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</note> ſo <hi>Impiety</hi> and <hi>Iniquity</hi> the bane of all Felicity, begot and hatcht together in our Body of <hi>Popery,</hi> and Doctrine of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> by <hi>Merits</hi> and <hi>Free-will,</hi> haue the <hi>Maſſe</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> to bewitch the world from <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then the <hi>Maſſe</hi> oppoſed to our EVCHARIST, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our CREED (which enioynes vs to beleeue, as we look to be happy, that IESVS CHRIST himſelfe heere ſuffering for vs, and for our Saluation, aſcended vp to Heauen, and there
<pb facs="tcp:183763:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſitting by his <hi>Father,</hi> is thence to come againe to fet vs vp thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) muſt needes bee <hi>Hereſie</hi> by common Sence and Reaſon, in all that doe beleeue it; and a Sinne of higher Nature to ſuch as in their Conſciences being priuy to the contrary, yet ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill obdurat, refuſe their owne Saluation, and deſpiſe the Spirit of <hi>Grace:</hi> ſhall not <hi>Vſury</hi> then I ſay, be accounted high Treaſon? And then what is <hi>Popery</hi> wherein both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meete? But ſtand ſome-thing neerer, and reade further yet.</p>
            <p>If that MAN alone, whoſe Natiue <hi>Bounty</hi> proceeding from <hi>Grace,</hi> and gratious diſpoſition ſetting foorth his <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> aboue all other Men, makes himſelfe moſt honoured and reueren'ſt as a GOD, with all Mens conſent, by the Name of KING.</p>
            <p>If that KING I meane, whoſe Eſſence being <hi>Bullion,</hi> of the ſefe-ſame <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer</hi> (which none can Coyne but he, and ſhewes him to be KING) giues many a thouſand pound for his owne ſpeciall <hi>Honor,</hi> and benefit of all.</p>
            <p>Now if that ſelfe-ſame Perſon being thus thy MAN-KING GOD, to whom thy ſelfe among others, by Nature and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hauing vow'd thy Subiection as to thy lawfull SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNE, haſt ſworne Fealty and Allegiance, or ſhouldſt do at the leaſt; to comfort thee withall, and make thee ſtill minde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of his <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> ſhould giue thee but an <hi>Angell,</hi> a <hi>Shilling,</hi> or a <hi>Penny</hi> (for all comes to <hi>One: </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>How in GREAT-BRITTAINE, to keepe out Popes and Popery, by Number, Waight, and Meaſure, at One Srandart of <hi>Truth,</hi> aſ wel in
<list>
                        <item>RELIGLON Cathedrally.
<list>
                              <item>as IVSTICE <hi>Diſtributiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>y</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>ALL comes to ONE, and ONE with ALL togither, admire MAIESTY, no where fixt perſonally, but in
<list>
                        <item>¶ One GOD, eternall and only All-ſufficient, both in Heauen and Earth, by the rules of Religion.
<list>
                              <item>¶ One KING, ſucceſsiue, moſt powerfully ſubſiſtent both in Church &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, by the rules of <hi>Iuſtice</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>¶ ONE orderly Liturgie, for Vnity and Truth, in Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and Deuotion, in all Chappels, Churches, and Temples Cathedrally.
<list>
                              <item>¶ One reaſonable Lawe, for Obedience and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in Equitie and Right, in all Courts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice Subalterne and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, Diſtributiuely.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>¶ ONE common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to the Maieſty of <hi>ONE God,</hi> Creator, to auoide I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, and furtherance of our Trafficke vpward and downward, for the daylye vſe of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> called PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER-NOSTER.
<list>
                              <item>¶ ONE Currant kind of Mony, to auoid Diſloialty and ſhew the fixed Maieſty of one King Coyner, for furtherance of our Traffick outward &amp; inward, by <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; Tuum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                                 </hi> &amp; ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of <hi>Bullion,</hi> cald a <hi>Penny.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>¶ Twelue conſtant Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of One Standing <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> to auoide Impietie, make one Catholick <hi>Creed</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>¶ Twelue coined pence of one ſtanding alloy, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid Iniquity, make one currant ſhilling.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>¶ Ten perfect comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, concerning <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> containde in one Decalogue.
<list>
                              <item>¶ Ten currant ſhillinges betweene Soueraigne and Subiects, compriſd in one <hi>Angell.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>¶ Two Sacramentes of Grace, ſhew the Truth and Goodneſſe of one Head &amp; Sauiour, our Soueraigne <hi>per amount.</hi> Chriſt Ieſus.
<list>
                              <item>¶ Two Angels of Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhew the Greatnes and woorth of one <hi>Iacobus</hi> our Soueraigne <hi>per aual.</hi> and annointed King <hi>Iames.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>¶ In and through whoſe Goodneſſe by Prayer and Thankeſ-giuing. ONE &amp; ALL tog ther adoring Maieſty in Deity giue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to one God the Father, one God the Sonne, and one God the Holy Spirite of al Wiſedom Power, and Grace, with <hi>Alleluya</hi> in the Heauens, Peace on Earth, and Good-will amongeſt Men.
<list>
                              <item>¶ In and through whoſe Greatneſſe, by <hi>Bountie</hi> and <hi>Exchange,</hi> All and One to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, admiring M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ieſtie in Royalty: Honour one Kingdome of the Father, one Principality of the ſon, and the prouidenc wiſdom of one Priuy Counſel cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the kingdome tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, <hi>Beati Pacifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>,</hi> and God ſaue King <hi>Iames</hi> and his Poſterity.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
O the vnity or vnion <hi>(aliâs Happineſſe)</hi> of GREAT-BRITAINE, if <hi>Iuſtice Commutatiue (aliâs Traffique)</hi> had her <hi>Staples</hi> for <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> as <hi>Diſtributiue</hi> hath her <hi>Courts</hi> for <hi>Equity,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Temples</hi> for <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Deuotion!</hi> For her Home-borne <hi>Staples</hi> turnd to Mart-Townes beyond Seas, makes her at diſcor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> within her ſelfe, and a By-word to the world.</p>
                  <p>But who beleeues Truth from the mouth of a <hi>Cuſtomer?</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>) What would'ſt thou doe or ſay? He is honourable and louing, and expecting nought but Reciproke Loue and Thankes, vouchſafes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect thee of his owne meere Natiue <hi>Grace?</hi> Shouldſt not thou be likewiſe Loyall and honeſt at the leaſt, and with Duty, Fear, and Reuerence, reſpect his <hi>Honour</hi> when thou ſee'ſt it in his <hi>Picture,</hi> or beholdſt it as his Face, and in no wiſe to abuſe it? And as <hi>He</hi> by free guift, or his owne firſt <hi>Exchange,</hi> did value ir vnto thee by the worth of Himſelfe, and receiues it ſo again: ſo thou, vnto another beeing ſtampt for his <hi>Honour,</hi> and thy mutuall <hi>Good?</hi> Can any be ſo mad then, or fooliſh at the beſt, (I ſpeake to ſenſe and reaſon, let <hi>Ieſuites</hi> alwaies goe, <hi>Rumpan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; ilia Codro</hi>) as to ſay, beleeue or thinke that this KINGS Royall Perſon, in Body, Blood, or Bone, is any way within it, when hee ſees, or heares, or knowes him to bee ſitting in his <hi>Throne,</hi> or reſiding elſe-where? Yet ſuch is the Witch-craft wherewith <hi>Ieſuites</hi> in <hi>Popery</hi> enchanting the Worlde, ſeduce poore Catholikes by the <hi>Maſſe</hi> in this kind, and damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Free-will</hi> and <hi>Merits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now thinke but ere thou ſpeake, and then ſpeake, but as thou think'ſt as thy conſcience doth aduiſe thee, without equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation. Had not I then reaſon, out of <hi>Duty, Feare,</hi> &amp; <hi>Zeale,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the <hi>Honour</hi> of ſacred KINGS, and <hi>Good</hi> of all <hi>Catholiques,</hi> (not yet voyde of Conſcience) by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Adoption, to cry out as I did, againſt the Witch-craft of <hi>Popery, aliâs Vſury,</hi> and that <add> Man od Sinne, and</add> 
               <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> in theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes following:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Au Loup pourtant Subiects, Monarches tous et Roys</l>
                     <l>Ça Chrestiens, Catholiques, Estats trestous, en ſomme</l>
                     <l>Ça Ça tous Princes libres, Defenſeurs de la Foy</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enez tous a la chaſſe du Loup-Garou de Rome.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heere therefore</hi> Subiects <hi>all, heere</hi> Kings <hi>and</hi> Monarkes <hi>eyther,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heere heere you</hi> Princes <hi>free, and</hi> States <hi>both all and ſome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heere</hi> Chriſtian Kings <hi>and</hi> Catholiques, <hi>come now ioyne hands together,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Defend with vs the</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Faith, and rowſe this Wolfe of</hi> Rome.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, <hi>Ab Ioue principium</hi> (REGES) <hi>Iouis omnia plena.</hi> And to giue GOD thankes withall, for the bleſſed Memories of our <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Peeres,</hi> that heeretofore with-ſtood him, and thrice bleſſed learned hand of our SOVERAIGNES late Endeuours that ſo conſtantly purſues him. For as CHRIST now puts down <hi>Anti-Chriſt,</hi> make <hi>Cardinals</hi> crooch to KINGS, that would ſeeme <hi>Anti-Kinges,</hi> and as the <hi>Maſſe</hi> giues way to the <hi>Eucharist;</hi> ſo make <hi>Vſury</hi> know <hi>Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne: therefore I ſay again, <hi>Ab Ioue principiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> REGES?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Ignorance.) Ab Ioue Principium</hi> REGES? What meanes this Repetition, and why call yee ſo on KINGS? <hi>(Customer.)</hi> That MAIESTY may be ſeene, and SOVERAIGNTY might ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, as in GOD ſo now in KINGES; for GOD forgets not his part, let <hi>Kings</hi> performe their owne. <hi>(Ignorance.)</hi> As howe? <hi>(Customer.)</hi> By their <hi>Bullion</hi> and <hi>Exchange,</hi> for if Coyning and Creating be meerely <hi>Synonimas,</hi> and mean but one thing, what creating is to GOD, the ſame is Coyning vnto <hi>Kings,</hi> leaſt <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects</hi> ſhould be <hi>Coyners. (Ignorance.)</hi> How ſhall <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes</hi> be ſo able to Create, that <hi>Subiectes</hi> bee no <hi>Coyners? (Cuſtomer.)</hi> By their <hi>Standarts,</hi> and their <hi>Bullion:</hi> For as a ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Standart,</hi> and ſtore of <hi>Bullion</hi> to Coyne at will, by meanes of their <hi>Exchange,</hi> makes all thinges good cheape, holds <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects</hi> to their <hi>Trades,</hi> and <hi>Trades</hi> in requeſt, whereby <hi>Kings</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Powerfull, and <hi>Subiectes</hi> Wealthy: So if <hi>Standarts</hi> bee vncertaine, and <hi>Kings</hi> want <hi>Bullion,</hi> as Coyne growes engroſt into priuate Mens hands, all things waxe deare, <hi>Kings</hi> beeome weake, and <hi>Subiectes</hi> poore, whilſt Coyne it ſelfe by <hi>Vſurie,</hi> (which <hi>Marchants</hi> call <hi>Exchange</hi>) eates out Induſtry in <hi>Trades,</hi> and <hi>Marchants</hi> by <hi>Monopolies</hi> ſeeke to ſtrangle <hi>Traffique. (Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.)</hi> What meane you by <hi>Standarts? [Cuſtomer.]</hi> I meane <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> in <hi>Weights, Numbers,</hi> and <hi>Meaſures.</hi> But in paſſing thus by <hi>Standarts,</hi> my minde becomes tranſported, and cannot but admire the <hi>Wiſedome</hi> both of GOD, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:183763:23"/>
of <hi>Kings.</hi> For when I read the BYBLE (ô read it <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi>) and finde therein commaunded, but <hi>Vnum Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> and <hi>Vna Menſura:</hi> I reſolue thus with my ſelfe; Surelie, if <hi>Truth</hi> be tyed to <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> as <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> is to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Kinges</hi> themſelues be <hi>Gods;</hi> then whereby can their <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> that's to ſay their <hi>Bounty,</hi> that's to ſay their <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> be more ſenſibly diſcerned then in their <hi>Standarts?</hi> As where withall alone, by the <hi>Power</hi> of their <hi>Preemption,</hi> and <hi>Quitrents</hi> of their <hi>Customes,</hi> being potentially poſſeſt of all the Lands &amp; Goods their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes doe containe (though they leaue notwithſtanding to each of their <hi>Subiects</hi> his <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> and full vſe of his owne) they may raiſe and pull down, the prices and worth, of euery Mans wealth, at their owne wils and pleaſure, by means of their <hi>Exchange. (Ignorance.)</hi> And why not ſo by <hi>Vſurie? (Customer.)</hi> Becauſe <hi>Exchange</hi> eyther louingly giues, or elſe by buying and ſelling, makes <hi>Meum</hi> to be <hi>Tuum,</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> to be <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um,</hi> by altering the propriety, for Reciproke Good: whereas <hi>Vſury</hi> neither giues out of <hi>Loue,</hi> nor lends out of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> nor ſo buyes or ſels as alters any propriety; but for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of <hi>Money,</hi> contracts for priuate-gaine. <hi>(Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.)</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mit al this at home might wel be performd between <hi>Soueraignes</hi> and <hi>Subiects</hi> within their owne Dominions. How ſhall <hi>Kinges</hi> with <hi>Kinges</hi> maintaine their <hi>Standarts,</hi> and keepe <hi>Subiects</hi> from Coyning? <hi>(Cuſtomer.)</hi> By their <hi>Treaties</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-courſe</hi> and <hi>Mutuall Contracts,</hi> to maintaine <hi>Equity,</hi> preuent aduantage, and keepe fraud from ſhelter. For if GOD haue commaunded in ſo ſtrict words and tearmes, but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> and <hi>Vna Menſura;</hi> as Himſelfe is but <hi>One,</hi> and KINGS but his LIEVTENANTS, to whom DEVS <hi>omnibus Idem:</hi> by what warrant or Commiſſion can they iuſtifie their Coynage, but by their <hi>Standarts?</hi> the ſpeciall charge of KINGS; to giue thereby as well true worth and content, as true length and breadth to all proportions; for <hi>Proportions</hi> ſhewe <hi>Perfection,</hi> whoſe vſes being <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Endes</hi> being <hi>Peace;</hi> bring all at laſt to <hi>Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> by <hi>Identity</hi> of <hi>Standart,</hi> and Mutuall <hi>Exchange.</hi> For look how <hi>Exchange,</hi> of the ſelfe-ſame <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> in <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer</hi> fixt, by the Name of <hi>Bullion,</hi> way'd out in Coyne, and warranted for vſe by the name of <hi>Money,</hi> ſhewes Men to be <hi>Kings</hi> by generall conſent, and <hi>Kings</hi> to be <hi>Gods,</hi> by infuſiue <hi>Grace:</hi> And how <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer</hi> becomes in this reſpect, the very Body and Blood of <hi>Kings;</hi> for without the <hi>Power</hi> of coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, euen <hi>Kinges</hi> are but <hi>Men,</hi> and without their materials, how can they Coyne <hi>Money?</hi> As the ſame <hi>Exchange</hi> I ſay, by altering the propriety (though not the Nature of eyther <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Bullion</hi>) of <hi>Meum</hi> into <hi>Tuum</hi> Reciprokely; becomes the very <hi>Cyment</hi> that glewes ſo together the communion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction
<pb facs="tcp:183763:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of <hi>Soueraignes</hi> with their <hi>Subiects,</hi> and <hi>Subiects</hi> each with other: Euen ſo the <hi>Identity</hi> of <hi>Standarts</hi> betweene <hi>Kinges</hi> and their <hi>Kingdomes</hi> by Reciproke Commerce, is the meanes of mutuall <hi>Happineſſe;</hi> as well in <hi>Matter, Order,</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> as <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> by protecting all their <hi>Liuings,</hi> all their <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> all their <hi>Liues,</hi> all their <hi>Honour,</hi> and the <hi>Peace</hi> of all their <hi>Land.</hi> The neglect whereof, or <hi>Ignorance,</hi> chuſe whether, hath made <hi>Popes</hi> to keepe down <hi>Emperors, Cardinals</hi> challenge <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Subiects</hi> to be Coyners.</p>
            <p>But howſoeuer heeretofore thinges haue beene neglected, vnknown, or miſtaken, which the Ages to come muſt reforme as they may; MAIESTY at all hands muſt firſt or laſt be ſeene, and SOVERAIGNTY muſt ſubſiſt, by one meanes or other, or neuer let <hi>Subiects</hi> euer looke to be happy. Wherein there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, be thou <hi>Popiſh</hi> or preciſe, ſo thou bee not obſtinate, and vnwilling to ariſe, or become ſo deſperate, that thou wilt cloſe thine eyes; lend me but thine eare awhile, and ſerious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, for the better vnderſtanding of the State of all in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, ſince I ſpeake to Diſcretion, and write to ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>¶ Whatſoeuer <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Is,</hi> or hath any <hi>Being,</hi> is manifeſt by <hi>Light. Being</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> are Thinges inſeparat, <hi>Light</hi> begotten by <hi>Being,</hi> &amp; <hi>Being</hi> appearing to <hi>Be</hi> ſuch as it <hi>Is</hi> by <hi>Light;</hi> for as <hi>Light</hi> hath ſubſiſtance onely from <hi>Being;</hi> ſo <hi>Being</hi> is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, ſo or ſo to be by <hi>Light. Being Loues</hi> to <hi>Liue,</hi> and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to <hi>Be; Light Loues</hi> to ſhew, and euer to be <hi>Seene;</hi> ſo both become manifeſt. <hi>Being</hi> ſtill in <hi>Light,</hi> and euer <hi>Light</hi> in <hi>Being.</hi> From which Reciproke <hi>Loue,</hi> proceedes the Spirit of <hi>Vnion,</hi> mouing ſtill from <hi>Being,</hi> and collecting ſtill by <hi>Light,</hi> and thus they <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Liue</hi> eternally together, ESSE, LVX, SPIRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVS, VNVM. &amp; this VNVM or ONE is ALL in ALL; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that bleſſed State of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> wherein by Creation, wee <hi>Loue, Liue, Moue, Enioy, See,</hi> and ſtill <hi>Behold</hi> all our happy <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> in <hi>Pondere Numerò &amp; Menſura,</hi> by the Names of GOD, CREATOR, IEHOVA, or DEITY.</p>
            <p>Among Things created, the firſt that was made and called <hi>Good,</hi> was <hi>Light;</hi> that <hi>Light</hi> might ſhew and diſtinguiſh <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> by degrees, as <hi>Good, Better,</hi> and <hi>Best;</hi> for in all Thinges Created, <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> is comparatiue in, and diffuſiue of it ſelfe; &amp; <hi>Motion</hi> is in <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> as <hi>Collection</hi> is in <hi>Light,</hi> by the Spirit of <hi>Vnion;</hi> for as <hi>Being</hi> cannot <hi>Be</hi> without <hi>Light,</hi> ſo <hi>Light</hi> without <hi>Goodnes,</hi> can haue no <hi>Being</hi> at <hi>All. Light</hi> the forme of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Being</hi> the forme of <hi>Light;</hi> ſuch is their <hi>Vnion</hi> or <hi>Vnity, Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie</hi> or <hi>Idem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodnes</hi> haue likewiſe one <hi>Eſſence</hi> or <hi>Being</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:24"/>
together by the Spirit of <hi>Vnion:</hi> ſo that GOD being <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> muſt likewiſe be <hi>Truth. Truth</hi> then being in <hi>Deity</hi> Creating, as <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in <hi>Humanity</hi> Created; can <hi>Truth</hi> in GOD be <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt</hi> or <hi>Fraud</hi> in KINGES? For KINGES are GODS. Can <hi>Vnity</hi> in GOD make <hi>Deity</hi> ſtill ſubſiſt, and <hi>Diuiſion</hi> in <hi>Kinges</hi> maintaine <hi>Regality?</hi> Or can <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> be any way deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in GOD or his <hi>Lieutenants?</hi> How then ſhall their MAIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIE be diſcerned without <hi>Light Intuitiuely?</hi> And how ſhall their SOVERAIGNTY be able to ſubſiſt <hi>Materially?</hi> If <hi>Kings</hi> be <hi>Per aeual,</hi> what <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Per amont,</hi> their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> muſt be <hi>Vnion,</hi> and their <hi>Identity</hi> muſt be <hi>Idem,</hi> for <hi>Deus omnibus Idem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of GOD is his owne diffuſiue <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and omnipotency in GOD eſſentiall with his <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> by the power of Creating: ſo the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of <hi>Kinges,</hi> is their <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> fixt in <hi>Bullion,</hi> for their <hi>Bullion</hi> ſhewes their <hi>Bounty,</hi> their <hi>Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> ſhewes their <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> by the abſolute <hi>Power</hi> of Coyning; for euen <hi>Bullion</hi> ſtill vncoynd, is naught of it ſelfe, but a weight of Maſſy Mowld and ſenſeleſſe <hi>Being:</hi> nor is <hi>Money</hi> to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued but onely for the vſe, which is that we tearme <hi>Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the brightneſſe of this <hi>Sunne,</hi> ſeeme to dazell all thy ſight, or thine eyes ſee not cleere to diſcerne this <hi>Myſterie,</hi> let <hi>Art</hi> releeue <hi>Nature</hi> by the helpe of <hi>Grace,</hi> and though com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons may ſeeme fearefull betweene Heauenly and Earthlie <hi>Beings,</hi> yet <hi>Examples</hi> may illuſtrate (I hope) without offence, where <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Probity</hi> contend for nothing elſe, but with all proſtrate reuerence, to ſee ſacred <hi>Maieſty</hi> betweene <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum,</hi> and to ſerue and ſet forth <hi>Soueraignty</hi> in her own ſubſiſtance: Therefore look but in my <hi>Myrroer,</hi> and ſee what I haue ſeene, and with my dim Spectacles read as I haue done.</p>
            <p>If all our <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Happineſſe</hi> can grow from none other then GOD and his LIEVTENANTS, what <hi>Goodnes</hi> is to <hi>God,</hi> let <hi>Bounty</hi> be to <hi>Kings,</hi> but all depend on <hi>God</hi> in reſpect of his <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> ſo let all depend on his <hi>Kings</hi> in regard of their <hi>Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> to ſhew their <hi>Greatneſſe.</hi> Now <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in <hi>God</hi> is euery way his owne as his naturall <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> by his infuſion; ſo <hi>Bounty</hi> ſtill in <hi>Kings</hi> by <hi>Grace, Conſent,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> ſtill fixt in themſelues, deſcends vnto <hi>Subiects.</hi> This leads vs ſtraight to <hi>Bullion,</hi> for though <hi>God</hi> by his <hi>Goodnes</hi> made <hi>All</hi> Things of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and ſo preſerues them ſtill, yet <hi>K ngs</hi> muſt haue <hi>Matter</hi> to fixe their <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in. This points at <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> and leades vs to <hi>Soueraignty,</hi> ſhewing <hi>Creatures</hi> to be <hi>Creatures,</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects</hi> to be <hi>Subiects,</hi> to auoyde <hi>Confuſion;</hi> for as GOD aboue Creates; ſo <hi>Kinges</hi> belowe Coyne: ſo then heere comes in <hi>Money,</hi> for as GOD ſhewes his MAIESTY in all things cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Infuſiuely,</hi> ſo <hi>Kings</hi> in their <hi>Money Intuitiuely:</hi> and as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignty</hi> in <hi>God</hi> ſubſiſts of it ſelfe in the <hi>Beauty</hi> of his worke,
<pb facs="tcp:183763:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by meanes of his <hi>Goodneſſe;</hi> ſo <hi>Soueraignty</hi> in <hi>Kinges</hi> ſubſiſts of it ſelfe, in the <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> of their <hi>Bounty,</hi> by meanes of their <hi>Money.</hi> But as <hi>God</hi> ſtill creates, and his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> ſtill releeuing; ſo <hi>Kinges</hi> muſt ſtill Coyne, and their <hi>Bounties</hi> ſtill bee giuing. Are not they then ſtrange <hi>Subiects,</hi> that repine at <hi>Kings Bounty,</hi> and <hi>Soueraignes</hi> ſtill beſtowing? Help <hi>Kings</hi> but to their <hi>Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and they cannot be more too-<hi>Bountifull,</hi> then <hi>God</hi> may bee to-<hi>Good.</hi> Happy then thoſe <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> where <hi>Kings</hi> are known by <hi>Bounty,</hi> and their <hi>Bounty</hi> findes their <hi>Bullion:</hi> for as <hi>God</hi> by his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> makes <hi>Catholiques</hi> happy <hi>Christians,</hi> by Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of himſelfe in bleſſed <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> Myſtically; So <hi>Kinges</hi> releeue their <hi>Subiects,</hi> and communicate their <hi>Eſſence</hi> in purg'd <hi>Golde</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi> weigh'd out in their Coyne. <hi>God</hi> woorking by the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> and <hi>Kinges</hi> by their <hi>Exchange. [Ignorance.]</hi> And why not ſo by <hi>Vſury,</hi> ſince their worke is ſtil by <hi>Money;</hi> wherein lyes the Witch-craft that makes the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence? <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> In the very Name and tearme, and by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king t'one for t'other: For <hi>Exchange</hi> euen in <hi>Money,</hi> making <hi>Meum</hi> to be <hi>Tuum,</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> to be <hi>Meum,</hi> ſtill alters the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, for one reſpect or other immediatly: but <hi>Vſury, Quaſi mons à mouendo,</hi> by the vſing of <hi>Money</hi> would faine ſeeme <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> though ſhe alter no propriety, putting <hi>Money</hi> to her ſhiftes, and ſending her a Whooring, receiues her home with ſhame. <hi>[Ignorance.] Ignotum per Ignotius:</hi> I cannot ſpell your Reaſons. <hi>[Customer.]</hi> Why hearke a little further, and ſtop not thine eares, nor wrangle with thy ſelfe by taking <hi>This</hi> for <hi>That,</hi> leaſt <hi>Quos perire Deus vult, Hos ipſe Deus occaecat.</hi> The KING Coynes a <hi>Penny,</hi> which none may doe but <hi>Hee,</hi> for feare of <hi>High-Treaſon,</hi> whoſe weight by the <hi>Standart,</hi> eyther is, or elſe ſhould be, thirty two Graines of Wheate, in the midſt of the eare.<note place="margin">A Penny, according to the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dart at the Conqueſt, the weight whereof now makes three pence.</note> This weight the <hi>King</hi> warrants by his Crowne, Seale of his Armes, <hi>Letters</hi> of his <hi>Name,</hi> ſtamp of his <hi>Face,</hi> and by the worth of himſelfe values it to others; and being ſo made cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haec eſt</hi> MONETA MEA, <hi>Hoc eſt</hi> CORPVS MEVM.</note> he cals it by the Name, and ſayes it is his <hi>[Money]</hi> not as <hi>Mons à mouendo quia minime mouet;</hi> but <hi>Moneta, quaſi monens ne quid fraudis in Materia Signo vel Pondere fiat)</hi> and by his <hi>Exchange,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Permutationibus rerum preſto eſt Communis Menſura, ex hominum Inſtitutis non vt Naturae nata. Haec autem Moneta eſt, Rebus Menſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; aeſtimationem inferens. Eſtque Medius quodamodo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> id eſt cuncta metitur, ac Rerum inaequalium precia, ea menſura, ad aequlitatem reuocantur. Et quia ex Lege eſt, non Natura, proinde Numi prorepſit appellatio, à Nomo, id eſt Lege. Eſtque tanquam Rerum omnium Fide-Iuſſor. Ante cuius inuentionem Rerum ipſarum fiebat permuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, &amp; Res, indigentia metiebantur. Coelij Rhodigini, fol. <hi>896.</hi> lib. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> maintaines it for a <hi>Penny</hi> all his Kingdome through. What warrant now hath <hi>Vſury</hi> without altering the propriety, by conſent of contract and honeſt marriage, to proſtitute this <hi>Penny</hi> to falſe clipping, or ſtrange Coyning. For when <hi>Kinges</hi> thus Coyne <hi>Money,</hi> as they value it vnto others by the worth of themſelues, they receiue it ſo againe by the reaſon and rule of their owne <hi>Exchange.</hi> But <hi>Bankers</hi> vſe <hi>Money</hi> if it come to their hands, as <hi>Bauds</hi> abuſe <hi>Virgins,</hi> till they get a great belly by a monſtrous kinde of Inceſt, and vnlawfull Coynage, and to couer ſhameleſſe <hi>Vſury,</hi> call their Intereſt their <hi>Exchange;</hi> like
<pb facs="tcp:183763:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thoſe that call their <hi>Baſtards,</hi> their naturall Children. If a Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell be not meaſure, or a yard be more or leſſe then the ſize of the <hi>Standard,</hi> the <hi>Clearke</hi> of the Market ſoone takes you by the eares, and then you knowe what followes; take greater heede of <hi>Money,</hi> and runne away from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> as you would from <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> the <hi>Patrons</hi> now of <hi>Popery,</hi> for feare of Soules and Bodies. <hi>[Igno.]</hi> Though <hi>Vſury</hi> proue <hi>Popery,</hi> yet how came it firſt from <hi>Rome? [Customer.]</hi> With the <hi>Maſſe</hi> and <hi>Idolatry:</hi> for, as the <hi>Maſſe</hi> of Creatures makes <hi>Idols;</hi> ſo <hi>Vſury</hi> makes of <hi>Money,</hi> and the <hi>Maſſe</hi> with <hi>Vſury</hi> goe paralell together, as the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist</hi> with <hi>Exchange;</hi> ſo the <hi>Eucharist</hi> to the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> to <hi>Vſury,</hi> make a flat <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> and <hi>Diametricall</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition the one againſt the other. <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> Is <hi>Vſury</hi> then a greater Sinne, then to clip, waſh, and counterfeit, or to coyne falſe <hi>Money? [Cuſtomer.]</hi> By farre, like the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> if witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and willingly it be obſtinately vſed; yea, by ſo many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, as I know not how farre; for that eclipſeth MAIESTY, and ſo blindfoldes but her Face, that ſhe cannot well be ſeene. This with her owne Finger ſo puts out her eyes, as makes her vnable both to ſee and to be ſeene. That offends onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Perſons</hi> of <hi>Kings.</hi> This againſt their <hi>Power, Wils, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Soueraignty,</hi> and <hi>Subſistance</hi> of their <hi>Eſſence</hi> &amp; <hi>States.</hi> That againſt a KINGS PREHEMINENCE, for his <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> whoſe roome may bee ſupplyd though a <hi>Ieſuit</hi> had deſtroyd him. This againſt PREROGATIVE, blowes vp <hi>Kinges</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> both for <hi>Matter, Perſons, Place, Order,</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> which cannot be ſupplyde; the reſt you may aduiſe on, for I dare goe no further.</p>
            <p>Now had not I then reaſon (let common ſence be Iudge) in the <hi>Epilogue</hi> or <hi>Concluſion</hi> of my ſecond APOLOGY, to reply confidently thus? That EXCHANGE in <hi>Marchandize,</hi> and MARCHANDIZING <hi>Exchange,</hi> is that Labyrinth of <hi>Errors</hi> and priuate practiſe, whereby though KINGS weare Crowns, and ſeeme powerfully to raigne; yet particulars <hi>Bankers,</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate <hi>Societies</hi> of <hi>Marchants</hi> and couetous <hi>Perſons,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ends</hi> are Priuate-gaine; are able to ſuſpend their Counſels, and Comptroll their Pollicies: offering <hi>Bounty</hi> to their SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNES, KINGS, and QVEENES; the very Fountaines of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> but to ſhelter their ſhame, and lending for Inrereſt to EMPERORS and KINGES, that onely can Coyne, and ſhould haue to ſpend largely, and giue vnto others; making <hi>Soueraignes</hi> thus but <hi>Subiects,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vaſſals</hi> to be <hi>Kings.</hi> That ſuch was the ſtrength of that ſtaine and ſtay of <hi>Piety,</hi> that contempt of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that ſeede of <hi>Diſſention,</hi> that World of warre, that Art of Witch-craft, VSVRY. And that ſuch is and will bee the <hi>Power</hi> thereof ſtill, at all occaſions, till <hi>Kinges</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:26"/>
take their owne charge in hand, and next to RELIGION that ſanctifies all, releeue &amp; maintain the Nurce of IVSTICE that rectifies all; to wit, our FREE-BORNE-TRAFFIQVE, I meant in ENGLAND, and ENGLISH-TRAFFIQVE.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>In Magnis voluiſſe ſat est, ſint caetera</hi> DIVVM.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> Then farewell priuate profit, and Intereſt for <hi>Mony,</hi> with <hi>Couetiſe</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> &amp; equiuocating <hi>Popery;</hi> yea, fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well <hi>Fraud</hi> and all. I will become a <hi>Catholike,</hi> for they may bee <hi>Christians</hi> and honeſt Men to, &amp; learne to know the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> and liue by <hi>Exchange. [Diſcretion.]</hi> And ſo will I doe too; for glorious out of queſtion muſt thoſe kingdoms be, whoſe <hi>Kings</hi> thus by Coynage hold Amity together, their <hi>Nobles</hi> moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and their <hi>Subiects</hi> moſt happy. But ſuppoſe all this effected in their <hi>Standarts</hi> by <hi>Iuſtice;</hi> how ſhould <hi>Catholiques</hi> be agreed in points of <hi>Religion?</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Maſſe</hi> is ſo predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, both at <hi>Rome</hi> and in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> is ſo admir'd by <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and others. <hi>[Custoemr.] Religion</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> are ſo twiſted ſtill togither by the Twine of one <hi>Truth,</hi> their Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Beame</hi> and <hi>Standart,</hi> that take away but <hi>Vſury</hi> by reſtoring our <hi>Exchange,</hi> and the <hi>Maſſe</hi> cannot ſubſiſt; and remoouing the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> muſt needes be packing, and <hi>Purgatory</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: Now <hi>Religion</hi> muſt haue <hi>Byſhops,</hi> though <hi>Popes</hi> may bee gone, and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> will haue <hi>Kinges</hi> though <hi>Cardinals</hi> be none: ſo that, in <hi>Ordine</hi> and <hi>Spiritualia,</hi> or conſequence, chuſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Catholikes</hi> may be <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and honeſt Men too, though <hi>Ieſuites</hi> prooue neyther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> But how come the <hi>Maſſe</hi> and <hi>Vſury</hi> by <hi>Popery</hi> ſo vnited? <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> What the <hi>Maſſe</hi> is to <hi>Religion,</hi> the ſame is <hi>Vſury</hi> to <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and they both goe together; whereby it comes to paſſe, that <hi>Catholiques</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are bewitched ſo by <hi>Ieſuites. [Ignorance.]</hi> Wherein lyes the Witch-craft? <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> In the Names of the one, and Idolatry of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for as <hi>Ieſuites</hi> would ſeeme <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſo <hi>Vſury</hi> would vſe <hi>Money,</hi> not as <hi>Ieſus</hi> a Sauiour, for indeed they are nothing leſſe, nor as <hi>Money</hi> is <hi>Moneta, quaſi monens ne quid fraudis in Materia Signo vel Pondere fiat:</hi> but as <hi>Mons à mouendo, quod minime mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet. [Ignorance.]</hi> But how doth the Idolatry of the <hi>Maſſe</hi> bring <hi>Vſury</hi> to be <hi>Popery? [Cuſtomer.]</hi> By the Pictures in Coyne, for <hi>Vt mundo Natura Curſum, Soli lumen, ſic gratiam Auro;</hi> Men looking on the <hi>Beauty</hi> of <hi>Bullion,</hi> and powerfulneſſe of <hi>Money,</hi> by too too much admiring the pourtraitures of KINGES ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in their Coyne, fall in loue with their <hi>Pictures,</hi> as the <hi>Heathen</hi> with their Idols. <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> It ſeemes then by this meanes, that the <hi>Maſſe</hi> may proue a higher ſinne then <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and <hi>Vſury</hi> more then <hi>Treaſon,</hi> what ſinne may that be? <hi>[Cuſt.]</hi> Nay there forſooth I leaue you, for I dare not once think ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:183763:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
much leſſe determine. <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> What helps to excuſe it for the ſinnes that are paſt? <hi>[Customer.]</hi> Onely meere ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, frailty, and weakneſſe. <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> And what may expiat the guilt thereof in eyther? <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> Harty repentance for all that is paſt, and a ſerious entention to forbeare it hereafter. <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> Then farewell ſinfull <hi>Maſſe</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſince wilfulneſſe obdurates ſo fearefully in either. O dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> that bewitch ſtill the World by ſuch kinde of <hi>Popery!</hi> But whats all this to <hi>Customers? [Customer.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">The CVSTOMER, by his Method, ſeeing MAIESTY no where fixed, but in GOD and Chriſtian KINGS <hi>Perſonally,</hi> and Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a ſworne Seruant and Cuſtomer to a Chriſtian KING, whoſe MA: ſeemes ecclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and defectiue in his <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> ſhowes heer the Reaſon why, and manner how, He, <hi>Ex Officio,</hi> became forc'ſt (firſt of all others) to ſearch out the Grounds of ſo Great <hi>Iniuſtice, Radicitùs</hi> as it were, and <hi>Originally.</hi> Namely, Finding that <hi>Impietie</hi> by direct oppoſition did vndermine <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> in all Chriſtian <hi>Religion</hi> ſtil by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and <hi>Iniquitie</hi> by <hi>Vſury,</hi> to attempt the like on <hi>Equity</hi> in all Kingly <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> by miſvſing their Moneyes Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally: and obſeruing withall, howe <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> by holding hands together, did illuſtrate each other, He came at laſt to diſcerne howe POPERY by the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> diſguiſing Chriſtianity, &amp; bewitching Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks, found the way to hoodwink <hi>Kings</hi> and enthral <hi>Kingdoms</hi> eccleſiaſtically: and with VSVRY as with <hi>Gunpowder</hi> to blow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp at laſt, with their <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> &amp; <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi> Whereupon, the <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> leauing <hi>Impiety</hi> with the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> for Diuines to lay open, (following ſtill his Method) in the <hi>Miſtery of Iniquity,</hi> or Secular kind of <hi>Popery,</hi> He betooke Himſelfe directly to the POPES owne <hi>Perſon:</hi> whoſe main Subſiſtence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing SIN, and <hi>Rome</hi> by Iubilees, &amp;c. the <hi>Mart</hi> and <hi>Staple</hi> thereof, to poiſon the world, by Bankers and Bawdes, drawing home his <hi>Annates, Peter-pence,</hi> and <hi>Reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes,</hi> depends moſt on VSVRY. For, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no naturall Mines of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, nor Mints to make Mony, nor Wares worth the battering: HE ſettles there, and makes Port-ſale from thence of all kinde of SIN, articificially for <hi>Bullion,</hi> and rebelliouſly vſurping the EMP. powerfull <hi>Mints,</hi> makes HIS Kingly <hi>Stamps</hi> ſtrike <hi>His</hi> Counterfet <hi>Coyn,</hi> as by his <hi>Face</hi> thereon, and <hi>Armes</hi> is intuitiuely euident and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickly cleare. And, inſtead of lawfull <hi>Tributes</hi> (as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſometimes had) ſettes Taxes, Impoſts, and Impoſitions, by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion to keepe KINGS and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſtill diſtracting their STANDARDS, &amp; debauching their EXCHANGE.</note> The ſame with GOD and KINGES, for <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> are <hi>Catholiques,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Men too, and faine would bee happy; but as <hi>Popery</hi> by <hi>Idolatry</hi> preſuming vppon <hi>Deity,</hi> eclipſeth MAIESTY in KINGES; ſo <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> by <hi>Vſury,</hi> are put by their <hi>Cuſtomes. [Ignorace.]</hi> Why, from whence came their <hi>Cuſtomes? [Custo.]</hi> From their <hi>Staples. [Ignorance.]</hi> Where then are their <hi>Staples? [Cuctomer.]</hi> They were ſometimes at home, though now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilde beyond Seas, and would faine returne, if <hi>Vſury</hi> were put downe; for our <hi>Temples</hi> and our <hi>Staples</hi> were wont to ſtand together. <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> How <hi>Temples</hi> with <hi>Staples? [Customer.] Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> haue euer helde together, and as the one had her Altars for <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> ſtill kept in her <hi>Temples;</hi> ſo the other had her <hi>Mints</hi> vnited to her <hi>Staples,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Mintes</hi> Coyn'd the <hi>Money</hi> wherewith <hi>Traffique</hi> at our <hi>Ports</hi> did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge her homage, before ſhee croſt the Seas, which is that we call <hi>Cuſtomes. [Ignorance.]</hi> But what haue KINGS to doe with <hi>Staples,</hi> in the queſtion of <hi>Money? [Cuſtomer.]</hi> In regard of their <hi>Bullion,</hi> ſince none but they may Coyne, and their <hi>Bullion</hi> is no where to bee found but at their <hi>Staples,</hi> by vertue of their <hi>Load-ſtones</hi> that are there laid vp together: ſo that, No <hi>Staples,</hi> no <hi>Load ſtones:</hi> No <hi>Loadſtones,</hi> no <hi>Bullion:</hi> No <hi>Bullion,</hi> no <hi>Mints:</hi> No <hi>Mints,</hi> no <hi>Money:</hi> No <hi>Money,</hi> no <hi>Customes:</hi> No <hi>Customes,</hi> no <hi>Honour:</hi> No <hi>Honour,</hi> no <hi>Homage:</hi> No <hi>Homage,</hi> no <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> and no <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> no <hi>Religion:</hi> and all for lacke of <hi>Staples. [Ignorance.]</hi> Why, ſay KINGES ſhould Coyne no <hi>Money</hi> for want of their <hi>Bullion,</hi> and ſay they haue no <hi>Staples,</hi> yet if <hi>Subiects</hi> may but Coyn, ſo it be at their <hi>Mints,</hi> what harme can come of it? <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> If <hi>Subiects</hi> may bee Coyners, that's as <hi>Vſury, aliâs Popery</hi> would haue it, then what becomes of <hi>Exchange,</hi> and then where is <hi>Bounty?</hi> Where's <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> that makes KINGS weare the Crowne? Nay, when the Spirits of their <hi>Pulſes</hi> haue no blood of their owne, where ſubſiſtes their <hi>Eſſence,</hi> if their <hi>Subſtance</hi> bee gone? <hi>[Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.]</hi> Indeede this ſeemes ſomething. <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> If any thing be ſomething, graunt this, or graunt nothing; therfore let <hi>Common Senſe</hi> be Iudge, if I had not ſometimes Reaſon, in ſeeking after <hi>Staples,</hi> thereby to finde <hi>Bullion,</hi> when comparing
<pb facs="tcp:183763:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
things by contraries to illuſtrate each other; I crid out againſt <hi>Couetiſe</hi> and Priuate-gaine thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Great, Greater,</hi> and <hi>Greateſt</hi> of all, muſt their Accompts be, both to GOD and KINGES, that prepoſtorouſly peruerting their proper <hi>Materials,</hi> turne their beſt helpes for <hi>Bullion</hi> to their priuate aduantage, to the intollerable diſturbance both of <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and almoſt vnrecouerable wrong to the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Crowne. [Ignorance.]</hi> This is much to their <hi>Mints</hi> indeed, but what are <hi>Staples</hi> to <hi>Iustice? [Cuſtomer.]</hi> What are <hi>Temples</hi> to <hi>Religion? [Ignorance.] Temples</hi> ſure are <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries</hi> for the maintenance of <hi>Religion:</hi> for, I read it thus writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. O worſhip the Lord in the <hi>Glory</hi> of his <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> of his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> which I take to be <hi>Temples</hi> and <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> in regard of <hi>Deuotion. [Customer.]</hi> Euen ſo ſay of <hi>Staples.</hi> O Honour the <hi>King</hi> in the <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> of his <hi>Bounty,</hi> or <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of his Courtes <hi>Subalterne</hi> and <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> which in this caſe of ours, I call the COMMON-PLEAS, together with his <hi>Staples,</hi> in regard of <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> by the one, and <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> by the other. For as the Graue Court of STAR-CHAM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BER, by ſet daies of hearing and preſence of the <hi>King,</hi> ſhewes MAIESTY and SOVERAGNTY betweene <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum, Vitia perimendo ſeruatis hominibus,</hi> beſides his owne <hi>Counſell,</hi> and PRIVY-COVNSELL-TABLE:</p>
            <p>And as the KING on his BENCH, in the midſt of his <hi>Iudges,</hi> by publique proceedings betweene <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>Subiects,</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Iustice</hi> to <hi>All,</hi> breakes Bread to the meaneſt according to Birth-right; and out of loue and affection (as well may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme <hi>Him</hi>) ſtandes gratious to ſome more then all the reſt: protects notwithſtanding from priuate oppreſſion, or wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues, the <hi>Liuings, Liberties, Honour,</hi> and <hi>Weddinges</hi> of <hi>Pupils</hi> and <hi>Orphanes</hi> in a <hi>Nurcery</hi> beſides, for his <hi>Wardes</hi> and <hi>Liueries,</hi> whereby KINGES are nouriſhing Fathers, and QVEENES nouriſhing Mothers, as well as <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Iudges:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the KING in his Court of Publick-COMMON-PLEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DINGS, deſciding diſputes betweene <hi>Subiect</hi> and <hi>Subiect,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> both in <hi>Tythes</hi> and in <hi>Tributes;</hi> to ſhew MARIESTY to <hi>Strangers,</hi> as it were <hi>Face</hi> to <hi>Face,</hi> in the <hi>Honour</hi> of his <hi>Mints</hi> and glorious <hi>Exchange;</hi> maintaines not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding at his <hi>Staples</hi> a franke and free Commerce for ready <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi> by the name of <hi>Bullion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that, as to ſee GOD in regard of <hi>Religion</hi> in the <hi>Glory</hi> of his <hi>Sanctuaries,</hi> is to ſeeke him in his <hi>Temples,</hi> and in the <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> to heare him in his <hi>Churches</hi> Cathedrally: ſo to ſee the <hi>King</hi> in regard of his <hi>Iustice,</hi> in his <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> is to ſee him in his Courtes <hi>Diſtributiuely,</hi> and in the <hi>Bounty</hi> of his <hi>Bullion,</hi> by meanes of his <hi>Exchange,</hi> to ſeeke him
<pb facs="tcp:183763:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in his <hi>Staples Commutatiuely. [Ignorance.]</hi> This indeed is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and cannot be to much, in regard of <hi>Kingly Bounty,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept GOD may be to good; Which <hi>Piety</hi> dares not thinke, nor profaneneſſe ſpeake: But what's this to our <hi>Religion?</hi> Since our <hi>Temples</hi> ſtand vpright, and our <hi>Churches</hi> moue deuotion; how come <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> thus able to hunt after <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſee ſo farre as ROME? <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> Their ſtanding makes them ſee, and their ſeeing moues their Conſciences not to hold their peace. <hi>[Ignoranee.]</hi> What makes them diue ſo deepe, and delue into the groundes of <hi>Diuinity</hi> and <hi>Humanity,</hi> to finde out the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of <hi>Impiety</hi> and <hi>Iniquity,</hi> in the Bowels of <hi>Popery? [Cuſt.]</hi> They ſeeke for <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies,</hi> and ſeruing GOD, and KINGS would gladly be happy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>As the <hi>Motyue</hi> and <hi>Occaſion</hi> of Writing the MISTERY of INIQVITY grew firſt from the KINGS owne commaundement by Sir <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Hay</hi> vpon his, reading of the Preface to my former ACROAMATA, ſo the <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the ſame, fals out by this Accompt of a Cuſtomer of his owne, to concerne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong OTHERS, His <hi>Maieſties Owne Selfe.</hi> For when the Iewes of IERVSALEM, their Country being ſubdued, and they paying Tribute vnto CAESAR, came to liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romans,</hi> as <hi>Freedenizons</hi> of ROME; <hi>Gentiliſme</hi> and <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> ioyning hands each with other, <hi>Impietie</hi> and <hi>Iniquity</hi> committing Inceſt together, begat thoſe two Monſters of the World, the Idolatrous MASSE, and profane VSVRY. Which by <hi>Bankers</hi> &amp; <hi>Bawds</hi> afterward corrupting true <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> both together, with the daily loue of Money (to keepe downe Chriſtianitie) ſo out-faced the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and ſcorned <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> that as <hi>Italy</hi> grew full of Baſtard In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, ROME it ſelfe became the very Box of PANDORA, and <hi>Staple</hi> of Sinne for <hi>Bullion</hi> to the Catholicke Diſorder and Diſcord of all Churches of Chriſtendom, and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Common-wealthes. The miſcheefes whereof, by the pride of POPES and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, though the <hi>Emperors</hi> and <hi>Publicans,</hi> did at firſt deuide betweene them (for both ſtood and fell together, with the ruine of the Empire) the Inconueniences at laſt haue extended ſo farre, as to threaten KINGS annointed within their owne <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and haue coſt ſome <hi>Kinges</hi> their liues, by <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and others. Haue not <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers</hi> then reaſon (in the <hi>Out-Portes</hi> at leaſt) to looke out and cry alowd, <hi>Ab Ioue Principium Reges?</hi> and to tell ſuch to their faces,
<q>
                        <l>Quiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſitit <hi>(REGIS)</hi> ſatiari ſanguine <hi>NOSTRI<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Cum <hi>PAPA</hi> praeceps, Author &amp; actor eat</l>
                        <l>Nam, Cui Religio Stuprum, ira, ſuperbia, caedes,</l>
                        <l>Error, Mollities, Fulmina, turpe Lucrum,</l>
                        <l>Corpora qui vendit <hi>CHRISTI,</hi> Solumque Polu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>,</l>
                        <l>Caeleſtes Genios, Sydera, Iura, <hi>DEOS:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Fama refert, Scriptura docet, Peccata loquuntur</l>
                        <l>Huic, Huic, vita breuis, paena perennis erit.</l>
                        <l>Dictum puta<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> SCIOPPI.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </note> But what haue CVSTOMES and the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage</hi> to diſlike of in <hi>Popery? [Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomer.]</hi> If MAIESTY muſt bee ſeene, and SOVERAIGNTY ſubſiſt, as in GOD, ſo in KINGES; what <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> are to <hi>God,</hi> the ſame are <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies</hi> to <hi>Kings,</hi> his immediat <hi>Lieutenants,</hi> and beyond the boundes that his <hi>Wiſedome</hi> hath laide out for the practiſe of his <hi>Truth;</hi> our <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion</hi> may hunt, but ſhall finde nought but <hi>Error,</hi> what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes is but <hi>Popery</hi> by Proiects to diſtract both <hi>Churche,</hi> and diſturbe <hi>Common-Wealth:</hi> for as <hi>Omne minimum,</hi> is <hi>Inimica Naturae,</hi> ſo <hi>Omne Nimium vertitur in vitium;</hi> Enough ſtill makes a Feaſt, but abuſes marre all, by means of POPES and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> as who reades but our MYSTERY of INIQVITY, may plainely diſcerne, and eaſily ſee, heere now to be declared. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> What hath <hi>Italy</hi> to doe with the MYSTERY of INIQVITY, and what doubt you ſo from thence? <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> Leaſt the ſowreneſſe of their Grapes (I meane her <hi>Imposts</hi> and <hi>Vſury</hi>) ſhould ſet mens teeth an edge, by her neereneſſe vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> and make them drunke at laſt wthout the help of <hi>Meſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to;</hi> I mean the <hi>Grace</hi> of GOD. <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> But let the <hi>Maſse</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> alone, howe hath <hi>Rome</hi> infected the <hi>Customes</hi> due to <hi>Kings,</hi> and offended <hi>Cuſtomers? [Customer.]</hi> By her practiſe and Example. For euen <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelfe, that from the bare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of ſeauen barren Hils, became Miſtreſſe and Empreſſe at the laſt of all the World; in her greateſt height of <hi>Happines,</hi> ſtood moſt of all aſſured, and conſtantly ſetled, by her eaſie rates of <hi>Customes,</hi> and mildneſſe of <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Publicans.</hi> Till <hi>Extreamity</hi> began to teach all Men to <hi>Shift,</hi> whereby <hi>Shiftes</hi> incurd <hi>Suspition,</hi> and <hi>Suspition</hi> argu'd <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Ignorance</hi> brought forth <hi>Errors, Errors</hi> turn'd to <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefes,</hi> and <hi>Miſcheefes</hi> to <hi>Inconueniences,</hi> the high way to <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, Diſorder,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion.</hi> Whereby as <hi>Traffique</hi> grewe confounded both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> offences by
<pb facs="tcp:183763:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
conſequence increaſt more and more, which like to pudled Waters and corrupted Ayre, bred and ingendred nothing, but creeping <hi>Informens,</hi> noyſome <hi>Caterpillers,</hi> and rauenous <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to vexe and torment the <hi>Emperors</hi> themſelues, and <hi>Empire</hi> withall: ſo that,
<q>
                  <l>When <hi>Vtile</hi> had gotten the ſtart of <hi>Honeſtum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Couetiſe</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> fell at oddes each with other,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Profit</hi> turning <hi>Priuate,</hi> made <hi>Honour</hi> ſeeme nothing,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Honeſtum</hi> firſt, then <hi>Vtile,</hi> ſhould haue gone both together.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>O ROME, therefore ROME! And muſt it be the lot of a <hi>Customer</hi> at laſt,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſticall <hi>Popery</hi> by the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently laid open by <hi>Diuines:</hi> but Secular <hi>Popery</hi> by <hi>Vſury,</hi> neuer directly declared till now.</note> to lay open thy ſhame, and diſcouer thine <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> before <hi>Emperors</hi> and <hi>Kings?</hi> Thy <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Preſumption</hi> in Coyning of their Monies? thy ſale of Sinne for <hi>Bullion?</hi> thy <hi>Iewiſh Extortion</hi> and <hi>Baudry</hi> with <hi>Bankers,</hi> to drawe home thy Reuennewes? thy <hi>Rebellion?</hi> thy <hi>Popery?</hi> In a word, thy <hi>Vſury</hi> the bane of their <hi>Exchange?</hi> No maruell at all, ſeeing thy <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetiſe</hi> and <hi>Ambition</hi> in the greatneſſe of thy glory, made ſo ſlight accompt of <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> and of their beſt Endeuours. Witneſſe the very <hi>Graueſt-Wiſest Senators</hi> that euer were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, bred, or brought vp, in thee, for thee, or by thee.</p>
            <p>For what Man euen at this day, that heares or reades there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, admires not the <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Happineſſe</hi> of the Citty it ſelfe of <hi>Rome?</hi> And in <hi>Rome</hi> withall, the powerfull Authority of <hi>Eloquence</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> of that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erè Pater Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae,</hi> MARCVS TVLLIVS CICERO?</p>
            <p>ROMA <hi>autem, olim Imperij Domicilium, virtutis cumulo vel ipſis</hi> ATHENIS <hi>longè ſuperior, &amp; elocutionis laude par, aut paulo inferior; etiam-nunc hodie, quamvis papiſtico luxu, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioſo Christianiſmo, Bonorum omnium odio ſubiecta ſit: caeteris tamen omibus,</hi> CICERONIS <hi>Eloquentia &amp; ingenio ſic poſteritati co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendata est; vt quandiu literarum latinarum vel fructu adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, vel illustrati vlli extiterint; vrbis</hi> ROMae <hi>memoria, duratura eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the whole <hi>Roman Common-wealth,</hi> euen in their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> conſiſted but of three Degrees or Orders. SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NATORES, EQVITES, <hi>&amp;</hi> PLEBIj; <hi>Senators, Knights,</hi> and <hi>Plebians,</hi> or <hi>Commons.</hi> And in that of <hi>Knighthood,</hi> the <hi>Publicans</hi> were cheefe by <hi>Tullies</hi> owne wordes, thus pleading for <hi>Planci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Florem Ciuitatis, Ornamentum Imperij &amp; Firmamentum Reipub: Publicanorum Ordine contineri.</hi> And, <hi>Ad Quintu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem, Si Publicanis aduerſemur, Ordinem de Nobis optime me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum, &amp; per Nos cum Repub: coniunctum, à nobis &amp; à Repub: diſiungimus:</hi> Glorying at it were in the milde diſpoſition of the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> in his time, aboue thoſe of other Countries, ſaying: <hi>Non eſſe leniores in tribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is exigendis Graecos, quàm nostros Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanos. Hinc enim est quod Caunij nuper ex Inſulis quae erant
<pb facs="tcp:183763:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
à Sylla Rhodijs attributae ad Senatum confugerunt, vt Nobis poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us vectigalia penderent quàm Rhodijs. fimam tantum partem earum rerum quae exportabantur, Portorij nomine</hi> (of Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize outward, by the Name of <hi>Cuſtomes) &amp; vectigalis</hi> (Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize Inward, called <hi>Jncomes</hi> and Reuennues) wherein four things at this day are worthy to be noted. 1. The ordring <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of their <hi>Traffique,</hi> into <hi>Outward</hi> and <hi>Inward.</hi> 2. The Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of <hi>Tributes</hi> into <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> and <hi>Subſidies</hi> by the name of <hi>Reuennewes.</hi> 3. Their low and eaſie <hi>Rates,</hi> in regard of other <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Countries.</hi> 4. And <hi>Protection</hi> and <hi>Direction</hi> of all their <hi>Commerce,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> attended on ſeriouſly, by the whole <hi>Senate,</hi> leaſt one Mans will might be euery Mans woe. But to read his loue to <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> and withall, his care of the State, by beating downe ſo earneſtly the ſtrong conceipts and forwardneſſe of the wiſeſt of thoſe times, that in fauour of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> ſought to raiſe the <hi>Reuennewes,</hi> by <hi>Vtile</hi> without <hi>Honestum,</hi> to make a Man in loue with the Memory &amp; Wiſdome of our late Lord <hi>Treaſurer</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> within theſe fifty years: read in the third Book of his <hi>Offices,</hi> his paſſionate ſpeeches thus. <hi>Quouſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tandem audebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dicere quicquam vtile quod non prius Honeſtum? Nullam autem pestem maiorem vitae &amp; Societati hominum poſſe contingere dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim, quàm eorum opinio qui ista diſtraxerint. Potest ne vlli Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio, quod gloria &amp; Sociorum beneuolentia fultum eſſe debet, Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le eſſe odium &amp; infamia? Ego autem cum Marco Catone meo ſepe diſſenſi. Nimis enim praefractè &amp; obſtinate, Aerarium, vectigalia<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> viſus est defendere, &amp; Omnia Publicanis negare, cum quibus ſic agere vt cum Colonis deberemus, eò<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> magis, quod eius Ordinis coniunctio ad ſalutem Reipub: apprimè pertinet. Male item Curio cauſam tranſpadanam aequam dicendo, ſemper addebat.</hi> VINCAT VTILITAS. Read him alſo, <hi>Ad Memmium. Epiſt.</hi> 10. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentium Varronem, M: Bruto commendantem. Quòd maturè ſe contulerit in Societatem Publicanorum; cuius ordinis mihi antea commendatiſſimi cauſa, fecit amicitiam nostram multo firmiorem, &amp; Epiſt.</hi> 7. <hi>ad Atticum. Caeſari amantiſſimos Publicanos aijt, Et homines ampliſſimos nominatim appellat.</hi> And aboue all, to ſhew his Iudgement in <hi>Cuſtome</hi> Cauſes, and acquaintance with <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers;</hi> read him in <hi>Verrem. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Iuriſdictione Sicilienſi,</hi> at theſe wordes. <hi>Nam quod in Publicanorum Cauſis plurimum aetatis meae verſor, vehementer<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illum Ordinem obſeruo, ſatis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modè mihi videor eorum conſuetudinem vſu, tractando<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cognoviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe;</hi> But who reades the wordes following, and obſerues his proceedings with LVCIVS VIBIVS, head <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> of SY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RACVSA, by the Bookes of his <hi>Accompts,</hi> to ſift and ſpy out <hi>Verruvius,</hi> for <hi>Verres</hi> would ſoone bee perſwaded, that euen TVLLY himſelfe had ſometimes beene a <hi>Cuſtomer;</hi> ſo farre of was he from thinking it a diſparagement in credit, to giue
<pb facs="tcp:183763:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his minde vnto <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> or diſgrace to his perſon, to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>Cuſtomers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But howſoeuer. It is moſt apparant to ſuch as liſt obſerue it, that if TVLLY himſelfe for all his wit and eloquence had not beene ſtudious to know the vſe of <hi>Customes,</hi> and been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant with <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> hee had neuer beene able to haue left vnto the World thoſe two Golden workes of his (the pledges of his Loyalty, and Creame of his Iudgment) called TVLLIES OFFICES, and TVLLY-DE-REPVBLICA. The firſt, an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyridion</hi> of <hi>Honeſtum</hi> ioyn'd with <hi>Vtile,</hi> teaching all Men euen at this day, the true Rules of <hi>Ciuility</hi> and <hi>Christian Polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> The other, likewiſe able to make any Man a Wiſe-man, in leſſe then one daies reading, (as honeſt <hi>Roger Askam,</hi> and learned <hi>Iohn Sturmius,</hi> did both belieue and write) if it were to be found. Much like perhaps our ALPHABET and PRYMER, in the <hi>Amalthean Vatican</hi> of Sir THOMAS BODLEY at OX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORD, laid vp amongſt others, though <hi>Cardinall Pooles</hi> 2000. Crownes miſt it at <hi>Cracouia,</hi> when writing into <hi>Poland</hi> he ſent for it thither. <hi>[Igno.]</hi> Your reaſons haue won me to conceiue ſo wel of <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> that I am almoſt perſwaded, by <hi>Tullyes</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to wiſh my ſelfe a <hi>Customer. [Cuſtomer.]</hi> No, no, not yet, reſerue your ſelfe for better Times and Place; for Times doe alter, and we with the Times: yet, the <hi>Bonds</hi> onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wherewith <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> are tide, and diſgraces of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I could wiſh not you onely, but any Man beſides, not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, but altogether a <hi>Customer,</hi> though but for three yeares. And for my part at leaſt, now after twenty yeares and more, ſo <hi>Trafficke</hi> had her <hi>Staples,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> his <hi>Bullion,</hi> and his <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> but their credit,<note place="margin">The CVSTOMERS extraordinary zeale to his COVNTRIES Proſperitie, and SOVERAIGNES ſetled Happineſſe.</note> that their Functions doe require: I would willingly reſigne my Patent and my Place, and in this kind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more vnhappy then my Fellowes. But ſo it is &amp; muſt be, till <hi>Truth</hi> be better knowne, which <hi>Experience</hi> will lay open; For if our foreſaid L. <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> or the ſame <hi>Marcus Tullius Cicero,</hi> that out of zeale vnto his Country, fell out with <hi>Marcus Cato,</hi> his neereſt deereſt Friend, in defence of <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> were now to plead their caſes, hee might well deplore their States, but would hardly be a <hi>Cuſtomer,</hi> in the <hi>Out-Ports</hi> at leaſt. Or if Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> himſelfe, that ſometimes was a <hi>Cuſtomer,</hi> were now againe aliue, he might wonder to ſee, that it would not be enough to be an honeſt Man, no not a Chriſtian, were hee <hi>Kentiſh</hi> bred and borne, if the Name of a <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> were once but caſt vpon him.</p>
            <p>But ô thoſe <hi>Aſian</hi> warres, aboue all that hath beene ſpoken by <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> ſo feelingly deplored, &amp; wiſely ſet down, fatall both to <hi>Publicans,</hi> together with the <hi>Emperours,</hi> and the <hi>Empire</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and other <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> with their <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi> For the <hi>Truth</hi> indeed is this,<note place="margin">
                  <p>As <hi>M. Aurelius</hi> ſhewes plainely, how the Conqueſt of <hi>Aſia</hi> laid the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Romain Empires</hi> fatall ruine, by tranſporting <hi>Iewiſh Vſury</hi> (with other Sins and Vices) from IERVSALEM to ROME: ſo read in the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> what <hi>England</hi> gained, and <hi>Edward</hi> the third got in belaying the Conqueſt of <hi>France</hi> at ſo high a rate, as the loſſe of all his <hi>Staples,</hi> for paſſage onely tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>Flanders</hi> thither: namely, by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting the <hi>Staple</hi> of <hi>Kent</hi> firſt from <hi>Sandwich</hi> to <hi>Bruges,</hi> for fifteene yeares: and after, from <hi>Canterbury</hi> to <hi>Calis;</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as firſt the <hi>Golden fleeces</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> became the <hi>Trophees</hi> of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and ſo continues: ſo after, as our <hi>Mynes</hi> were tranſported, our <hi>Mints</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed (for ſhaddowes by Nature, muſt mooue with their Bodies) and <hi>England</hi> forſt by <hi>Statutes,</hi> to draw ouer her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſtill from <hi>Callis,</hi> hauing loſt both her <hi>Mints</hi> and <hi>Mines</hi> at home.</p>
                  <p>But with the loſſe of <hi>Callis,</hi> how our <hi>Staples</hi> and our <hi>Trafficke</hi> in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> (neither fixt nor well vſed, but wandring vp and downe) maintained tumultuous wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es there, for fifty yeares and more, and by warming their blood ſtill, ſtrau'd our owne at home; Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience beſt can tell.</p>
               </note> that after IVDEA by Conqueſt ſubdued, was made a <hi>Prouince</hi> to the <hi>Empire,</hi> and IERVSALEM it ſelfe became ſubiect to ROME, amongſt many other enormities which thoſe Warres did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get; <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> turn'd to <hi>Subſidies,</hi> and <hi>Subſidies</hi> into <hi>Taxes, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posts</hi> and <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> out of Ielouſie, ſuſpition, <hi>Couetiſe,</hi> and <hi>Pride; Cuſtomes,</hi> by <hi>Searchers</hi> and <hi>Informers,</hi> were made cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Diuine <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to keepe the <hi>Iewes</hi> vnder, who in reſpect of themſelues, cald all the Worlde <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and hauing loſt their former freedome, in hatred of their <hi>Tributes,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> now and <hi>Customers</hi> liue ſtill together, held <hi>Customers</hi> for <hi>Ethnickes,</hi> and <hi>Searchers</hi> greateſt Sinners, by the name of <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans,</hi> for that encluded eyther, as well thoſe of themſelues, as ſent thither from <hi>Rome;</hi> namely, Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi> and <hi>Zacheus.</hi> And as their <hi>Adiuncts</hi> then, cald <hi>Socij, Predes</hi> and <hi>Mancipes,</hi> like <hi>Comptrollers, Surueyers,</hi> and <hi>Searchers</hi> now, pretending all <hi>Tributes</hi> (which <hi>Tully</hi> cald <hi>Aurum Iudaicum</hi>) but enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding moſt themſelues, beeing accomptable for nothing, were at all hands called <hi>Publicans Cathexochen;</hi> ſo now, and at this day be the Sinners, who ſhall, will, or can; the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> name and perſon beares all the blame, as the <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> couer all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> are not truſted, nor the <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> rightly known. And as after <hi>Tully</hi> all diſſolued into <hi>Farmes, Publicans</hi> being <hi>Farmers,</hi> and <hi>Adiuncts</hi> with others; euen <hi>Publicans</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Farmers</hi> and <hi>Publicans</hi> to, which by the <hi>Grace</hi> of GOD I neuer meane to do. <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> Are <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> then Duties of ſo great import, as you ſet them forth? I pray you for my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deſcribe them vnto me, and ſhew me what they bee, ſince <hi>Impoſtes, Impoſitions,</hi> and <hi>Subſidies</hi> to, are all ſtiled <hi>Cuſtomes. [Cuſtomer.] Cuſtomes</hi> of themſelues, and properly taken, are but ſmall and eaſie payments of ready current <hi>Money,</hi> by <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Subiects,</hi> or <hi>Strangers,</hi> for ſuch Stapled Commodities, as for <hi>Art</hi> as well as <hi>Nature,</hi> beeing orderly bought and ſold, and for <hi>Number, Weight,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> ſufficiently cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, with the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Staple</hi> Seales, and ſpeciall Certificats to <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> at their <hi>Ports</hi> come warranted thither, for our <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes</hi> onely <hi>Homage,</hi> as Lorde of all the <hi>Fee,</hi> before they croſſe the Seas, and our Countries credit. Whereby you may perceiue howe all our happineſſe, for <hi>Matter, Perſons, Place, Order,</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> concurre in this one word <hi>[Customes]</hi> and how our <hi>Customes</hi> including our <hi>Soueraignes Honor,</hi> and <hi>Subiects Wealth,</hi> that <hi>Honeſtum</hi> and <hi>Vtile</hi> may ſtill goe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; do preſuppoſe <hi>Money.</hi> Now <hi>Money</hi> points at <hi>Mints, Mints</hi> worke by <hi>Bullion,</hi> and <hi>Bullion</hi> argues <hi>Mines,</hi> Artificiall or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall. But <hi>Mines</hi> by Nature, as <hi>England</hi> neuer had, her <hi>Mines</hi> Artificiall haue euer beene her <hi>Staples,</hi> where her <hi>Load-stones</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
were preſerued, whoſe vertues ſtill attractiue by the benefit of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> affoord more <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi> then the Mines of the World; ſo that, thus ſtill in <hi>England</hi> the caſe hath euer ſtood. Without <hi>Staples,</hi> no <hi>Elixars</hi> nor <hi>Loadstones</hi> at all: No <hi>Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones,</hi> no <hi>Bullion:</hi> No <hi>Bullion,</hi> no <hi>Mints:</hi> No <hi>Mints,</hi> no <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney:</hi> and no <hi>Money,</hi> no <hi>Customes:</hi> Which being but compared to <hi>Quitrents</hi> or <hi>Tythes,</hi> are conuertible, or reciproke and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude in this wiſe. As no <hi>Quitrents</hi> know no <hi>Mannors;</hi> and no <hi>Tythes,</hi> no <hi>Churches:</hi> ſo no <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> no <hi>Staples:</hi> and no <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> no <hi>Customes:</hi> and ſo by conſequence no orderly <hi>Traffique,</hi> or no <hi>Traffique</hi> at all. Now if <hi>Trafficke</hi> either faile, or be any waies diſturb'd; how ſhall MAIESTY be ſeene, or auoyde at the leaſt to bee dangerouſly eclipſed? And how ſhall SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNT ſubſiſt? And if both of theſe two faile, for they ſtand and fall together; How ſhall <hi>Subiects</hi> euer looke or hope to be happy? <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> I ſee and perceiue that <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> growes from <hi>Staples</hi> by <hi>Traffique,</hi> as Honey doth from <hi>Bees</hi> in Hiues. But how doth <hi>Trafficke</hi> depend and ſubſiſt by <hi>Staples</hi> ſo needfully. <hi>[Customer.]</hi> As <hi>Religion</hi> doth by <hi>Temples,</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> by her Courts <hi>Distributiuely,</hi> for euen <hi>Iustice Commutatiue,</hi> is the ſame wee call <hi>Traffique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know there are ſundry that weene themſelues wiſe, who by meere ſpeculation pretending loue to <hi>Traffique,</hi> cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>Staples</hi> for feare of our ſhipping. And ſome that hold <hi>Temples</hi> to be needleſſe for <hi>Religion,</hi> thinking if al <hi>Creekes</hi> were <hi>Head-Ports,</hi> without Limb or Member, it were happy for <hi>Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke;</hi> as if the cheriſhing of Oakes were the way to hinder Timber, and ſpoyle all our Trees, and the rayſing of our Hiues againe, were to ſpill all our Hony, and ſmother all our <hi>Bees.</hi> Or as if our ſtatelieſt <hi>Byſhopprickes</hi> might well be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by poor Schollars and Clarks, and our skilfulſt Roads and Hauens, were fit for no ſhipping but Boates and ſmall Barkes. But ſend ſuch to <hi>Antycira</hi> to purge their franticke folly. <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> by reaſon and <hi>Religion</hi> both, reioyce in their harts to ſee GOD in his Temples, the <hi>Beauty</hi> of his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> Cathedrallie: and in regard of their <hi>Customes,</hi> wiſh to ſee the KING in the Seates of his <hi>Honour Commutatiuely,</hi> by crying ſtill for <hi>Staples.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>That as <hi>GOD</hi> by his Goodneſſe and Truth doth direct vs,</l>
               <l>whoſe Mercy endures for euer:</l>
               <l>And his loue with his fauour, ſeemes ſtill to protect vs,</l>
               <l>for his Mercy endures for euer.</l>
               <l>So our <hi>Traffique</hi> by <hi>Staples</hi> in temper againe,</l>
               <l>ſince his Mercy endures for euer:</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Ports</hi> with their <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> might chant it amaine,</l>
               <l>that his Mercy endures for euer.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>[Ignorance.]</hi> It ſeemes you liue in hope ſtill, to find out your <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> and ſo to be happy. <hi>[Cuſtomer.]</hi> In working thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, <hi>Quo fato quidem neſcio, ſed non fine Numine,</hi> as my hope and comfort is, ſince <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> cals me forward, I haue cauſe to bee weary, and am almoſt tyred; yet I cannot diſpaire in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of <hi>Religion,</hi> whoſe Temples vpright, ſtill make her to flouriſh: And ſeruing at the <hi>Altar,</hi> if I may but liue thereby, I ſhall hold out the better. For when all Churches were infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie, none ſtood for <hi>Truth</hi> but ATHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NASIVS all alone; the World againſt Him, and He againſt the World, with the Emperours diſpleaſure, and hazzard of his life, whoſe Doctrine notwithſtanding, is a part of our <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie,</hi> and now taught for our <hi>Creede;</hi> ſuch is the power of conſtancy and <hi>Truth.</hi> And there was a time likewiſe, when the whole Chriſtian World was all ſet on fire, kindled by diſputes, and diſtracted by opinions, about the <hi>Head</hi> of the Church Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, Apoſtolikely Catholike, and ſome points of <hi>Religion,</hi> wherin <hi>Truth</hi> found few fauorers and vnfained friends indeed, but the zealous endeuors of an humble minded <hi>Fryer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">LVTHER.</note> and who could then haue thought, or any waies beleeued, that againſt ſuch mighty enemies and ſtrong oppoſitions, ſo weak a Man &amp; means ſhold euer haue preuailed; but <hi>Magna ſemper veritas, preualuit &amp; preualebit:</hi> to GODS eternall <hi>Glory,</hi> our <hi>Neighbors</hi> daily comfort, &amp; our Kingdoms <hi>Happines,</hi> aboue al parts of the World, eyther publike or priuate. And doth not the like euen now (I ſay now) by the Truce in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> offer it ſelfe in Iuſtice, to helpe vs againe to our owne <hi>Home-borne, Free-borne Traffique,</hi> that cryes but for paſſage, and deſires to be releeued from the <hi>Pride</hi> of <hi>Anwarpe,</hi> the <hi>Ingratitude</hi> of <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> from the <hi>Taxes</hi> of <hi>Flanders, Impostes</hi> of <hi>Italie,</hi> and <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bargoes</hi> of <hi>Spaine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What though thoſe Workes and nine bookes of SIBYLS (whereof three were dearely bought,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The <hi>Sybils</hi> wrote 9. Bookes of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil Gouernment,</hi> ſo highly valued as none durſt buy them Of which <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus</hi> at laſt bought three, and gaue as much for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the nine altogether were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly eſteemed at <list>
                        <item>1. The Cuſtomers APOLOGY.</item>
                        <item>2. His REPLY or ſecond <hi>Apology.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. His CAVTION again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſ extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity by Farmers.</item>
                        <item>4. His true vſe of PORT BANDES.</item>
                        <item>5 His ALPHABET and PRIMER for orderly Commerce.</item>
                        <item>6. His <hi>Acroamata</hi> for <hi>Bullion</hi> at <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. His Anſwere prepared about <hi>Bands</hi> of <hi>Employments,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>8. His <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>9. His <hi>Cuſtomers Accompt,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſaide Myſtery.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </note> and carefully preſerued by <hi>Tarquine</hi> the elder) bee all burnt vp and gone, by <hi>Stillico</hi> that Traytor?</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ne tantum Patrijs ſaeuiret Proditor Armis,</l>
               <l>Sancta Sybillinae fata cremauit Opis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>We haue the BIBLE and NEVV-TESTAMENT, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone and of themſelues are able and ſufficient to ſhew the way to happineſſe to all that are not obſtinate, and deſpiſe their owne ſaluation. Beſides nine workes yet extant of a <hi>Cuſtomers beſt endeuours,</hi> as fit for our purpoſe perhaps, as thoſe were.</p>
            <p>Yea, what though that Heathens AGROAMATA of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Doctrine, ſo grauely diſcuſt, and attentiuely heard, were ſo richly rewarded, with <hi>Talents</hi> of Gold, and ours not regarded? <hi>Non eſt mortale quod opto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>Nay, what though, euen TVLLY-DE-REPVBLICA (which, learned men ſo wiſh for, and Cardinall POOLE ſo ſought for, euen with the loſſe of all his Crownes) be held for forlorne, and no where to bee found? Our ALPHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BET is extant (as fit for <hi>Great-Britain</hi> as that for the <hi>Romans</hi>) and of all to bee ſeene in the <hi>Amalthaean Vatican</hi> of our late TARQVINIVS PRISCVS,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Thomas Bodlies</hi> Library at <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </note> whoſe <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Loue</hi> to lerning in the Kingdome of the <hi>Muſes,</hi> deſerues a golden Crowne. And this is more my comfort. The light all they ſaw by, were but <hi>Glimſes</hi> of the beams of our moſt glorious SONNE. Their beſt <hi>Enthuſiaſmes,</hi> were but motions to <hi>Honeſty,</hi> from the ful &amp; free Infuſions of the SPIRIT of adoption, that ſanctifies all our wits, bleſſeth our endeuours, and illuſtrates my <hi>Theame.</hi> And their cleareſt waters but borrowed from the ſtreames of that euer-flowing FOVNTAINE, that runs ſo frankely, and ſerues our turnes ſo well. Beſides, the true Chriſtian Catholick <hi>Religion</hi> takes my part, whereof they could not tell.</p>
            <p>For this our <hi>Traffick,</hi> being nothing elſe but a frank and free-barring of one good thing for another, or a buying and ſelling of <hi>Vendible Wares</hi> for ready Gold and Siluer betweene <hi>Subiects</hi> and <hi>Allies,</hi> at <hi>Places</hi> conuenient, according to the <hi>Rules</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciproke Commerce, generally intending al <hi>Honor</hi> vnto <hi>Kings,</hi> and all Wealth to <hi>Common-weales,</hi> doth plainly lay open vnto ſuch as liſt obſerue them, all thoſe fiue Vowelles in twice fiue ſubſtantiall words, that makes vs all to ſpeak both for 1. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>u. u.</hi> KING and PRINCE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>v.</hi> PRIVY-COVNCELL.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>w.</hi> COMMON-WEALE.</p>
               </note> 2 <hi>Perſons.</hi> 3. <hi>Place.</hi> 4. <hi>Order.</hi> 5. <hi>End;</hi> and ſound the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of all our 1. <hi>Liuings.</hi> 2. <hi>Liberties.</hi> 3. <hi>Liues.</hi> 4. <hi>Honors.</hi> and 5. <hi>Peace</hi> of our <hi>Land.</hi> For the firſt being put for <hi>a.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſounds <hi>e.</hi> The third ſtands for <hi>i.</hi> And the fourth for <hi>o.</hi> But the fift points out <hi>u.</hi> &amp; <hi>u.</hi> (SIRS) and <hi>v.</hi> my <hi>Lords, <hi>w.</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which ioyes me moſt, and reuiues my Spirits withal, is this.<note place="margin">This points to a Parleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> wiſh and hope for (yet in very good time) for the KINGS fixed Honor, and States proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, howſoeuer Guilt, Feare, or Ignorance ſeeme to doubt or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wade it.</note> When CASTOR came alone to the top of our <hi>Maſt,</hi> &amp; POLLVX did but follow, I had cauſe to doubt the weather; but now CASTOR and POLLVX, the Gods of our Seas, that are able and powerfull to warrant our <hi>Trafficke,</hi> comming both againe togither, doe boade vs all good lucke; for the Winde turnd North, ſhewes the ſtormes almoſt gone; and skilful PALI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVRVS comming now to Port or Helme, obſerues himſelfe our Compaſſe, (bidde <hi>Marchants</hi> ſtandes by) and giues both hope and comfort of attaining at laſt, to our long deſired <hi>Port</hi> that's now within a kenning, for the forelands apear. And our Barke is ſtrong enough to beare out all our Leakes: therefore be of good cheare, Saint <hi>George</hi> heeretofore, now GOD and CHRIST to borrow. Our <hi>Loadſtones</hi> proue as good as euer they wer, and our <hi>Compaſſe</hi> is true, therfore bear aloofe but a while, for feare of the <hi>Goodwines,</hi> by the cape of good hope, to the Iſland of <hi>Exchange,</hi> the Hauen of all ſafety, and Port of <hi>Peace</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:183763:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt,</hi> where <hi>Bounty</hi> now commaunds: For <hi>Reliquis tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm ſinus est &amp; ſtatio malefida carinis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But admit all this were nothing, which by way of <hi>Accompt</hi> hath beene hitherto ſet downe, or a <hi>Paradox</hi> at leaſt. Mine APOLOGY but Humor; my REPLY a Conceipt; mine AL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHABET, a Dreame; and my MYSTERY, but a leſt, becauſe a <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> only ſpeaks: yet if this be but beleeued, that <hi>Truth</hi> tels <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> doth ſuggeſt; namely, that looke what the Soule is to the actions of the body in ordering Members ſo, as to Nature ſeemes fit, for the good of the whol Man: the ſame is <hi>Trafficke,</hi> in diſpoſing <hi>Myſteries</hi> and <hi>Trades,</hi> to the benefit and behoofe of the whole <hi>Common-weal;</hi> thogh our ISIS be gone, and no Image of hir face, yet <hi>Aegeus</hi> our DAY STAR being riſen in hir place, and his hopefull THESEVS like the DAWNING of all <hi>Grace</hi> apearing in our eyes, ſo reuiues my dull SPIRITES, that I cannot diſpair, but liue ſtil in hope that the time may yet come, when this hearty zeale of mine, to my <hi>Soueraignes Honor,</hi> and <hi>Subiects Wealth,</hi> may bee better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and deſerue not only thankes and good wordes, but make all men confeſſe (<hi>Marchants</hi> at leſt) to owe as much to theſe my weake endeauours (if <hi>Trafficke</hi> may be valued) I ſay not as one <hi>Staple,</hi> one <hi>Mint,</hi> one <hi>Port,</hi> one <hi>Towne,</hi> or one City of LONDON; but many <hi>Staples,</hi> many <hi>Mints,</hi> many <hi>Ports,</hi> many <hi>Townes,</hi> and many <hi>Citties</hi> like LONDON, and all their Wealth is worth. Some few, priuate, particular, and preuenting perſons excepted, of whom I looke for no thankes, nor ſeeke any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</p>
            <p>Heere then to conclude and cloſe vp this <hi>Accompt,</hi> the ſum of all is this: Since all Men by Nature deſire to be happy, and <hi>Customers</hi> with the reſt, whoſe ſilence pleads for them by ſigns with their Pens, though themſelues dare not ſpeake. For <hi>Aſſai domanda eneor che mai non grida chi ben ſeruendo tace:</hi> there are but two wayes that lead to Felicity, <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Trafficke</hi> encludes either; the zeale whereof onely hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented all my ſtudies, almoſt conſum'd my ſelfe, and yet is the <hi>Motiue</hi> of all my beſt endeuors.</p>
            <p>For my Countries ſake therfore, in regard of publike good,<note place="margin">Summa Totalis.</note> and for no ſide reſpects, in beating out the way that leads vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> as I haue not bin ydle, &amp; haue not held my peace: ſo now for my <hi>Soueraignes</hi> ſake, KING IAMES and his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, as by Oath I am bound, in regard of his <hi>Bullion,</hi> for that is his right, and no Mans but his, by the Rules of <hi>Fixed Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> In regard of his <hi>Mints,</hi> for that is his <hi>Honor,</hi> &amp; no Mans but his, by the Rules of <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> In regard of his <hi>Exchange,</hi> for that is his <hi>Glory,</hi> and no Mans but his, by the Rules of <hi>Equity:</hi> And laſtly, for his <hi>Customes,</hi> in regard of his <hi>Homage,</hi> for that
<pb facs="tcp:183763:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is his profit, and no Mans but his, by the Rules of <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> as in <hi>Tithes,</hi> ſo in <hi>Tributes,</hi> that <hi>Honeſtum</hi> and <hi>Vtile</hi> may go orderly togither;<note place="margin">Honeſtum &amp; Vtile.</note> my Conſcience cannot reſt, but wiſh the returne of our HOME-BORNE-FREE-BORNE-TRAF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIQVE, at home againe in peace.</p>
            <p>And why ſhould I diſpaire, ſince as <hi>Religion</hi> hath her Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſo <hi>Iuſtice</hi> hath her Courts diſtributiuelie, whereby <hi>Truth</hi> with the time appeares to preuaile? And for <hi>Traffick</hi> at <hi>Staples</hi> by Nature ſtill admirable, and by Art made amiable, by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and Proportions, of <hi>Good, Better, Beſt,</hi> in <hi>Number, Weight,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> what can be leſſe ſpoken then a <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> hath ſaid?<note place="margin">The <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> zeale to the Honour and Happineſſe of <hi>Kings</hi> and Counſaile-Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, by <hi>Trafficke.</hi>
               </note> Namelie, that her Doctrine is heauenlie, and no waies fit for <hi>Emperickes,</hi> but KINGS and COVNCELL-TABLES. Her Seat and Reſidence the SOVERAIGNES owne boſome. Her voice well tunde, the Harmony of Chriſtian Kingdomes. To whom <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> owe Fealtie and Homage; the Meaneſt <hi>Subiects</hi> ſtill feeling her <hi>Care,</hi> and the Greateſt PRIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CES ſtill ſubiect to her <hi>Prouidence.</hi> And whom, both NOBLE and <hi>Ignoble</hi> admire and loue; as Norice and Prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rice of all their earthlie <hi>Happineſſe, Proſperities,</hi> PEACE, and Ioy. <hi>Ab Ioue principium (Reges &amp; Conſules ergo) Iouis omnia plena.</hi> GOD hath begun his part, by means of the <hi>Eucharict,</hi> let <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi> follow, by reſtoring their <hi>Exchange,</hi> that <hi>Vſury</hi> with the <hi>Maſſe</hi> may be packt away for <hi>Rome,</hi> where <hi>Popery</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing MAIESTY for want of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and SOVERAIGNTY finding no place nor meanes to ſubſiſt, for want of <hi>Truth;</hi> the POPE with his <hi>Cardinals</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites</hi> each with other, may hide them in <hi>Vtopia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Cuſtomers Reſolution.</note> or <hi>Purgatory,</hi> chuſe whether, whilſt <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> and <hi>Christians,</hi> and <hi>Customers</hi> altogether, reſolue in their hearts to doe their beſt endeuours, <hi>To finde and hold fast Innocency, and take heede to that is right;</hi> for that at the laſt, and nothing elſe, brings <hi>Summa Summarum</hi> and all to perfect <hi>Happineſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">SVMMA SVMMARVM.</note> in one word to [PEACE.]</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His Confeſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note>Now GOD from whom all Holy thoughts, and beſt endeuours grow,</l>
                  <l>Make me poſſeſſe that perfect PEACE the World cannot beſtow:</l>
                  <l>And that which of my ſelfe I can by Merits no way gaine,</l>
                  <l>Grant that thy GRACE by Faith and Workes may helpe me to obtaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His Prayer and Thankeſgiuing. Pſal. 4.</note>O GOD. that art my righteouſneſſe, Lord heare me when I call,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt ſet me at liberty, when I was bond and thrall:</l>
                  <l>Haue mercy Lord therefore on me, and grant me my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>For vnto thee vnceſſantly, to cry I will not reſt.</l>
                  <l>O Mortall Men how long will ye, the Glory nf God deſpiſe?</l>
                  <l>Why wander ye in vanity, and follow after lies?</l>
                  <l>Know ye that good and godly Men, the Lord doth take and chuſe,</l>
                  <l>And when to him I make my plaint, he doth not me refuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183763:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Sinne not but ſtand in awe therefore, examine well your heart,</l>
                  <l>And in your Chambers quietly, ſee you your ſelues conuert.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Greater Sort</hi> craue worldly goods, and Riches do imbrace,</l>
                  <l>But Lord grant me thy countenance, thy fauour and thy Grace:</l>
                  <l>For thou thereby ſhalt make my heart, more ioyfull and more glad,</l>
                  <l>Then they that of their SILKES and WINE, ſo great increaſe haue had.</l>
                  <l>In PEACE therefore lye downe will I, taking my reſt and ſleepe,<note place="margin">His QVIETVS-EST.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For thou alone wilt me (O Lord) alwaies in ſafety keepe.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>ANd heere to ſhut vp all by way of Remembrance,<note place="margin">His ſhort <hi>Memorandum</hi> of the whole Accompt.</note> in <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuam Rei memoriam,</hi> for our SOVERAIGNES ſpeciall <hi>Honor,</hi> his Loyall <hi>Subiects</hi> good, and <hi>Kingdomes</hi> proſperitie: Since nothing can preuail but <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> from GOD, and <hi>Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> from KINGS, to make <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All, Happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let TRAFFIQVE be releeued,</l>
                  <l>Of GOODNES long depreeued,</l>
                  <l>And TRVTH be ſtill beleeued,</l>
                  <l>That SVBIECTS may be bliſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For TRAFFIQVE out of thrall,</l>
                  <l>Makes KINGS be ſeene of all,</l>
                  <l>What ere to POPES befall,</l>
                  <l>And SOVERAIGNES to ſubſiſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>In the meane time, for <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> diſcharge of all Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſt and to come, againſt <hi>Ignorance</hi> and her Fellowes, in that which hath bin ſaid, by the Law of Nature and Nations both. <hi>Imputari non debet, Ei per Quem non ſtat ſi non facit quod per ipſum eſt faciendum.</hi> The reaſon being currant withal, <hi>Quia culpa caret, Qui fit &amp; prohibere nequit.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>For,</hi> In Magnis voluiſſe ſat eſt, ſint caetera Diuum,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And,</hi> Magna Magnus perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>DEVS.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO: MILLES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
